<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>paulolivier.dehaye.org</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/</link><description>Opinions are my own</description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Oct 2014 22:21:39 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Networked scholars placeholder post</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/networked-scholars-placeholder-post.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;This is my placeholder post for #scholar14, a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.networkedscholars.net/"&gt;course for networked scholars&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>scholar14</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/networked-scholars-placeholder-post.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 12 Oct 2014 20:20:01 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>MOOCs, journalism and digital disruption</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/moocs-journalism-and-digital-disruption.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you missed today's &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ccourses?src=hash"&gt;#ccourses&lt;/a&gt; discussion on &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/privacy?src=hash"&gt;#privacy&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/trust?src=hash"&gt;#trust&lt;/a&gt; you can watch it here: &lt;a href="http://t.co/JMkWGG09Ss"&gt;http://t.co/JMkWGG09Ss&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— DML Research Hub (@dmlresearchhub) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dmlresearchhub/status/520687983591448576"&gt;October 10, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;p&gt;I just listened to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://archive.org/details/RitchinBtfInterview"&gt;an audio interview&lt;/a&gt; conducted by Jonathan Worth for his &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://phonar.org.uk"&gt;photography course #phonar&lt;/a&gt;, back in 2013. The interviewee is &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fred_Ritchin"&gt;Fred Ritchin&lt;/a&gt;, a journalist, professor and author. Originally I was attracted to the interview because of a question asked by Ritchin during a #ccourses hangout about trust. He essentially asked how an entire profession (journalism) could rebuild trust with its audience once it was lost. It felt as if he was hoping educators could help give an answer that is eluding his profession.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have talked &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html"&gt;before on this blog&lt;/a&gt; of the parallels I see in Worth's approach in #phonar and mine with MOOC teaching. It looks like Ritchin can help explore these parallels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The older paradigm for photojournalists was to simply record events, with the hope—and frequently the expectation—that people and their governments would be moved to respond to the injustices pictured, as witnessed by the impact of certain images during the Civil Rights movement and the Vietnam War. Given evolving media and political climates, however, including the billions of images now available online from all kinds of sources, the purpose and effectiveness of media, in particular of visual journalism, has been called into question. Bending the Frame, by author and critic Fred Ritchin, addresses the new and emerging potentials for visual media to impact society. Also encompassing online efforts, uses of video, and a diverse range of books and exhibitions, this volume aims for as wide-ranging and far-reaching a discussion as possible, asking the critical question: how can images promote new thinking and make a difference in the world?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://aperture.org/shop/books/bending-the-frame-fred-ritchin-books#sthash.JKE7mMEM.dpuf"&gt;About&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Bending the Frame: Photojournalism, Documentary, and the Citizen&lt;/em&gt;, Fred Ritchin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, digital photography and the web have led to a complete rethink of the role of professional photographers in society, and a struggle now to find their relevance in the wider world. The interview is at times a litany of missed opportunities for the New York Times. Ritchin recalls experiments conducted by the editorial side of the New York Times, playing with new multimedia options. This was in 1994, and was instigated by the business side of the journal, actually, full of hope that this could lead to new revenues. Immediately of course this was squashed when all newspapers started making their content freely available on the web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ritchin's response then was to use this new media to show a new kind of story: instead of showing war, he would show peace. His test case was Bosnia, where he tried to construct a nonlinear narrative around the experience of a photojournalist arriving there, and convey some of the disorientation  and confusion of the fallout of an ethnic war. In constructing this narrative, he had to put the photographer back in the center, because of the need for multiple links between elements in different photographs. This was completely new territory for anyone: even the idea of clicking on an image had to be explained to the readers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
It opened up the idea of instead of the New York Times and the photographer telling you what is going on, you as a reader have to become a collaborator with them to figure out what is going on, because in fact the photographer does not really know what is going on. The New York Times does not really know what is going on. We are all piecing it together. We all have our own experiences and we could apply our own experiences to the situation.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work was submitted at the time for a Pulitzer price in public service, but immediately rejected because it wasn't on paper. He says it took many years "for institutions to investigate the new possibilities of digital, of telling stories differently, of understanding the world differently." He recalls his own thinking back then, that deviated sharply from this insitutional chokehold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
If this is a revolution in media, we have to think in revolutionary ways, we can't just do what we were doing before. And photography is very good at being reactive. It reacts well to situations. There is a war, we photograph it. Spectacular imagery. But I prefer a pro-active photography, one that says "We don't want a war to happen". How can we make images prevent war? Or minimize it. How can we minimize global warming? How can we do things before the bad stuff happens?&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, the institutions lost: there was a "collapse of the mainstream, which puts the marginal in the centre, as a new practice or rather an old pratice, but one we didn't want to acknowledge before." Finally, the old institutions have had to acknowledge that all those experimental ideas were going in the right direction. But in the twenty years interval, they have suffered drastically from the intrusion of many new players on their turf, leading to his original question about trust. How do bona fide journalist now regain the trust of the general public, in a new landscape where their credentials are often ignored? Ritchin himelf introduces some clues: through a reversal of roles, between the amateur embedded in a community, and the professional outsider coming to report about the community. In 2013, he sees the "integration of both as the greatest challenge in journalism right now".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is fascinating to me, and I can see many parallels with MOOCs and the institutional meddling at the frontline of online education. Photojournalism itself was born on the frontlines, with its founding fathers in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magnum_Photos"&gt;Magnum agency&lt;/a&gt;, a cooperative of photojournalists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
They didn't discuss photography in the founding years. They discussed the world. They were happy to have survived World War II. [..] They were very political. They were interested in the future of people. It wasn't the future of photography. They were interested in the future of people. And I appreciated that, because I think the point of photography is not to celebrate itself but the point of photography is to be useful in the world, to try to get us to a better place. And that's the way they were working. To me that's what the original spirit of Magnum was.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe we need a cooperative of MOOC educators?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Ritchin also talks about &lt;em&gt;horseless carriages&lt;/em&gt;, and the technological determinism that prevents us to see unintended consequences of inventions such as digital photography. And Magnum has built its &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/categories/social_machine.html"&gt;own social machine&lt;/a&gt; to crowdsource the metadata tagging of its archive, which has led to the find of a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.behind-the-enemy-lines.com/2011/06/crowdsourcing-and-discovery-of-hidden.html"&gt;hidden treasure&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>connected_course</category><category>crowdsourcing</category><category>mooc</category><category>phonar</category><category>social_machine</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/moocs-journalism-and-digital-disruption.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2014 23:39:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Coursera and Safe Harbour of student data</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The European Union and Switzerland have agreements on free trade with the United States. One of those is &lt;strong&gt;Safe Harbour&lt;/strong&gt;, which has &lt;strong&gt;drastic implication for privacy&lt;/strong&gt;. In principle, Safe Harbour is a good idea: it creates &lt;strong&gt;little (business) friction&lt;/strong&gt; but ensures some form of &lt;strong&gt;citizen oversight&lt;/strong&gt; over the fastest evolving areas of e-commerce, by &lt;strong&gt;enforcing transparency&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html#id4" id="id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. It is being heavily tested though: in light of the Snowden revelations, there is growing understanding that this data originally held for commercial reasons is also a leverage of power. Andrus Ansip, the European Commissioner for Digital Single Market (designate)  &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.euractiv.com/sections/innovation-enterprise/ansip-threatens-suspend-safe-harbour-data-agreement-us-308962"&gt;acknowledged&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bits.blogs.nytimes.com/2014/10/06/europe-digital-nominee-demands-stronger-u-s-data-rules/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; in his hearings to be confirmed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;When it comes to protecting data - safe harbors need to be safe. 
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/EPhearings2014?src=hash"&gt;#EPhearings2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Andrus Ansip (@Ansip_EU) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Ansip_EU/status/519165997673373697"&gt;October 6, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Safe Harbour is not secure. The Agreement has yet to live up to its name. [..] If the U.S. Government does not make a clear statement, we must consider suspending the Agreement&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—Andrus Ansip &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html#id5" id="id2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The developments around &lt;strong&gt;MOOCs have very serious consequences for privacy&lt;/strong&gt;. Dozens of European universities are working with US MOOC companies, spending lots, and ultimately contributing to data collection on millions of young EU citizens, all without clear purposes. There is very different cultural understanding across the Atlantic of the privacy protections of the relationships between platform and user, teacher and student and university and student. There are also very delicate (legal) constructions everywhere of what constitutes academic freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these ideas were extensively tested when I taught the class &lt;em&gt;Teaching goes massive: new skills required&lt;/em&gt; on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.coursera.org/course/massiveteaching"&gt;Coursera&lt;/a&gt;. Parts of this class were supposed to cover some of those issues, and explain directly to the students most concerned the privacy issues associated to Coursera's business models. Instead, I was &lt;strong&gt;censored&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;insulted&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;vilified&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;legally threatened&lt;/strong&gt;, and Coursera used &lt;strong&gt;false, misleading or deeply intrusive&lt;/strong&gt; data held about the course or me to get my employer to launch a disciplinary procedure against me (as even &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2014/07/15/after-massiveteaching-questions-about-mooc-quality-control"&gt;hinted to a newspaper&lt;/a&gt;!). On top, of course, my students have been left in the dark. And I have lost access to my course materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.coursera.org/about/privacy"&gt;Safe Harbour is a recourse here&lt;/a&gt; for me (as it is to any European student on Coursera). I have submitted a request to Coursera, if only to get back access to the material created.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving forward, Ansip has decided to follow a suggestion of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://juliareda.eu/en/"&gt;Julia Reda&lt;/a&gt;, a Pirate Party MEP, and host an online town hall meeting as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Watch &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/EU_Commission"&gt;@EU_Commission&lt;/a&gt; vice-presidency candidate &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Ansip_EU"&gt;@Ansip_EU&lt;/a&gt; agree to answer users' questions online: &lt;a href="https://t.co/ppTkzwojmi"&gt;https://t.co/ppTkzwojmi&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ephearings2014?src=hash"&gt;#ephearings2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Julia Reda (@Senficon) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Senficon/status/519179686967246849"&gt;October 6, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;p&gt;This hearing will take place soon, let's see what Coursera will have responded by then... &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html#id6" id="id3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let me know what should be on my "to-do-list" for the next 5 years – on Wed, Oct 15 from 11 -12 am. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/AskAnsip?src=hash"&gt;#AskAnsip&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Andrus Ansip (@Ansip_EU) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Ansip_EU/status/520593695029334016"&gt;October 10, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id4" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html#id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Let's say a US company wants to do business in the EU. The EU, well aware of dangers associated with big data businesses, is concerned about the privacy of its citizens. At the same time, it does not want to hamper innovation. The solution found with Safe Harbour is to enforce a &lt;strong&gt;series of privacy principles&lt;/strong&gt;,  as listed on the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Safe_Harbor_Privacy_Principles"&gt;Wikipedia page&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;&lt;li&gt;Notice - Individuals must be informed that their data is being collected and about how it will be used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choice - Individuals must have the option to opt out of the collection and forward transfer of the data to third  parties.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Onward Transfer - Transfers of data to third parties may only occur to other organizations that follow adequate data protection principles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Security - Reasonable efforts must be made to prevent loss of collected information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data Integrity - Data must be relevant and reliable for the purpose it was collected for.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Access - &lt;strong&gt;Individuals must be able to access information held about them&lt;/strong&gt;, and correct or delete it if it is inaccurate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enforcement - There must be effective means of enforcing these rules.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id5" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html#id2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Ansip is also former Prime Minister of Estonia, a country very much ahead in everything digital. One can even &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ibtimes.co.uk/estonia-first-country-offer-e-residency-digital-citizenship-1468766"&gt;become e-citizen there and get digital residency&lt;/a&gt;, with minimal requirements.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id6" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html#id3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Not very promising actually: within a few minutes of my original email, I got a canned message back sending me to assistance forums. I replied that this was not an answer to my request, and got the same canned message once again... Possibly I am the first Coursera user to make use of Safe Harbour.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;</description><category>connected_course</category><category>coursera</category><category>privacy</category><category>trust</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2014 18:33:34 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>MOOC research proposal, using crowdsourcing</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/mooc-research-proposal-using-crowdsourcing.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;In April 2014, I submitted a research proposal &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/mooc-research-proposal-using-crowdsourcing.html#id2" id="id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. Its title is &lt;em&gt;Engineering Discovery in Mathematics&lt;/em&gt;, after the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.amazon.com/Reinventing-Discovery-New-Networked-Science/dp/0691148902"&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Reinventing Discovery&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://michaelnielse.org"&gt;Michael Nielsen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposal is in two part, an &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://user.math.uzh.ch/dehaye/ERC/ExtendedSynopsis_Dehaye.pdf"&gt;Extended Synopsis&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://user.math.uzh.ch/dehaye/ERC/ResearchPlan_Dehaye.pdf"&gt;Research Plan&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main goal (project Z) of this four year proposal is to formalise mathematics. This is utterly unrealistic, and of course is to be considered a beacon very very far in the distance. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/paul-bernays-lectures-at-eth-zurich.html"&gt;Fields medalist Voevodsky suggests a 500 year horizon&lt;/a&gt; for this! To pile on to the difficulty of doing this, Thomas Hales explains his motivation of embarking on a formal proof of his own result, the proof of the Kepler conjecture. The background is that his paper had been accepted in one of the most prestigious mathematics journal, but conditionally on the grounds that his computer-generated proof was so complex that it could not be verified by even a team of 20 (very well trained) human referees:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In truth, my motivations for the project are far more complex than a simple hope of removing residual doubt from the minds of few referees. Indeed, I see formal methods as fundamental to the long-term growth of mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—Thomas Hales, Flyspeck project&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, mathematics and mathematicians are struggling to organise the information they produce, and the refereeing process will not be capable of responding to rapid advances in our capacities at theorem proving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why do I think my short four year proposal is interesting, alongside all those giants? Because it introduces a new idea in the picture, that of MOOCs. It is a fact that soon hundreds of students will be taking the same classes in parallel, and that graduate classes will be taken by dozens of students rather than handfuls. Also, professors in the more basic classes will start to collaborate more on content, and a formalisation effort can help in that direction. Admittedly, the proposal is not very specific, and exposes many ideas. I think the most promising avenue is in a bootstrapping process of the proofs, submitted as crowdsourced work in the context of a MOOC (with the expert explaining the material to formalise on video, say). Already &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://front.math.ucdavis.edu/1211.7012"&gt;it has been shown&lt;/a&gt; that a lot of the Flyspeck poject proofs can actually themselves be automated, and the smart introduction of human mathematician labor can help tighten all the feedback loops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, this is going to be hard work, far in the distance. In the near future the goals will be more limited, and will probably benefit from MOOC-based research efforts in other disciplines too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(This post also serves as an updated introduction to the "Connected Courses" course)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id2" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/mooc-research-proposal-using-crowdsourcing.html#id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;I have made a reference to it in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/what-i-am-doing-with-moocs-and-why-june-2nd.html"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;</description><category>connected_course</category><category>foundations</category><category>mooc</category><category>research</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/mooc-research-proposal-using-crowdsourcing.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2014 12:18:07 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What I am doing with MOOCs and why (June 2nd)</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/what-i-am-doing-with-moocs-and-why-june-2nd.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I gave a talk on July 2nd about MOOCs. The goal was to explain to interested individuals the different potential futures of MOOCs, informed with the perspective of a mathematician. A lot of what I say is undoubtedly naive, but this was four months ago, an eternity in the MOOC world. And in any case I prefer to be attacked for things I said in a talk setting at my own institution to colleagues rather than things I {reportedly, supposedly} said to students in a closed setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The title of my talk was &lt;em&gt;What I am doing with MOOCs and why&lt;/em&gt; (apologies for bad sound, one hour).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;iframe width="425" height="344" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/NCLHWaYxMyM?rel=0&amp;amp;hd=1&amp;amp;wmode=transparent"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;I gave this talk in anticipation of a conference co-organised the next day with Stanford in Zurich, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://user.math.uzh.ch/dehaye/edx_meeting.html"&gt;the first OpenEdX conference&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.openedx.org"&gt;OpenEdX&lt;/a&gt; is the platform that powers &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.edx.org"&gt;edx.org&lt;/a&gt;. This conference has now become a regular event, with the next one on the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://con.openedx.org/"&gt;Harvard campus&lt;/a&gt;. At the time of the conference, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/edx/edx-platform/wiki/Sites-powered-by-Open-edX/93583d8f92cf692766180eca247960294114af7a"&gt;24 separate installation sites were listed&lt;/a&gt; on the relevant Github pages, almost all of them in English. Four months later, the project now counts &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/edx/edx-platform/wiki/Sites-powered-by-Open-edX"&gt;47 sites&lt;/a&gt; all over the world, a significant progress! It also now has &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/edx/edx-platform/wiki/List-of-XBlocks"&gt;23 different publicly available Xblocks&lt;/a&gt;, which are extensions of OpenEdX to customise it to particular needs (only a couple had been released back then).
As I explain this in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://collab.switch.ch/p26oy3gl9aj/?launcher=false&amp;amp;fcsContent=true&amp;amp;pbMode=normal"&gt;first 4 minutes of this video&lt;/a&gt;, privacy issues are very significant in Switzerland, Europe, Quebec and the United States and motivated me to convene the workshop. This comes right after the Snowden scandals, and it is very hard for large actors outside the USA to trust a service like Amazon Web Services. A positive outcome was that it helped crystallise a need for separate service vendors, which edX then helped to get started. There are now eight different &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/edx/edx-platform/wiki/List-of-Open-edX-service-providers"&gt;commercial vendors&lt;/a&gt;, happily customising the platform to suit new needs.  The conference also helped a lot of local startups/nonprofits get a jump start in the MOOC space, such as &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.blue-planet-life.org/"&gt;Blue Planet Life&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Getting ready to rock the boat (literally) with &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/edXOnline"&gt;@edXOnline&lt;/a&gt; in Delft &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/FutureEDU?src=hash"&gt;#FutureEDU&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/StanfordOnline"&gt;@StanfordOnline&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://t.co/9W1T5bcZLg"&gt;pic.twitter.com/9W1T5bcZLg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— sefk (@sefk) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/sefk/status/474248230738595841"&gt;June 4, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;p&gt;A couple days later, I traveled to Delft to the edX Global Forum, to rock the boat there a bit as well. There was a panel on Open Source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/StanfordOnline"&gt;@StanfordOnline&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/edraak"&gt;@edraak&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/universite_num"&gt;@universite_num&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; XuetangX using Open edX to change the world. Inspiring! &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/FutureEDU?src=hash"&gt;#FutureEDU&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://t.co/QJdfb2DFi9"&gt;pic.twitter.com/QJdfb2DFi9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Wendy Cebula (@WendyCebula) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/WendyCebula/status/474558680315482112"&gt;June 5, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Single thing to take away about &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/OpenEdX?src=hash"&gt;#OpenEdX&lt;/a&gt; Platform? &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/universite_num"&gt;@universite_num&lt;/a&gt; - "&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/OpenSoure?src=hash"&gt;#OpenSoure&lt;/a&gt; is essential for innovation. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/FutureEDU?src=hash"&gt;#FutureEDU&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— edX (@edXOnline) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/edXOnline/status/474560155758387200"&gt;June 5, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;p&gt;George Siemens' keynote there was very impressive in that it touched on very similar topics to some of my intended goals. I was a bit disappointed however in the answer he gave to a question I asked at the end of his talk. It really did seem like noone had yet practically considered how MOOCs might change entire disciplines for research, or create new ones.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>coursera</category><category>crowdsourcing</category><category>gsiemens</category><category>mooc</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/what-i-am-doing-with-moocs-and-why-june-2nd.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2014 12:41:11 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Activating mathematical knowledge</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/activating-mathematical-knowledge.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;In 2011, when I applied to my current position as Swiss National Science Foundation Assistant Professor, I included an &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/Annex_Dehaye.pdf"&gt;Annex&lt;/a&gt; to the proposal, titled &lt;em&gt;Making data useful for mathematical collaboratories and the example of the LMFDB project&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;collaboratory&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/activating-mathematical-knowledge.html#id2" id="id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; is an organizational entity that spans distance, supports rich and recurring human interaction oriented to a common research area, and fosters contact between researchers who are both known and unknown to each other, and provides access to data sources, artifacts, and tools required to accomplish research tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://soc.ics.uci.edu/"&gt;Science of Collaboratories&lt;/a&gt;, SNF survey 2007&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Already then, I highlighted a significant evolution in mentalities since a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://soc.ics.uci.edu/"&gt;reference SNF survey&lt;/a&gt; of 2007. This trend was explained by Michael Nielsen in a TED talk at around the same time, also taking mathematics as basis for many of his examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;iframe width="425" height="344" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/DnWocYKqvhw?rel=0&amp;amp;hd=1&amp;amp;wmode=transparent"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the Annex, I make a distinction between &lt;em&gt;horizontal&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;vertical&lt;/em&gt; projects. &lt;cite&gt;Horizontal projects&lt;/cite&gt; are more infrastructure-like, &lt;cite&gt;with a wider mathematical audience, essentially the whole pure mathematical community&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
I would expect this difficulty in integrating new data to be the main cause of the lack of mathematical collaboratories. As such, it should be solved as a horizontal rather than vertical problem. From now on, I only discuss this problem, i.e. the creation of a flexible and coherent mathematical database starting from heterogenous data.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pushed to the extreme, one could see this problem as &lt;cite&gt;integrating all compiled knowledge in mathematics&lt;/cite&gt;, echoing a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/paul-bernays-lectures-at-eth-zurich.html#"&gt;description by Voevodsky&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was based around my experience for a few years with the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.lmfdb.org"&gt;LMFDB project&lt;/a&gt;, which is aimed at integrating lots of mathematical data in the general area of L-functions (two of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Millennium_Prize_Problems"&gt;Clay Millenium problems&lt;/a&gt; are in this area, the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Riemann_hypothesis"&gt;Riemann Hypothesis&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Birch_and_Swinnerton-Dyer_conjecture"&gt;Birch and Swinnerton-Dyer conjecture&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One interesting aspect of this annex is that it was, well, an annex. I knew including this as part of my main project could actually be hurtful and judged distracting to my main research proposal, since many of the ideas of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/research/consultations/science-2.0/consultation_en.htm"&gt;Science 2.0&lt;/a&gt; had not taken hold yet. Indeed, the Annex comes with a big disclaimer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
I have also described my more personal project, which is concerned with the integration of mathematical data for collaboratories. While I do not consider this project a mathematical project, I think it could be of great value to research in mathematics in general. I intend on pursuing it on the side as a service to the community, just as paper refereeing, outreach, CAS development, etc. I am only mentioning it here because of its (presumed) originality and wide audience.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One year later, I coorganised a workshop at Edinburgh. The topic was &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://aimath.org/pastworkshops/onlinedata.html"&gt;Online databases: from L-functions to combinatorics&lt;/a&gt;, and it was meant to start unifying two separate areas in this horizontal problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id2" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/activating-mathematical-knowledge.html#id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;A &lt;em&gt;portmanteau&lt;/em&gt; of collaboration and laboratory.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;</description><category>math</category><category>social_machine</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/activating-mathematical-knowledge.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2014 23:26:35 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Culture of humiliation</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/culture-of-humiliation.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I have learned a lot recently about online humiliation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monica Lewinsky's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.vanityfair.com/society/2014/06/monica-lewinsky-humiliation-culture"&gt;Vanity Fair piece&lt;/a&gt; was very insightful. Indeed, if anyone would know about being the victim of online shaming, it would be her. Interestingly, she shares that a new stage of horror for her was achieved when she understood the impact his scandal had on her family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In September of 2010, the culmination of these experiences began to snap into a broader context for me. A phone conversation with my mother shifted the lens through which I viewed my world. We were discussing the tragic death of Tyler Clementi. Tyler, you will recall, was an 18-year-old Rutgers freshman who was secretly streamed via Webcam kissing another man. Days later, after being derided and humiliated on social media, he committed suicide by jumping off the George Washington Bridge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My mom wept. Sobbing, she kept repeating over and over, “How his parents must feel … his poor parents.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was an unbearably tragic event, and while hearing of it brought me to tears, too, I couldn’t quite grasp why my mom was so distraught. And then it dawned on me: she was reliving 1998, when she wouldn’t let me out of her sight. She was replaying those weeks when she stayed by my bed, night after night, because I, too, was suicidal. The shame, the scorn, and the fear that had been thrown at her daughter left her afraid that I would take my own life—a fear that I would be literally humiliated to death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—Monica Lewinsky, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.vanityfair.com/society/2014/06/monica-lewinsky-humiliation-culture"&gt;Shame and Survival&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at the year, 2010, that's twelve years after the facts. A lot of time for a mom to suffer with weakened trust in her daughter that she would take on life, with its good and bad days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something else that crossed my path is a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mathbabe.org/2014/09/30/people-hate-me-i-must-be-doing-something-right/"&gt;post by Cathy O'Neil on her blog mathbabe&lt;/a&gt;, where she discusses some ways she has built a thick skin and maintains confidence in herself, even in the face of criticism that can get very personal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there’s one other thing I conclude when I piss people off: that I’m getting under their skin, which means what I’m saying is getting out there, to a wider audience than just people who already agree with me, and if that guy hates me then maybe 100 other people are listening and not quite hating me. They might even be agreeing with me. They might even be changing their minds about some things because of my arguments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I realize this sounds twisted, but when people hate me, I feel like I must be doing something right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One other thing I’ll say, which the article brings up. It is a luxury indeed to be a woman who can afford to be hated. I am not at risk, or at least I don’t feel at all at risk, when other people hate me. They are entitled to hate me, and I don’t need to bother myself about getting them to like me. It’s a deep and wonderful fact about our civilization that I can say that, and I am very glad to be living here and now, where I can be a provocative and opinionated intellectual woman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—Cathy O'Neil&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, the humiliation could get very deep in her psyche, but she makes her way of fighting it back very explicit. It's an utilitarian calculus, based on the scale of the positive impact she hopes to achieve versus the one negative comment she just had to face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She ends the piece with this powerful line:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Fuck yes! Let’s do this, people! Let’s have ideas and argue about them and disagree! It’s what freedom is all about.&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><category>connected_course</category><category>trust</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/culture-of-humiliation.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2014 21:37:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Building trust in #massiveteaching, through visuals</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;As part of the module on trust in &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.connectedcourses.net"&gt;Connected Courses&lt;/a&gt;, I would like to share some tricks that I have used to visually build trust across cultures. It was especially powerful for me to watch Jonathan Worth's video on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://phonar.org/2014/09/leveraging-you-why-in-answer-to-mike-wesch/"&gt;Leveraging your why&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html#id5" id="id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Worth offers that his "Why?" for #phonar is actually citizen journalism, and discusses a photo by John Stanmeyer, winner of the World Press Photo 2013 award.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this brings me back to, this is my ‘why?’ So this image is the winning image from the World Press Photo this year, by a photographer called John Stanmeyer, and this is why it annoys me so much. Because it’s by a photographer called John Stanmeyer. These are African immigrants standing on a beach, trying to get a phone signal before they jump in the water. Let me just get this right, “on the shore of Djibouti City at night raising their phones in an attempt to capture an inexpensive signal from neighbouring Somalia”. These are the people that aren’t in my class. They’re holding these smart devices which can all take pictures, and yet it takes a photographer from New York to bring it back and we can now talk about it.  What these people need is to be able to be trusted and to be heard, and these are the people that aren’t in the class. So this is my why, and this is my way marker, so this is definitely the best and most exciting thing that’s come out of my classes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://phonar.org/2014/09/leveraging-you-why-in-answer-to-mike-wesch/"&gt;Jonathan Worth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of my efforts with my &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.coursera.org/course/massiveteaching"&gt;Coursera course&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Massive Teaching: News skills required&lt;/em&gt; were some interesting blend of Worth's efforts in #phonar and in #connected_courses. Let's first consider the exact opposite of what I did. Relax, prepare some popcorn, and watch the following video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;iframe width="425" height="344" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/0rmJqQotDWo?rel=0&amp;amp;hd=1&amp;amp;wmode=transparent"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clealy this video exploits the elite university brand together with a lot of pixie dust to try to cement this elite brand even more. The "why?" of this MIT video certainly shows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as in Worth's #phonar course leading up to citizen journalism, I am hoping with parts of &lt;em&gt;Massive Teaching&lt;/em&gt; to enable some form of citizen-MOOCing, to create a small distributed network of video production, with no sacrifice on the quality of the education provided. My sidegoal was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to find the cheapest way to produce video, but to find a visual style that could appeal equally to institutions (even very elite) and lonely individuals anywhere in the world &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html#id6" id="id2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sidegoal was to make for a more homogeneous and egalitarian pool of video producers &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html#id7" id="id3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;, but it goes further. How do we enable anyone anywhere to build trust with &lt;strong&gt;connected diverse individuals&lt;/strong&gt; (a concept that I used in a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/moocs-as-inventions-chals14.html"&gt;recent talk&lt;/a&gt; and is obviously core to #ccourses)? Let's consider one of my videos, where the topic is precisely on tracking of individuals by large corporations, drawing parallels between educational analytics and AdWords style advertising.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;iframe width="425" height="344" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/qOCln176bM4?rel=0&amp;amp;hd=1&amp;amp;wmode=transparent"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;img alt="../crib.jpeg" class="align-right" src="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/crib.jpeg" style="width: 216.0px; height: 288.0px;"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note a few things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;&lt;li&gt;it uses easily findable DUPLO pieces &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html#id8" id="id4"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt; and paper cutouts;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I feel that using kids' toys produces emotional responses and increases trust;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my hands are there, and that makes the videos still personal (contrast with the expense at &lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:CEDE@EPFL"&gt;CEDE@EPFL&lt;/a&gt; for their &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=agbe9B5l_VI"&gt;invisible hand effect&lt;/a&gt;);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the production process is first audio, then video, and the two are completely separate (I replay the audio when filming the video). In this way I actually first write the transcript, record a reading, and then illustrate. It makes translations very easy: simply re-record the sound, at the pace of the video.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I designed a recording studio out of IKEA furniture pieces (a crib, for instance for a cage, so it is easy to attach camera, light, etc); IKEA is not cheap enough but it gives wide reach. I have confidence that this can be improved drastically, by posting on sites such as &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ikeahackers.net/"&gt;IKEAhackers&lt;/a&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I encouraged my students to do the same, by describing my process as throgouhly as possible (done here again);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;None of those cheap tricks are new, it is mere borrowing of on-the-street intelligence of High School teachers and the Maker movement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;As stated, one of the sidegoals was to enable anyone to do this, and for anyone to create trust with anyone else, without necessarily going through a central authority (like that provided by my Coursera course). For this purpose, I selected some articles to help guide students on what might build trust across cultural divides, such as &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.featureshoot.com/2013/03/photos-of-children-from-around-the-world-with-their-most-prized-possessions/"&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;, which clearly echoes the emotional response I was referring to earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what happened with &lt;em&gt;Massive Teaching&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, despite my best efforts it turns out that the fact that Coursera owned the channel was still &lt;em&gt;massively&lt;/em&gt; important. I might have made sure I owned all the content, and diluted as much as possible all ambient brands, I still needed Coursera for its reach (or at least I felt I did!). Going through them was not a smart way to challenge the general status quo in MOOCs, but the interesting paradox of #massiveteaching is that ultimately it is not the content that went missing, but rather the human (me, the instructor). The content was instead reinstated (well, actually only partially and with questionable motives), and I was unable to access the sources anymore, thereby losing some of my own content. This paradox was then compounded by further issues of trust and disinformation, where again access to communication channels was crucial. This account of course omits any of the students' perspectives, which must have been wildly different, depending on the activities they actually engaged in. With the instructor gone, only disaster was possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id5" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html#id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;He apparently himself was troubled by Mike Wesch's &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f_mcTLlG_wg&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be"&gt;fantastic talk&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;em&gt;Why we need a why&lt;/em&gt; (just making the chain of trust explicit here, as explained in the talk...)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id6" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html#id2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Judging from aggregate and individual feedback, that was achieved.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id7" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html#id3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;This echoes a parallel effort in academic publishing in some disciplines. Indeed, the refereeing process, which is a form of  authority and power, is done double-blind, to prevent reinforcement of biases. In mathematics the author of a submitted paper is not anonymous to the referee, which is arguably a problem.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id8" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html#id4"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;This in itself is very interestingly pain point. Can I use a DUPLO piece as a tool? I had &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dearrichblog.blogspot.ch/2014/05/cut-out-animations-moocs-and-copyright.html"&gt;to ask a lawyer for that&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;</description><category>connected_course</category><category>coursera</category><category>epfl</category><category>massive_teaching</category><category>mit</category><category>trust</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2014 11:38:58 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Security theatre, in airports and academia</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;When I was in Oxford, I had the best view in the world from my apartment. Off Merton Field, above Deadman's Walk onto &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christ_Church_Meadow,_Oxford"&gt;Christ Church Meadow&lt;/a&gt;. Uninterrupted grass landscape into the river, with rolling mist up to the river most mornings, &lt;em&gt;Lord of the Rings&lt;/em&gt;-style. In fact, Tolkien's office &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt;  the apartment upstairs, and I like to think the view inspired him. How come, in a cramped city like this, I could enjoy this same view decades later, centuries after the construction of the building I was living in? Well, because in the byzantine world of Oxford real estate, one college (ChristChurch) owned that land, while another owned grazing rights for cattle on it (forgot which, presumably Merton itself). Not that tourists would see cattle in that field: every year, the college with grazing rights would rent sheep for just one day, and move it there. The theory was that &lt;strong&gt;if they didn't exercise their right, they would legally lose it&lt;/strong&gt;, and the other college could build whatever they wanted there and ruin the view (Wikipedia mentions a road that was defeated). &lt;strong&gt;The pace at Oxford allowed to think this through: custom is built over centuries, and preserved with yearly activities.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why this long preamble?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was just in Goteborg for the #Chals14 conference, where a big part of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/moocs-as-inventions-chals14.html"&gt;my schpiel was that we should not succumb to the free-is-a-lie mantra of MOOCs&lt;/a&gt; and resist narrow views of the "Internet happening to education" (quoting George Siemens) based around technological determinism (quoting Evgeny Morozov). The afternoon session was in Swedish, so I was distracted and looking at Twitter. One person that I am following, Aral Balkan, tweeted this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Schiphol"&gt;@schiphol&lt;/a&gt; airport breaking EU law? They told me today that I could not opt of the full-body scanner.

&lt;a href="http://t.co/LfQ7k20ZLG"&gt;http://t.co/LfQ7k20ZLG&lt;/a&gt;

Via &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alloy"&gt;@alloy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Aral Balkan (@aral) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/aral/status/514736935978680320"&gt;September 24, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;p&gt;Balkan is a privacy advocate, who has been trying to raise the attention of people to the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://aralbalkan.com/notes/spyware-2.0/"&gt;Spyware 2.0 model&lt;/a&gt; employed by many companies now: in his Orwellian view, by offering free services, large corporations manage to convince us to give away all our data, so they can spy on us. He is leading the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ind.ie/manifesto"&gt;Indie-tech movement&lt;/a&gt; and peripherially (?) in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dmlcentral.net/blog/doug-belshaw/reclaiming-web-next-generation"&gt;Reclaim the Web movement&lt;/a&gt;, which also has declinations in the MOOC space (for instance with &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.wired.com/2014/09/known/"&gt;Known&lt;/a&gt;). His tweet got me pretty upset: a few years ago, Schiphol security classified a present from my mom, high quality Belgian chocolate paste, as a liquid. Back then I had checked, and legally they were, at least at the time, within their rights: individual employees have ultimate classification decision and chocolate paste is indeed a grey area. Still, because of an arbitrary decision by a person who gleefully threw away a present in the bin, I was forced to make-do with Swiss chocolate for a while, a clearly inferior proposition. If you want to dismiss my reasons to do this, you could say that I have a score to settle with Schiphol security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="../schiphol-hand.jpg" class="align-right" src="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/schiphol-hand.jpg" style="width: 540.0px; height: 360.0px;"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As luck would have it, on my flight back to Zurich from Goteborg, I was flying through Schiphol. On the very same day as Balkan. On top, the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/aral/status/514736935978680320"&gt;twitter thread&lt;/a&gt; had a ton of links to the relevant laws and websites, which were completely unambiguous. So all the work of retesting this more "scientifically" was cut out for me. In fact, &lt;strong&gt;one could argue that as an academic this is part of my work: to challenge institutions, spread knowledge, and contribute to society. These last two points made by many #Chals14 participants in the context of MOOCs.&lt;/strong&gt; I agree and generally take it seriously, especially living in a country where academic freedom is in the constitution (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.admin.ch/opc/en/classified-compilation/19995395/"&gt;Art. 20&lt;/a&gt;), where I am paid well to think, connect dots, etc. My view of academia might smack of arrogance and overreach, but bear with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few hours later, I myself landed in Schiphol, and got out of the transit area so I would have to intentionally get back through security. Since I could not print my legal backups on time, I had written on my hand the references to European regulation, 185/2010 4.1.1.10, a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://english.nctv.nl/themes/Counterterrorism/Security_and_civil_aviation/Security_Scan/FAQ_3.aspx"&gt;Dutch website URL&lt;/a&gt; and my plan:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;&lt;li&gt;refuse body scanner twice;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ask for an explanation of my rights;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;question the legality of their setup;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ask for the name of the person I was talking to;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ask to speak to a supervisor;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;iterate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I approached the security scanner, I looked around. Nowhere was it written that I could opt out. It was simply written that I should "feel free to ask questions". In Balkan's case, this was not helpful at all: since the security employee seems to have violated the law, Balkan couldn't just point to a sign and say he was wrong. The fact that there was no sign is, according to me, already a violation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before being screened by a security scanner, the passenger shall be informed of the technology used, the conditions associated to its use and the possibility to opt out from a security scanner&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/HTML/?uri=CELEX:02010R0185-20140409&amp;amp;from=EN"&gt;European regulation 185/2010&lt;/a&gt;, last line of article 4.1.1.10&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I had to finally talk to a Schiphol security officer and refuse the scanner, our interaction validated all the care I put in preparing this (and my general approach to a few similar challenge-the-authority projects I am involved in): his reaction was simply to ask me "Why?", why I was refusing. If there is one thing I learned this summer, it is to ask myself "Why?" and have a good answer to this question &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id9" id="id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. In this case, I could definitely answer it right away: "Because this is my right". &lt;strong&gt;By keeping a pretense of being citizen beta, I got the officer to volunteer the reason why he himself asked me "Why?"&lt;/strong&gt;: he volunteered "because sometimes people don't have the right information and think those are X-rays machines going through their skin" (regardless of the validity of the assertion, this is irrelevant to the fact that European law still allows me to opt out). I repeated that I was still refusing, and he said that was indeed my right, let me get around the scanner and started patting me down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To emphasize: &lt;strong&gt;this particular officer knew from the start that I it was my right to opt out&lt;/strong&gt;. While being perfectly courteous, he was making assumptions of my own ignorance, expecting to enlighten me with information about his very expensive, super advanced, and ultimately useless piece of technology &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id10" id="id2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;.  This &lt;strong&gt;explanation was supposed to somehow impress me, and lead me to willingly give away my own rights as a EU citizen (on EU soil)&lt;/strong&gt;. Given that I had gone to Goteborg to partly talk about technological determinism, with quotes of Zuckerberg on the evolving nature of privacy (including the "dumb fucks" quote, page 11 of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/goteborg-final.pdf"&gt;my slides&lt;/a&gt;), this was adding another layer of irony... There possibly was arrogance in my assumptions about my role as an academic, but certainly there were in the assumptions the officer was making: he didn't know about the Oxford sheep (presumably), all the necessary tabs opened and ready on my laptop, the writing on my hand, or the fact that I have quite a bit of experience with EU law (in the context of a separate private matter, I have previously encouraged the European Commission to initiate an &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/eu_law/your_rights/your_rights_en.htm"&gt;infringement procedure&lt;/a&gt; against my home country, Belgium. This is a &lt;em&gt;highly&lt;/em&gt; recommended and free legal avenue, available to any European citizen and maybe even resident).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once he had patted me down, and I had effectively gone through security, it was time to lay some of it out. Of course, I was quickly bounced around to the shift supervisor (who looked quite a bit senior). &lt;strong&gt;René was genuinely concerned and wanted to do the right thing: he took  pictures of my screen to get the relevant EU law lines and the original tweets. I told him to look for the #HelloSchiphol hashtag on Twitter. He thanked me.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But again he dismissed Balkan as just a tweeter among others, and I had to insist that he actually had many followers who care about privacy, that he is a big shot taking on Google, etc. I shouldn't have had to do that, and neither should it have mattered that I am a university professor, yet he did remark on the fact &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id11" id="id3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;. One can argue about my method and its transparency, but &lt;strong&gt;by playing dumb I actually got further&lt;/strong&gt; than just flashing legal printouts right away, since I now have &lt;strong&gt;one more data point on how Schiphol security officers respond to seemingly unprepared citizens concerned with airport security&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overall, this experience with Schiphol security was very positive, and I don't have a grudge against them anymore (provided they add relevant signage).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I want to contrast this with another security theatre incident &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id12" id="id4"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;, this time in the MOOC space. In September 5th &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://hackeducation.com/2014/09/05/beyond-the-lms-newcastle-university/"&gt;talk by Audrey Watters&lt;/a&gt; about the Learning Management System, she says this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The LMS was — is — designed as an Internet portal to the student information system, and much like the old portals of the Dot Com era, much like AOL for example, it cautions you when you try to venture outside of it. “ re you sure you want to leave AOL?” “Are you sure you want to leave the VLE?” “Aren’t you scared to be on the Web?” “There are strangers and strange ideas out there. Stay within the LMS! Stay within AOL!"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—Audrey Watters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There I was in Schiphol, facing the same security theatre to cross an actual physical portal.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watters might have been picking on older technologies (AOL and LMSes), but on that very same day (Sept 5th) the very same issues resurfaced for more modern technology, through Jonathan Mayer. Mayer is a lawyer, but also a PhD student at Stanford in computer science. Like Balkan, he is a big advocate for privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to come up with something that doesn’t count as market research or product improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.adexchanger.com/ad-exchange-news/privacy-advocate-jonathan-mayer-has-had-it-with-do-not-track/"&gt;Jonathan Mayer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far his research has cost &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mashable.com/2014/09/23/stanford-google-privacy-research/"&gt;Google 22.5M USD in fines&lt;/a&gt;, and what he has said in interviews has earned him the distinction of being &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.adexchanger.com/online-advertising/iab-mozilla/"&gt;labeled by the online advertising trade union&lt;/a&gt; a "Bolshevik of the Internet world" &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id13" id="id5"&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;.  He is 26.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He is also teaching a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.coursera.org/course/surveillance"&gt;course on Surveillance Law&lt;/a&gt; on Coursera (i.e. how the NSA, FBI, etc are legally accessing information about US citizens). A week before his course, he published a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://webpolicy.org/2014/09/04/a-funny-thing-happened-on-the-way-to-coursera/"&gt;blog post detailing some security flaws of Coursera itself&lt;/a&gt;. This was at his personal blog, but I assume he would consider this part of his work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Courserians, we are writing about a topic we take very seriously – user privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.google.com/?gfe_rd=cr&amp;amp;ei=L48jVJSRK6WG8QeY6oG4Cg#q=Brennan+Saeta"&gt;Brennan Saeta&lt;/a&gt; - Infrastructure Engineering, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blog.coursera.org/post/96686805237/response-to-reported-vulnerability-in-instructor-access"&gt;Coursera official blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coursera's response was given in a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blog.coursera.org/post/96686805237/response-to-reported-vulnerability-in-instructor-access"&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;. Slate has &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/future_tense/2014/09/05/coursera_is_patching_vulnerabilities_found_by_jonathan_mayer_a_surveillance.html"&gt;criticized that response&lt;/a&gt;, and smartly highlighted that any attack vector is good for a hacker. &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id14" id="id6"&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My team, Infrastructure, is taking a security class together, learning about cryptography because this is kind of relevant to security. So we try to improve ourselves and learn about best practices as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.google.com/?gfe_rd=cr&amp;amp;ei=L48jVJSRK6WG8QeY6oG4Cg#q=Nick%20Dellamaggiore"&gt;Nick Dellamaggiore&lt;/a&gt; - Infrastructure Lead, at Coursera Partners' Conference 2014 &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id15" id="id7"&gt;[7]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his talk at the Coursera Partners' Conference, Dellamaggiore has a background slide with the actual class that his Infrastructure team takes: Cryptography I, on Coursera of course, by Dan Boneh (ironically from Stanford). I went and looked at that course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;img alt="../crypto1.jpg" class="align-center" src="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/crypto1.jpg" style="width: 936.6px; height: 431.9px;"&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sure enough, 9 minutes into the first video, &lt;em&gt;social engineering&lt;/em&gt; is highlighted as nullifying the value of encryption and many other security methods. Given that Coursera superprofessors are supposed to be the best of the best (at their very very narrow discipline), and given the way academia works, I expect a fair share of Coursera professors to be greying a bit. &lt;strong&gt;I want to question how the decision was made by Coursera to think those professors could be trusted with this level of access&lt;/strong&gt;. I have had access to more information than the general public to help answer this question, but do not know enough at this time to actually answer it. &lt;strong&gt;I am not willing to reshare publicly the information I still have because of personal legal risk.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's great, but how do we keep data from falling in the wrong hands, say they try to access our physical machines in the cloud or our production databases or what not. So this slide is a little bit more technical, so bear with me, I will kind of go through it quicker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—Nick Dellamaggiore - Infrastructure Lead, a few seconds later&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This lack of public transparency is itself is a concern, in the context of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://asilomar-highered.info"&gt;Asilomar convention&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Without more transparency from Coursera on their data policies, I have genuine concern that Coursera itself is just using security theatre for commercial advantage&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id16" id="id8"&gt;[8]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case it is not clear at this stage, I still have a score to settle with Coursera, but I try to be a patient man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If someone’s not going to follow the practices, that’s something that society faces in general, and that’s why we have police and courts [..] In the academic world, we don’t need police and courts, but we have academic discipline, we have academic institutional standards, we have research standards. If people don’t comply with those, they do need to be deal[t] with. In our set of relationships, that’s between the university and the instructor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2014/07/15/after-massiveteaching-questions-about-mooc-quality-control"&gt;Vivek Goel&lt;/a&gt;, Chief Academic Strategist, Coursera and apparently also "&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blog.coursera.org/post/77181132056/welcome-vivek-goel-to-courseras-leadership-team"&gt;still a professor at the Dalla Lana School of Public Health and the Institute for Health Policy, Management &amp;amp; Evaluation&lt;/a&gt;"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goel is textually correct of course. But he is also intentionally misleading (by offering this generic quote in an article about a course that I ran). And he is also unintentionally short-sighted, for very many reasons. One is that he indeed reminds me of looking up the local rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The University of Zurich (UZH) is an institution with a strong commitment to the free and open pursuit of scholarship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scholarship is the acquisition, the advancement and the &lt;strong&gt;dissemination of knowledge in a methodological and critical manner&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To flourish, scholarship must be &lt;strong&gt;free from external influences, constraints and ideological pressures&lt;/strong&gt;. The University of Zurich is committed to &lt;strong&gt;unrestricted freedom in research and teaching&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Academic freedom calls for a high degree of responsibility, including &lt;strong&gt;reflection on the ethical implications of research activities for humans, animals and the environment&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.uzh.ch/about/basics/mission_en.html"&gt;University of Zurich's mission statement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another is that he has resorted to using innuendos. I can use my own too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We see all the platforms now really starting to talk about the social aspects [..] of learning, which come from the other theories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—The &lt;em&gt;Zuckerberg-wannabe of the higher education world&lt;/em&gt;, aka the &lt;em&gt;Chief-Academic-Strategist-formerly-known-as-an-academic&lt;/em&gt; aka Vivek Goel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't worry, the nickname is based on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://youtu.be/PCV5xBPoxnE?t=4m47s"&gt;actual data&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id9" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Deserves a shoutout to Kate Bowles and #ccourses for reminding me of the importance of this question.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id10" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;I claim this general technology is useless based on still unpublished research &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.wired.com/2014/08/study-shows-how-easily-weapons-can-be-smuggled-past-tsas-x-ray-body-scanners"&gt;announced last month&lt;/a&gt;. I was unprepared to enter that debate there with the security officer, not knowing exactly which model Schiphol was using. I suspect the officer was not ready either. The point is that we shouldn't have to, as this particular European law was drafted anticipating rapid evolution in this security field, both regarding threat detection and evasion.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id11" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;He only learned that at the very end, when I wrote #HelloSchiphol on my business card. There is, so far in my life, only one (repeated) instance where I have flashed the fact that I am a professor: apartment hunting in Switzerland, for which competition is so fierce that local society admits pretty much &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; move is fair. The fact that many academics pride themselves not to use business cards or Twitter show a profound lack of understanding of their own place in the physical and digital world: conversation with any other citizen is important and that might require using their medium.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id12" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id4"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;To use the language of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.schneier.com"&gt;Bruce Schneier&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id13" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id5"&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;I will admit it, I am jealous and do hope that Mayer has that written on his business card. As I explained in  &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/the-academic-social-machine-part-I.html"&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; I currently fulfill four out of five crowdsourced stereotypes about academics, and am unsure of others' perception of me on the fifth (but I know where I stand).&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id14" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id6"&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;I also did at the time, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blog.coursera.org/post/96686805237/response-to-reported-vulnerability-in-instructor-access"&gt;in the comments to the Coursera blog post&lt;/a&gt;, for the fact that Coursera was not properly acknowledging the value of Mayer's work for them in testing their platform.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id15" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id7"&gt;[7]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;This was at the &lt;em&gt;Data Privacy and Policy&lt;/em&gt; talk. There is a recorded version of this talk, which is not available to the general public.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id16" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id8"&gt;[8]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;For the inevitable straw men, I am asking for partial transparency. Let me raise you: I am not asking for Nick Dellamaggiore's formidably long password.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;</description><category>aral</category><category>audreywatters</category><category>bsaeta</category><category>connected_course</category><category>evgenymorozov</category><category>finkd</category><category>gsiemens</category><category>jonathanmayer</category><category>katemfd</category><category>mooc</category><category>nickdella</category><category>schneierblog</category><category>security_theatre</category><category>why</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2014 00:25:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>U Colorado system Coursera contract</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/u-colorado-system-coursera-contract.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Over at his blog, Jonathan Rees &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://moreorlessbunk.net/technology/as-the-learning-management-system-turns/"&gt;discusses the decision of the Colorado State University in Fort Collins to switch LMSes&lt;/a&gt;, from Blackboard to Canvas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He makes sly references to the fact that this blog post starts hitting very close to his own "home", since he is working himself at Colorado State University - Pueblo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a previous post on the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-contracts-of-stony-brook-roma-unc-colorado-kentucky-michigan-utoronto-ucsc.html"&gt;Coursera contracts&lt;/a&gt;, I gathered together all the Coursera contracts that I could find online. This was in fact partly a response to repeated appeals he has done in the past for faculty to speak up across universities (see first line of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/edtech-policies-part-ii.html"&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of those contracts was from the University of Colorado system, it is &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/coursera-Colorado.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I was wondering how the decision was taken in Colorado of joining Coursera in the first place, and if faculty were consulted on this. The comments are below, feel free to contribute (even anonymously if you would like).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I was also wondering how he (and other professors and administrators) would react to this present post, over which he has no control (and we haven't discussed this beforehand).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To increase likelihood that someone would respond, I also posted a comment on his blog sending readers here.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>coursera</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/u-colorado-system-coursera-contract.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2014 13:25:02 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>