<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>paulolivier.dehaye.org (connected_course)</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/</link><description></description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2014 12:33:02 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>MOOCs, journalism and digital disruption</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/moocs-journalism-and-digital-disruption.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you missed today's &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ccourses?src=hash"&gt;#ccourses&lt;/a&gt; discussion on &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/privacy?src=hash"&gt;#privacy&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/trust?src=hash"&gt;#trust&lt;/a&gt; you can watch it here: &lt;a href="http://t.co/JMkWGG09Ss"&gt;http://t.co/JMkWGG09Ss&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— DML Research Hub (@dmlresearchhub) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dmlresearchhub/status/520687983591448576"&gt;October 10, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;p&gt;I just listened to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://archive.org/details/RitchinBtfInterview"&gt;an audio interview&lt;/a&gt; conducted by Jonathan Worth for his &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://phonar.org.uk"&gt;photography course #phonar&lt;/a&gt;, back in 2013. The interviewee is &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fred_Ritchin"&gt;Fred Ritchin&lt;/a&gt;, a journalist, professor and author. Originally I was attracted to the interview because of a question asked by Ritchin during a #ccourses hangout about trust. He essentially asked how an entire profession (journalism) could rebuild trust with its audience once it was lost. It felt as if he was hoping educators could help give an answer that is eluding his profession.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have talked &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html"&gt;before on this blog&lt;/a&gt; of the parallels I see in Worth's approach in #phonar and mine with MOOC teaching. It looks like Ritchin can help explore these parallels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The older paradigm for photojournalists was to simply record events, with the hope—and frequently the expectation—that people and their governments would be moved to respond to the injustices pictured, as witnessed by the impact of certain images during the Civil Rights movement and the Vietnam War. Given evolving media and political climates, however, including the billions of images now available online from all kinds of sources, the purpose and effectiveness of media, in particular of visual journalism, has been called into question. Bending the Frame, by author and critic Fred Ritchin, addresses the new and emerging potentials for visual media to impact society. Also encompassing online efforts, uses of video, and a diverse range of books and exhibitions, this volume aims for as wide-ranging and far-reaching a discussion as possible, asking the critical question: how can images promote new thinking and make a difference in the world?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://aperture.org/shop/books/bending-the-frame-fred-ritchin-books#sthash.JKE7mMEM.dpuf"&gt;About&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Bending the Frame: Photojournalism, Documentary, and the Citizen&lt;/em&gt;, Fred Ritchin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, digital photography and the web have led to a complete rethink of the role of professional photographers in society, and a struggle now to find their relevance in the wider world. The interview is at times a litany of missed opportunities for the New York Times. Ritchin recalls experiments conducted by the editorial side of the New York Times, playing with new multimedia options. This was in 1994, and was instigated by the business side of the journal, actually, full of hope that this could lead to new revenues. Immediately of course this was squashed when all newspapers started making their content freely available on the web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ritchin's response then was to use this new media to show a new kind of story: instead of showing war, he would show peace. His test case was Bosnia, where he tried to construct a nonlinear narrative around the experience of a photojournalist arriving there, and convey some of the disorientation  and confusion of the fallout of an ethnic war. In constructing this narrative, he had to put the photographer back in the center, because of the need for multiple links between elements in different photographs. This was completely new territory for anyone: even the idea of clicking on an image had to be explained to the readers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
It opened up the idea of instead of the New York Times and the photographer telling you what is going on, you as a reader have to become a collaborator with them to figure out what is going on, because in fact the photographer does not really know what is going on. The New York Times does not really know what is going on. We are all piecing it together. We all have our own experiences and we could apply our own experiences to the situation.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work was submitted at the time for a Pulitzer price in public service, but immediately rejected because it wasn't on paper. He says it took many years "for institutions to investigate the new possibilities of digital, of telling stories differently, of understanding the world differently." He recalls his own thinking back then, that deviated sharply from this insitutional chokehold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
If this is a revolution in media, we have to think in revolutionary ways, we can't just do what we were doing before. And photography is very good at being reactive. It reacts well to situations. There is a war, we photograph it. Spectacular imagery. But I prefer a pro-active photography, one that says "We don't want a war to happen". How can we make images prevent war? Or minimize it. How can we minimize global warming? How can we do things before the bad stuff happens?&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually, the institutions lost: there was a "collapse of the mainstream, which puts the marginal in the centre, as a new practice or rather an old pratice, but one we didn't want to acknowledge before." Finally, the old institutions have had to acknowledge that all those experimental ideas were going in the right direction. But in the twenty years interval, they have suffered drastically from the intrusion of many new players on their turf, leading to his original question about trust. How do bona fide journalist now regain the trust of the general public, in a new landscape where their credentials are often ignored? Ritchin himelf introduces some clues: through a reversal of roles, between the amateur embedded in a community, and the professional outsider coming to report about the community. In 2013, he sees the "integration of both as the greatest challenge in journalism right now".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is fascinating to me, and I can see many parallels with MOOCs and the institutional meddling at the frontline of online education. Photojournalism itself was born on the frontlines, with its founding fathers in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magnum_Photos"&gt;Magnum agency&lt;/a&gt;, a cooperative of photojournalists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
They didn't discuss photography in the founding years. They discussed the world. They were happy to have survived World War II. [..] They were very political. They were interested in the future of people. It wasn't the future of photography. They were interested in the future of people. And I appreciated that, because I think the point of photography is not to celebrate itself but the point of photography is to be useful in the world, to try to get us to a better place. And that's the way they were working. To me that's what the original spirit of Magnum was.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe we need a cooperative of MOOC educators?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Ritchin also talks about &lt;em&gt;horseless carriages&lt;/em&gt;, and the technological determinism that prevents us to see unintended consequences of inventions such as digital photography. And Magnum has built its &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/categories/social_machine.html"&gt;own social machine&lt;/a&gt; to crowdsource the metadata tagging of its archive, which has led to the find of a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.behind-the-enemy-lines.com/2011/06/crowdsourcing-and-discovery-of-hidden.html"&gt;hidden treasure&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>connected_course</category><category>crowdsourcing</category><category>mooc</category><category>phonar</category><category>social_machine</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/moocs-journalism-and-digital-disruption.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2014 23:39:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Coursera and Safe Harbour of student data</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The European Union and Switzerland have agreements on free trade with the United States. One of those is &lt;strong&gt;Safe Harbour&lt;/strong&gt;, which has &lt;strong&gt;drastic implication for privacy&lt;/strong&gt;. In principle, Safe Harbour is a good idea: it creates &lt;strong&gt;little (business) friction&lt;/strong&gt; but ensures some form of &lt;strong&gt;citizen oversight&lt;/strong&gt; over the fastest evolving areas of e-commerce, by &lt;strong&gt;enforcing transparency&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html#id4" id="id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. It is being heavily tested though: in light of the Snowden revelations, there is growing understanding that this data originally held for commercial reasons is also a leverage of power. Andrus Ansip, the European Commissioner for Digital Single Market (designate)  &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.euractiv.com/sections/innovation-enterprise/ansip-threatens-suspend-safe-harbour-data-agreement-us-308962"&gt;acknowledged&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bits.blogs.nytimes.com/2014/10/06/europe-digital-nominee-demands-stronger-u-s-data-rules/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; in his hearings to be confirmed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;When it comes to protecting data - safe harbors need to be safe. 
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/EPhearings2014?src=hash"&gt;#EPhearings2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Andrus Ansip (@Ansip_EU) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Ansip_EU/status/519165997673373697"&gt;October 6, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Safe Harbour is not secure. The Agreement has yet to live up to its name. [..] If the U.S. Government does not make a clear statement, we must consider suspending the Agreement&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—Andrus Ansip &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html#id5" id="id2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The developments around &lt;strong&gt;MOOCs have very serious consequences for privacy&lt;/strong&gt;. Dozens of European universities are working with US MOOC companies, spending lots, and ultimately contributing to data collection on millions of young EU citizens, all without clear purposes. There is very different cultural understanding across the Atlantic of the privacy protections of the relationships between platform and user, teacher and student and university and student. There are also very delicate (legal) constructions everywhere of what constitutes academic freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these ideas were extensively tested when I taught the class &lt;em&gt;Teaching goes massive: new skills required&lt;/em&gt; on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.coursera.org/course/massiveteaching"&gt;Coursera&lt;/a&gt;. Parts of this class were supposed to cover some of those issues, and explain directly to the students most concerned the privacy issues associated to Coursera's business models. Instead, I was &lt;strong&gt;censored&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;insulted&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;vilified&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;legally threatened&lt;/strong&gt;, and Coursera used &lt;strong&gt;false, misleading or deeply intrusive&lt;/strong&gt; data held about the course or me to get my employer to launch a disciplinary procedure against me (as even &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2014/07/15/after-massiveteaching-questions-about-mooc-quality-control"&gt;hinted to a newspaper&lt;/a&gt;!). On top, of course, my students have been left in the dark. And I have lost access to my course materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.coursera.org/about/privacy"&gt;Safe Harbour is a recourse here&lt;/a&gt; for me (as it is to any European student on Coursera). I have submitted a request to Coursera, if only to get back access to the material created.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving forward, Ansip has decided to follow a suggestion of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://juliareda.eu/en/"&gt;Julia Reda&lt;/a&gt;, a Pirate Party MEP, and host an online town hall meeting as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Watch &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/EU_Commission"&gt;@EU_Commission&lt;/a&gt; vice-presidency candidate &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Ansip_EU"&gt;@Ansip_EU&lt;/a&gt; agree to answer users' questions online: &lt;a href="https://t.co/ppTkzwojmi"&gt;https://t.co/ppTkzwojmi&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ephearings2014?src=hash"&gt;#ephearings2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Julia Reda (@Senficon) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Senficon/status/519179686967246849"&gt;October 6, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;p&gt;This hearing will take place soon, let's see what Coursera will have responded by then... &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html#id6" id="id3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let me know what should be on my "to-do-list" for the next 5 years – on Wed, Oct 15 from 11 -12 am. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/AskAnsip?src=hash"&gt;#AskAnsip&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Andrus Ansip (@Ansip_EU) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Ansip_EU/status/520593695029334016"&gt;October 10, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id4" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html#id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Let's say a US company wants to do business in the EU. The EU, well aware of dangers associated with big data businesses, is concerned about the privacy of its citizens. At the same time, it does not want to hamper innovation. The solution found with Safe Harbour is to enforce a &lt;strong&gt;series of privacy principles&lt;/strong&gt;,  as listed on the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Safe_Harbor_Privacy_Principles"&gt;Wikipedia page&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;&lt;li&gt;Notice - Individuals must be informed that their data is being collected and about how it will be used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choice - Individuals must have the option to opt out of the collection and forward transfer of the data to third  parties.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Onward Transfer - Transfers of data to third parties may only occur to other organizations that follow adequate data protection principles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Security - Reasonable efforts must be made to prevent loss of collected information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data Integrity - Data must be relevant and reliable for the purpose it was collected for.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Access - &lt;strong&gt;Individuals must be able to access information held about them&lt;/strong&gt;, and correct or delete it if it is inaccurate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enforcement - There must be effective means of enforcing these rules.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id5" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html#id2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Ansip is also former Prime Minister of Estonia, a country very much ahead in everything digital. One can even &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ibtimes.co.uk/estonia-first-country-offer-e-residency-digital-citizenship-1468766"&gt;become e-citizen there and get digital residency&lt;/a&gt;, with minimal requirements.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id6" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html#id3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Not very promising actually: within a few minutes of my original email, I got a canned message back sending me to assistance forums. I replied that this was not an answer to my request, and got the same canned message once again... Possibly I am the first Coursera user to make use of Safe Harbour.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;</description><category>connected_course</category><category>coursera</category><category>privacy</category><category>trust</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2014 18:33:34 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>MOOC research proposal, using crowdsourcing</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/mooc-research-proposal-using-crowdsourcing.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;In April 2014, I submitted a research proposal &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/mooc-research-proposal-using-crowdsourcing.html#id2" id="id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. Its title is &lt;em&gt;Engineering Discovery in Mathematics&lt;/em&gt;, after the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.amazon.com/Reinventing-Discovery-New-Networked-Science/dp/0691148902"&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Reinventing Discovery&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://michaelnielse.org"&gt;Michael Nielsen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The proposal is in two part, an &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://user.math.uzh.ch/dehaye/ERC/ExtendedSynopsis_Dehaye.pdf"&gt;Extended Synopsis&lt;/a&gt; and a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://user.math.uzh.ch/dehaye/ERC/ResearchPlan_Dehaye.pdf"&gt;Research Plan&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main goal (project Z) of this four year proposal is to formalise mathematics. This is utterly unrealistic, and of course is to be considered a beacon very very far in the distance. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/paul-bernays-lectures-at-eth-zurich.html"&gt;Fields medalist Voevodsky suggests a 500 year horizon&lt;/a&gt; for this! To pile on to the difficulty of doing this, Thomas Hales explains his motivation of embarking on a formal proof of his own result, the proof of the Kepler conjecture. The background is that his paper had been accepted in one of the most prestigious mathematics journal, but conditionally on the grounds that his computer-generated proof was so complex that it could not be verified by even a team of 20 (very well trained) human referees:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In truth, my motivations for the project are far more complex than a simple hope of removing residual doubt from the minds of few referees. Indeed, I see formal methods as fundamental to the long-term growth of mathematics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—Thomas Hales, Flyspeck project&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indeed, mathematics and mathematicians are struggling to organise the information they produce, and the refereeing process will not be capable of responding to rapid advances in our capacities at theorem proving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why do I think my short four year proposal is interesting, alongside all those giants? Because it introduces a new idea in the picture, that of MOOCs. It is a fact that soon hundreds of students will be taking the same classes in parallel, and that graduate classes will be taken by dozens of students rather than handfuls. Also, professors in the more basic classes will start to collaborate more on content, and a formalisation effort can help in that direction. Admittedly, the proposal is not very specific, and exposes many ideas. I think the most promising avenue is in a bootstrapping process of the proofs, submitted as crowdsourced work in the context of a MOOC (with the expert explaining the material to formalise on video, say). Already &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://front.math.ucdavis.edu/1211.7012"&gt;it has been shown&lt;/a&gt; that a lot of the Flyspeck poject proofs can actually themselves be automated, and the smart introduction of human mathematician labor can help tighten all the feedback loops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, this is going to be hard work, far in the distance. In the near future the goals will be more limited, and will probably benefit from MOOC-based research efforts in other disciplines too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(This post also serves as an updated introduction to the "Connected Courses" course)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id2" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/mooc-research-proposal-using-crowdsourcing.html#id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;I have made a reference to it in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/what-i-am-doing-with-moocs-and-why-june-2nd.html"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;</description><category>connected_course</category><category>foundations</category><category>mooc</category><category>research</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/mooc-research-proposal-using-crowdsourcing.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2014 12:18:07 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Culture of humiliation</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/culture-of-humiliation.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I have learned a lot recently about online humiliation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monica Lewinsky's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.vanityfair.com/society/2014/06/monica-lewinsky-humiliation-culture"&gt;Vanity Fair piece&lt;/a&gt; was very insightful. Indeed, if anyone would know about being the victim of online shaming, it would be her. Interestingly, she shares that a new stage of horror for her was achieved when she understood the impact his scandal had on her family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In September of 2010, the culmination of these experiences began to snap into a broader context for me. A phone conversation with my mother shifted the lens through which I viewed my world. We were discussing the tragic death of Tyler Clementi. Tyler, you will recall, was an 18-year-old Rutgers freshman who was secretly streamed via Webcam kissing another man. Days later, after being derided and humiliated on social media, he committed suicide by jumping off the George Washington Bridge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My mom wept. Sobbing, she kept repeating over and over, “How his parents must feel … his poor parents.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was an unbearably tragic event, and while hearing of it brought me to tears, too, I couldn’t quite grasp why my mom was so distraught. And then it dawned on me: she was reliving 1998, when she wouldn’t let me out of her sight. She was replaying those weeks when she stayed by my bed, night after night, because I, too, was suicidal. The shame, the scorn, and the fear that had been thrown at her daughter left her afraid that I would take my own life—a fear that I would be literally humiliated to death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—Monica Lewinsky, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.vanityfair.com/society/2014/06/monica-lewinsky-humiliation-culture"&gt;Shame and Survival&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at the year, 2010, that's twelve years after the facts. A lot of time for a mom to suffer with weakened trust in her daughter that she would take on life, with its good and bad days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something else that crossed my path is a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mathbabe.org/2014/09/30/people-hate-me-i-must-be-doing-something-right/"&gt;post by Cathy O'Neil on her blog mathbabe&lt;/a&gt;, where she discusses some ways she has built a thick skin and maintains confidence in herself, even in the face of criticism that can get very personal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there’s one other thing I conclude when I piss people off: that I’m getting under their skin, which means what I’m saying is getting out there, to a wider audience than just people who already agree with me, and if that guy hates me then maybe 100 other people are listening and not quite hating me. They might even be agreeing with me. They might even be changing their minds about some things because of my arguments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I realize this sounds twisted, but when people hate me, I feel like I must be doing something right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One other thing I’ll say, which the article brings up. It is a luxury indeed to be a woman who can afford to be hated. I am not at risk, or at least I don’t feel at all at risk, when other people hate me. They are entitled to hate me, and I don’t need to bother myself about getting them to like me. It’s a deep and wonderful fact about our civilization that I can say that, and I am very glad to be living here and now, where I can be a provocative and opinionated intellectual woman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—Cathy O'Neil&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, the humiliation could get very deep in her psyche, but she makes her way of fighting it back very explicit. It's an utilitarian calculus, based on the scale of the positive impact she hopes to achieve versus the one negative comment she just had to face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She ends the piece with this powerful line:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Fuck yes! Let’s do this, people! Let’s have ideas and argue about them and disagree! It’s what freedom is all about.&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><category>connected_course</category><category>trust</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/culture-of-humiliation.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2014 21:37:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Building trust in #massiveteaching, through visuals</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;As part of the module on trust in &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.connectedcourses.net"&gt;Connected Courses&lt;/a&gt;, I would like to share some tricks that I have used to visually build trust across cultures. It was especially powerful for me to watch Jonathan Worth's video on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://phonar.org/2014/09/leveraging-you-why-in-answer-to-mike-wesch/"&gt;Leveraging your why&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html#id5" id="id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Worth offers that his "Why?" for #phonar is actually citizen journalism, and discusses a photo by John Stanmeyer, winner of the World Press Photo 2013 award.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this brings me back to, this is my ‘why?’ So this image is the winning image from the World Press Photo this year, by a photographer called John Stanmeyer, and this is why it annoys me so much. Because it’s by a photographer called John Stanmeyer. These are African immigrants standing on a beach, trying to get a phone signal before they jump in the water. Let me just get this right, “on the shore of Djibouti City at night raising their phones in an attempt to capture an inexpensive signal from neighbouring Somalia”. These are the people that aren’t in my class. They’re holding these smart devices which can all take pictures, and yet it takes a photographer from New York to bring it back and we can now talk about it.  What these people need is to be able to be trusted and to be heard, and these are the people that aren’t in the class. So this is my why, and this is my way marker, so this is definitely the best and most exciting thing that’s come out of my classes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://phonar.org/2014/09/leveraging-you-why-in-answer-to-mike-wesch/"&gt;Jonathan Worth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of my efforts with my &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.coursera.org/course/massiveteaching"&gt;Coursera course&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Massive Teaching: News skills required&lt;/em&gt; were some interesting blend of Worth's efforts in #phonar and in #connected_courses. Let's first consider the exact opposite of what I did. Relax, prepare some popcorn, and watch the following video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;iframe width="425" height="344" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/0rmJqQotDWo?rel=0&amp;amp;hd=1&amp;amp;wmode=transparent"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clealy this video exploits the elite university brand together with a lot of pixie dust to try to cement this elite brand even more. The "why?" of this MIT video certainly shows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as in Worth's #phonar course leading up to citizen journalism, I am hoping with parts of &lt;em&gt;Massive Teaching&lt;/em&gt; to enable some form of citizen-MOOCing, to create a small distributed network of video production, with no sacrifice on the quality of the education provided. My sidegoal was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to find the cheapest way to produce video, but to find a visual style that could appeal equally to institutions (even very elite) and lonely individuals anywhere in the world &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html#id6" id="id2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sidegoal was to make for a more homogeneous and egalitarian pool of video producers &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html#id7" id="id3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;, but it goes further. How do we enable anyone anywhere to build trust with &lt;strong&gt;connected diverse individuals&lt;/strong&gt; (a concept that I used in a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/moocs-as-inventions-chals14.html"&gt;recent talk&lt;/a&gt; and is obviously core to #ccourses)? Let's consider one of my videos, where the topic is precisely on tracking of individuals by large corporations, drawing parallels between educational analytics and AdWords style advertising.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;iframe width="425" height="344" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/qOCln176bM4?rel=0&amp;amp;hd=1&amp;amp;wmode=transparent"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;img alt="../crib.jpeg" class="align-right" src="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/crib.jpeg" style="width: 216.0px; height: 288.0px;"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note a few things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;&lt;li&gt;it uses easily findable DUPLO pieces &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html#id8" id="id4"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt; and paper cutouts;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I feel that using kids' toys produces emotional responses and increases trust;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my hands are there, and that makes the videos still personal (contrast with the expense at &lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:CEDE@EPFL"&gt;CEDE@EPFL&lt;/a&gt; for their &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=agbe9B5l_VI"&gt;invisible hand effect&lt;/a&gt;);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the production process is first audio, then video, and the two are completely separate (I replay the audio when filming the video). In this way I actually first write the transcript, record a reading, and then illustrate. It makes translations very easy: simply re-record the sound, at the pace of the video.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I designed a recording studio out of IKEA furniture pieces (a crib, for instance for a cage, so it is easy to attach camera, light, etc); IKEA is not cheap enough but it gives wide reach. I have confidence that this can be improved drastically, by posting on sites such as &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ikeahackers.net/"&gt;IKEAhackers&lt;/a&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I encouraged my students to do the same, by describing my process as throgouhly as possible (done here again);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;None of those cheap tricks are new, it is mere borrowing of on-the-street intelligence of High School teachers and the Maker movement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;As stated, one of the sidegoals was to enable anyone to do this, and for anyone to create trust with anyone else, without necessarily going through a central authority (like that provided by my Coursera course). For this purpose, I selected some articles to help guide students on what might build trust across cultural divides, such as &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.featureshoot.com/2013/03/photos-of-children-from-around-the-world-with-their-most-prized-possessions/"&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;, which clearly echoes the emotional response I was referring to earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what happened with &lt;em&gt;Massive Teaching&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, despite my best efforts it turns out that the fact that Coursera owned the channel was still &lt;em&gt;massively&lt;/em&gt; important. I might have made sure I owned all the content, and diluted as much as possible all ambient brands, I still needed Coursera for its reach (or at least I felt I did!). Going through them was not a smart way to challenge the general status quo in MOOCs, but the interesting paradox of #massiveteaching is that ultimately it is not the content that went missing, but rather the human (me, the instructor). The content was instead reinstated (well, actually only partially and with questionable motives), and I was unable to access the sources anymore, thereby losing some of my own content. This paradox was then compounded by further issues of trust and disinformation, where again access to communication channels was crucial. This account of course omits any of the students' perspectives, which must have been wildly different, depending on the activities they actually engaged in. With the instructor gone, only disaster was possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id5" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html#id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;He apparently himself was troubled by Mike Wesch's &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f_mcTLlG_wg&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be"&gt;fantastic talk&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;em&gt;Why we need a why&lt;/em&gt; (just making the chain of trust explicit here, as explained in the talk...)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id6" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html#id2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Judging from aggregate and individual feedback, that was achieved.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id7" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html#id3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;This echoes a parallel effort in academic publishing in some disciplines. Indeed, the refereeing process, which is a form of  authority and power, is done double-blind, to prevent reinforcement of biases. In mathematics the author of a submitted paper is not anonymous to the referee, which is arguably a problem.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id8" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html#id4"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;This in itself is very interestingly pain point. Can I use a DUPLO piece as a tool? I had &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dearrichblog.blogspot.ch/2014/05/cut-out-animations-moocs-and-copyright.html"&gt;to ask a lawyer for that&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;</description><category>connected_course</category><category>coursera</category><category>epfl</category><category>massive_teaching</category><category>mit</category><category>trust</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2014 11:38:58 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Security theatre, in airports and academia</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;When I was in Oxford, I had the best view in the world from my apartment. Off Merton Field, above Deadman's Walk onto &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christ_Church_Meadow,_Oxford"&gt;Christ Church Meadow&lt;/a&gt;. Uninterrupted grass landscape into the river, with rolling mist up to the river most mornings, &lt;em&gt;Lord of the Rings&lt;/em&gt;-style. In fact, Tolkien's office &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt;  the apartment upstairs, and I like to think the view inspired him. How come, in a cramped city like this, I could enjoy this same view decades later, centuries after the construction of the building I was living in? Well, because in the byzantine world of Oxford real estate, one college (ChristChurch) owned that land, while another owned grazing rights for cattle on it (forgot which, presumably Merton itself). Not that tourists would see cattle in that field: every year, the college with grazing rights would rent sheep for just one day, and move it there. The theory was that &lt;strong&gt;if they didn't exercise their right, they would legally lose it&lt;/strong&gt;, and the other college could build whatever they wanted there and ruin the view (Wikipedia mentions a road that was defeated). &lt;strong&gt;The pace at Oxford allowed to think this through: custom is built over centuries, and preserved with yearly activities.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why this long preamble?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was just in Goteborg for the #Chals14 conference, where a big part of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/moocs-as-inventions-chals14.html"&gt;my schpiel was that we should not succumb to the free-is-a-lie mantra of MOOCs&lt;/a&gt; and resist narrow views of the "Internet happening to education" (quoting George Siemens) based around technological determinism (quoting Evgeny Morozov). The afternoon session was in Swedish, so I was distracted and looking at Twitter. One person that I am following, Aral Balkan, tweeted this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Schiphol"&gt;@schiphol&lt;/a&gt; airport breaking EU law? They told me today that I could not opt of the full-body scanner.

&lt;a href="http://t.co/LfQ7k20ZLG"&gt;http://t.co/LfQ7k20ZLG&lt;/a&gt;

Via &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/alloy"&gt;@alloy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Aral Balkan (@aral) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/aral/status/514736935978680320"&gt;September 24, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;p&gt;Balkan is a privacy advocate, who has been trying to raise the attention of people to the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://aralbalkan.com/notes/spyware-2.0/"&gt;Spyware 2.0 model&lt;/a&gt; employed by many companies now: in his Orwellian view, by offering free services, large corporations manage to convince us to give away all our data, so they can spy on us. He is leading the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ind.ie/manifesto"&gt;Indie-tech movement&lt;/a&gt; and peripherially (?) in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dmlcentral.net/blog/doug-belshaw/reclaiming-web-next-generation"&gt;Reclaim the Web movement&lt;/a&gt;, which also has declinations in the MOOC space (for instance with &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.wired.com/2014/09/known/"&gt;Known&lt;/a&gt;). His tweet got me pretty upset: a few years ago, Schiphol security classified a present from my mom, high quality Belgian chocolate paste, as a liquid. Back then I had checked, and legally they were, at least at the time, within their rights: individual employees have ultimate classification decision and chocolate paste is indeed a grey area. Still, because of an arbitrary decision by a person who gleefully threw away a present in the bin, I was forced to make-do with Swiss chocolate for a while, a clearly inferior proposition. If you want to dismiss my reasons to do this, you could say that I have a score to settle with Schiphol security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="../schiphol-hand.jpg" class="align-right" src="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/schiphol-hand.jpg" style="width: 540.0px; height: 360.0px;"&gt;&lt;p&gt;As luck would have it, on my flight back to Zurich from Goteborg, I was flying through Schiphol. On the very same day as Balkan. On top, the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/aral/status/514736935978680320"&gt;twitter thread&lt;/a&gt; had a ton of links to the relevant laws and websites, which were completely unambiguous. So all the work of retesting this more "scientifically" was cut out for me. In fact, &lt;strong&gt;one could argue that as an academic this is part of my work: to challenge institutions, spread knowledge, and contribute to society. These last two points made by many #Chals14 participants in the context of MOOCs.&lt;/strong&gt; I agree and generally take it seriously, especially living in a country where academic freedom is in the constitution (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.admin.ch/opc/en/classified-compilation/19995395/"&gt;Art. 20&lt;/a&gt;), where I am paid well to think, connect dots, etc. My view of academia might smack of arrogance and overreach, but bear with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few hours later, I myself landed in Schiphol, and got out of the transit area so I would have to intentionally get back through security. Since I could not print my legal backups on time, I had written on my hand the references to European regulation, 185/2010 4.1.1.10, a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://english.nctv.nl/themes/Counterterrorism/Security_and_civil_aviation/Security_Scan/FAQ_3.aspx"&gt;Dutch website URL&lt;/a&gt; and my plan:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;&lt;li&gt;refuse body scanner twice;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ask for an explanation of my rights;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;question the legality of their setup;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ask for the name of the person I was talking to;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ask to speak to a supervisor;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;iterate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I approached the security scanner, I looked around. Nowhere was it written that I could opt out. It was simply written that I should "feel free to ask questions". In Balkan's case, this was not helpful at all: since the security employee seems to have violated the law, Balkan couldn't just point to a sign and say he was wrong. The fact that there was no sign is, according to me, already a violation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before being screened by a security scanner, the passenger shall be informed of the technology used, the conditions associated to its use and the possibility to opt out from a security scanner&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/HTML/?uri=CELEX:02010R0185-20140409&amp;amp;from=EN"&gt;European regulation 185/2010&lt;/a&gt;, last line of article 4.1.1.10&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I had to finally talk to a Schiphol security officer and refuse the scanner, our interaction validated all the care I put in preparing this (and my general approach to a few similar challenge-the-authority projects I am involved in): his reaction was simply to ask me "Why?", why I was refusing. If there is one thing I learned this summer, it is to ask myself "Why?" and have a good answer to this question &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id9" id="id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. In this case, I could definitely answer it right away: "Because this is my right". &lt;strong&gt;By keeping a pretense of being citizen beta, I got the officer to volunteer the reason why he himself asked me "Why?"&lt;/strong&gt;: he volunteered "because sometimes people don't have the right information and think those are X-rays machines going through their skin" (regardless of the validity of the assertion, this is irrelevant to the fact that European law still allows me to opt out). I repeated that I was still refusing, and he said that was indeed my right, let me get around the scanner and started patting me down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To emphasize: &lt;strong&gt;this particular officer knew from the start that I it was my right to opt out&lt;/strong&gt;. While being perfectly courteous, he was making assumptions of my own ignorance, expecting to enlighten me with information about his very expensive, super advanced, and ultimately useless piece of technology &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id10" id="id2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;.  This &lt;strong&gt;explanation was supposed to somehow impress me, and lead me to willingly give away my own rights as a EU citizen (on EU soil)&lt;/strong&gt;. Given that I had gone to Goteborg to partly talk about technological determinism, with quotes of Zuckerberg on the evolving nature of privacy (including the "dumb fucks" quote, page 11 of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/goteborg-final.pdf"&gt;my slides&lt;/a&gt;), this was adding another layer of irony... There possibly was arrogance in my assumptions about my role as an academic, but certainly there were in the assumptions the officer was making: he didn't know about the Oxford sheep (presumably), all the necessary tabs opened and ready on my laptop, the writing on my hand, or the fact that I have quite a bit of experience with EU law (in the context of a separate private matter, I have previously encouraged the European Commission to initiate an &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/eu_law/your_rights/your_rights_en.htm"&gt;infringement procedure&lt;/a&gt; against my home country, Belgium. This is a &lt;em&gt;highly&lt;/em&gt; recommended and free legal avenue, available to any European citizen and maybe even resident).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once he had patted me down, and I had effectively gone through security, it was time to lay some of it out. Of course, I was quickly bounced around to the shift supervisor (who looked quite a bit senior). &lt;strong&gt;René was genuinely concerned and wanted to do the right thing: he took  pictures of my screen to get the relevant EU law lines and the original tweets. I told him to look for the #HelloSchiphol hashtag on Twitter. He thanked me.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But again he dismissed Balkan as just a tweeter among others, and I had to insist that he actually had many followers who care about privacy, that he is a big shot taking on Google, etc. I shouldn't have had to do that, and neither should it have mattered that I am a university professor, yet he did remark on the fact &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id11" id="id3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;. One can argue about my method and its transparency, but &lt;strong&gt;by playing dumb I actually got further&lt;/strong&gt; than just flashing legal printouts right away, since I now have &lt;strong&gt;one more data point on how Schiphol security officers respond to seemingly unprepared citizens concerned with airport security&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overall, this experience with Schiphol security was very positive, and I don't have a grudge against them anymore (provided they add relevant signage).&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I want to contrast this with another security theatre incident &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id12" id="id4"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;, this time in the MOOC space. In September 5th &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://hackeducation.com/2014/09/05/beyond-the-lms-newcastle-university/"&gt;talk by Audrey Watters&lt;/a&gt; about the Learning Management System, she says this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The LMS was — is — designed as an Internet portal to the student information system, and much like the old portals of the Dot Com era, much like AOL for example, it cautions you when you try to venture outside of it. “ re you sure you want to leave AOL?” “Are you sure you want to leave the VLE?” “Aren’t you scared to be on the Web?” “There are strangers and strange ideas out there. Stay within the LMS! Stay within AOL!"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—Audrey Watters&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There I was in Schiphol, facing the same security theatre to cross an actual physical portal.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watters might have been picking on older technologies (AOL and LMSes), but on that very same day (Sept 5th) the very same issues resurfaced for more modern technology, through Jonathan Mayer. Mayer is a lawyer, but also a PhD student at Stanford in computer science. Like Balkan, he is a big advocate for privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s hard to come up with something that doesn’t count as market research or product improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.adexchanger.com/ad-exchange-news/privacy-advocate-jonathan-mayer-has-had-it-with-do-not-track/"&gt;Jonathan Mayer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far his research has cost &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mashable.com/2014/09/23/stanford-google-privacy-research/"&gt;Google 22.5M USD in fines&lt;/a&gt;, and what he has said in interviews has earned him the distinction of being &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.adexchanger.com/online-advertising/iab-mozilla/"&gt;labeled by the online advertising trade union&lt;/a&gt; a "Bolshevik of the Internet world" &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id13" id="id5"&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;.  He is 26.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He is also teaching a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.coursera.org/course/surveillance"&gt;course on Surveillance Law&lt;/a&gt; on Coursera (i.e. how the NSA, FBI, etc are legally accessing information about US citizens). A week before his course, he published a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://webpolicy.org/2014/09/04/a-funny-thing-happened-on-the-way-to-coursera/"&gt;blog post detailing some security flaws of Coursera itself&lt;/a&gt;. This was at his personal blog, but I assume he would consider this part of his work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Courserians, we are writing about a topic we take very seriously – user privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.google.com/?gfe_rd=cr&amp;amp;ei=L48jVJSRK6WG8QeY6oG4Cg#q=Brennan+Saeta"&gt;Brennan Saeta&lt;/a&gt; - Infrastructure Engineering, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blog.coursera.org/post/96686805237/response-to-reported-vulnerability-in-instructor-access"&gt;Coursera official blog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coursera's response was given in a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blog.coursera.org/post/96686805237/response-to-reported-vulnerability-in-instructor-access"&gt;blog post&lt;/a&gt;. Slate has &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.slate.com/blogs/future_tense/2014/09/05/coursera_is_patching_vulnerabilities_found_by_jonathan_mayer_a_surveillance.html"&gt;criticized that response&lt;/a&gt;, and smartly highlighted that any attack vector is good for a hacker. &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id14" id="id6"&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My team, Infrastructure, is taking a security class together, learning about cryptography because this is kind of relevant to security. So we try to improve ourselves and learn about best practices as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.google.com/?gfe_rd=cr&amp;amp;ei=L48jVJSRK6WG8QeY6oG4Cg#q=Nick%20Dellamaggiore"&gt;Nick Dellamaggiore&lt;/a&gt; - Infrastructure Lead, at Coursera Partners' Conference 2014 &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id15" id="id7"&gt;[7]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In his talk at the Coursera Partners' Conference, Dellamaggiore has a background slide with the actual class that his Infrastructure team takes: Cryptography I, on Coursera of course, by Dan Boneh (ironically from Stanford). I went and looked at that course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;img alt="../crypto1.jpg" class="align-center" src="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/crypto1.jpg" style="width: 936.6px; height: 431.9px;"&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sure enough, 9 minutes into the first video, &lt;em&gt;social engineering&lt;/em&gt; is highlighted as nullifying the value of encryption and many other security methods. Given that Coursera superprofessors are supposed to be the best of the best (at their very very narrow discipline), and given the way academia works, I expect a fair share of Coursera professors to be greying a bit. &lt;strong&gt;I want to question how the decision was made by Coursera to think those professors could be trusted with this level of access&lt;/strong&gt;. I have had access to more information than the general public to help answer this question, but do not know enough at this time to actually answer it. &lt;strong&gt;I am not willing to reshare publicly the information I still have because of personal legal risk.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's great, but how do we keep data from falling in the wrong hands, say they try to access our physical machines in the cloud or our production databases or what not. So this slide is a little bit more technical, so bear with me, I will kind of go through it quicker.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—Nick Dellamaggiore - Infrastructure Lead, a few seconds later&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This lack of public transparency is itself is a concern, in the context of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://asilomar-highered.info"&gt;Asilomar convention&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Without more transparency from Coursera on their data policies, I have genuine concern that Coursera itself is just using security theatre for commercial advantage&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id16" id="id8"&gt;[8]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case it is not clear at this stage, I still have a score to settle with Coursera, but I try to be a patient man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If someone’s not going to follow the practices, that’s something that society faces in general, and that’s why we have police and courts [..] In the academic world, we don’t need police and courts, but we have academic discipline, we have academic institutional standards, we have research standards. If people don’t comply with those, they do need to be deal[t] with. In our set of relationships, that’s between the university and the instructor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2014/07/15/after-massiveteaching-questions-about-mooc-quality-control"&gt;Vivek Goel&lt;/a&gt;, Chief Academic Strategist, Coursera and apparently also "&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blog.coursera.org/post/77181132056/welcome-vivek-goel-to-courseras-leadership-team"&gt;still a professor at the Dalla Lana School of Public Health and the Institute for Health Policy, Management &amp;amp; Evaluation&lt;/a&gt;"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goel is textually correct of course. But he is also intentionally misleading (by offering this generic quote in an article about a course that I ran). And he is also unintentionally short-sighted, for very many reasons. One is that he indeed reminds me of looking up the local rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The University of Zurich (UZH) is an institution with a strong commitment to the free and open pursuit of scholarship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scholarship is the acquisition, the advancement and the &lt;strong&gt;dissemination of knowledge in a methodological and critical manner&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To flourish, scholarship must be &lt;strong&gt;free from external influences, constraints and ideological pressures&lt;/strong&gt;. The University of Zurich is committed to &lt;strong&gt;unrestricted freedom in research and teaching&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Academic freedom calls for a high degree of responsibility, including &lt;strong&gt;reflection on the ethical implications of research activities for humans, animals and the environment&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.uzh.ch/about/basics/mission_en.html"&gt;University of Zurich's mission statement&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another is that he has resorted to using innuendos. I can use my own too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We see all the platforms now really starting to talk about the social aspects [..] of learning, which come from the other theories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—The &lt;em&gt;Zuckerberg-wannabe of the higher education world&lt;/em&gt;, aka the &lt;em&gt;Chief-Academic-Strategist-formerly-known-as-an-academic&lt;/em&gt; aka Vivek Goel&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Don't worry, the nickname is based on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://youtu.be/PCV5xBPoxnE?t=4m47s"&gt;actual data&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id9" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Deserves a shoutout to Kate Bowles and #ccourses for reminding me of the importance of this question.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id10" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;I claim this general technology is useless based on still unpublished research &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.wired.com/2014/08/study-shows-how-easily-weapons-can-be-smuggled-past-tsas-x-ray-body-scanners"&gt;announced last month&lt;/a&gt;. I was unprepared to enter that debate there with the security officer, not knowing exactly which model Schiphol was using. I suspect the officer was not ready either. The point is that we shouldn't have to, as this particular European law was drafted anticipating rapid evolution in this security field, both regarding threat detection and evasion.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id11" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;He only learned that at the very end, when I wrote #HelloSchiphol on my business card. There is, so far in my life, only one (repeated) instance where I have flashed the fact that I am a professor: apartment hunting in Switzerland, for which competition is so fierce that local society admits pretty much &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; move is fair. The fact that many academics pride themselves not to use business cards or Twitter show a profound lack of understanding of their own place in the physical and digital world: conversation with any other citizen is important and that might require using their medium.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id12" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id4"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;To use the language of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.schneier.com"&gt;Bruce Schneier&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id13" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id5"&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;I will admit it, I am jealous and do hope that Mayer has that written on his business card. As I explained in  &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/the-academic-social-machine-part-I.html"&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt; I currently fulfill four out of five crowdsourced stereotypes about academics, and am unsure of others' perception of me on the fifth (but I know where I stand).&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id14" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id6"&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;I also did at the time, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blog.coursera.org/post/96686805237/response-to-reported-vulnerability-in-instructor-access"&gt;in the comments to the Coursera blog post&lt;/a&gt;, for the fact that Coursera was not properly acknowledging the value of Mayer's work for them in testing their platform.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id15" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id7"&gt;[7]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;This was at the &lt;em&gt;Data Privacy and Policy&lt;/em&gt; talk. There is a recorded version of this talk, which is not available to the general public.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id16" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html#id8"&gt;[8]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;For the inevitable straw men, I am asking for partial transparency. Let me raise you: I am not asking for Nick Dellamaggiore's formidably long password.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;</description><category>aral</category><category>audreywatters</category><category>bsaeta</category><category>connected_course</category><category>evgenymorozov</category><category>finkd</category><category>gsiemens</category><category>jonathanmayer</category><category>katemfd</category><category>mooc</category><category>nickdella</category><category>schneierblog</category><category>security_theatre</category><category>why</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/security-theatre-in-airports-and-academia.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2014 00:25:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>MOOCs as inventions #chals14</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/moocs-as-inventions-chals14.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I just finished giving my talk on &lt;em&gt;MOOCs as inventions: opportunities and risks&lt;/em&gt; in Goteborg, at the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/search?f=realtime&amp;amp;q=%23chals14&amp;amp;src=typd"&gt;#chals14&lt;/a&gt; meeting. This is a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.facebook.com/chals14?fref=ts"&gt;reunion of Swedish universities&lt;/a&gt; convened by Jonas Gilbert (Chalmers University Library) to discuss MOOCs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My slides are available &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/goteborg-final.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the talk, I discussed the idea that MOOCs are &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social_machine"&gt;social machines&lt;/a&gt; put in the hands of professors (thanks to my PhD student &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.math.uzh.ch/index.php?id=assistenten&amp;amp;L=&amp;amp;key1=4144&amp;amp;key2=&amp;amp;key3=&amp;amp;keySemId="&gt;Helen Riedtmann&lt;/a&gt; for boiling down my ideas to this simple statement), and quoted Evgeny Morozov, which I am reading at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, it was much better to be last speaker of the morning, to offer a (hopefully constructive) balance to some of the other points made earlier. It also lead naturally to interesting discussions (including with &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.chalmers.se/en/about-chalmers/the-president-and-vice-presidents/Pages/karin-markides-president.aspx"&gt;Karin Markides&lt;/a&gt;, who asked me a few questions above my pay grade. It is much easier to convey these ideas offline than online, but indeed the audience is smaller and different).  Still, the digital world was interesting too: I was glad to see how Twitter added to the talk &lt;strong&gt;for me&lt;/strong&gt; afterwards (something I am not used to, since very few mathematicians use Twitter), which helped me assess how my ideas were received. In a talk about MOOCs' risks and opportunities, someone immediately called me up on the risks of the opportunities, with a reference to Jaron Lanier:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/chals14?src=hash"&gt;#chals14&lt;/a&gt; The social machine; I wonder what Jaron Lanier would say about that. Read "You are not a gadget" for a critical take in this.&lt;/p&gt;— Thommy Eriksson (@KuggenMedialab) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/KuggenMedialab/status/514714933813338113"&gt;September 24, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now adding this to my reading list, since in fact he seems to talk a lot about mathematics too! It was also good to meet &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://jorg.pareigis.se/"&gt;Jorg Pareigis&lt;/a&gt;, a fellow &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/search?f=realtime&amp;amp;q=%23ccourses&amp;amp;src=typd"&gt;#ccourses participant&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two quick mementos for myself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;&lt;li&gt;I have now traveled to the first 15 countries to constitute the European Union.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have never been before in such last minute trouble with computers: still private Google Slides locked out of my account, requiring Google two-factor authentication through a dead cell phone... Literally managed to get to the slides as I was walking to the stand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description><category>connected_course</category><category>coursera</category><category>mooc</category><category>social_machine</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/moocs-as-inventions-chals14.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2014 11:39:41 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Learning, working and ?</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/learning-working-and.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;A lot of my recent thoughts have turned around issues of crowdsourcing and online education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="../worklearn.jpg" class="align-right" src="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/worklearn.jpg" style="width: 346.4px; height: 85.6px;"&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of my co-authors (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://hci.uni-hannover.de/people/markus"&gt;Markus Krause&lt;/a&gt;) is co-organising a workshop on that topic, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.worklearn.org/"&gt;WorkLearn 2014&lt;/a&gt;. It will take place in Pittsburgh November 2-4, as part of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.humancomputation.com/2014/"&gt;Human Computation conference HCOMP2014&lt;/a&gt;. Human Computation is another expression interchangeable for &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/social-teaching-machines.html"&gt;social machine&lt;/a&gt;, although it has different connotations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stated motivation of the workshop is very ambitious:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The online education and crowdsourcing communities are addressing similar problems in educating, motivating and evaluating students and workers. The online learning community succeeds in increasing the supply side of the cognitively skilled labor market, and the crowdsourcing at scale community creates a larger marketplace for cognitively skilled work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linking online platforms for crowd work with platforms for MOOCs has the potential to: provide knowledge and training at a massive scale to contributors; collect data that identify expert skills; engage contributors in simultaneously working and learning in a social environment; and organize large communities around online courses on specific topics. These all provide new opportunities to support and deploy sophisticated algorithms for crowd learning and work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most successful example in this direction is of course &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://duolingo.com"&gt;Duolingo&lt;/a&gt;, which helps translate the web while using volunteer labor by language learners. If one omits the learning, the strategy there is not that different from the strategy used by my Coursera coworker &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.coursera.org/instructor/bernstein"&gt;Abraham Bernstein&lt;/a&gt; to translate books using &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amazon_Mechanical_Turk"&gt;Amazon Mechanical Turk&lt;/a&gt;, and indeed part of his efforts aim to design effective tools to program those social machines (with the programming language CrowdLang).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;embed&gt;&lt;iframe width="640" height="360" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/emCABRV2cUA" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have always had some qualms about the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://florianschmidt.co/the-good-the-bad-and-the-ugly/"&gt;ethics of crowdsourcing&lt;/a&gt;, even though it can clearly be used for good: the prototypical success story is in the work of Ushahidi during the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ushahidi.com/blog/2012/01/12/haiti-and-the-power-of-crowdsourcing/"&gt;2010 Haiti earthquake&lt;/a&gt;. I was thus very happy to see over Labor Day 2014 that Michael Bernstein from Stanford announced &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://crowdresearch.org/blog/?p=9039"&gt;guidelines for academic requesters on Amazon Mechanical Turk&lt;/a&gt;. He explains the rationale for this (a Turker is a worker on a crowdsourcing platform):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
An IRB-approved researcher experimented on the [crowdsourcing] platform unannounced. The result was Turker confusion, strife, and wasted time, in a system where time is what it takes to make ends meet.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These guidelines were themselves crowdsourced, designed together with the Turkers (it's only natural!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, over the summer, there was a huge controversy over the iffy ethics of social platforms experimentation. This is due to the release at the very end of June 2014 of a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/kashmirhill/2014/06/29/facebook-doesnt-understand-the-fuss-about-its-emotion-manipulation-study/"&gt;Facebook experiment on its users&lt;/a&gt; (don't miss the Cornell IRB flowchart there). There are a ton of links about this, but the best is probably the account by Mary L. Gray of an &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://marylgray.org/?page_id=203"&gt;ethics panel that took place at the Microsoft Research Faculty Summit&lt;/a&gt; (and unfortunately was published with much delay).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, this should give serious pause to any educator. One can see lots of fields suddenly getting much too close, with very different or inexistent values. Online learners, just as Turkers, are vulnerable. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://nogoodreason.typepad.co.uk/no_good_reason/2014/06/the-ethics-of-digital-scholarship.html"&gt;Martin Weller&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.elearnspace.org/blog/2014/01/13/the-vulnerability-of-learning/"&gt;George Siemens&lt;/a&gt; have recently insisted on this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what do you think? Anyone wants to submit a position paper (2 pages) on the topic? Any of my co-learners in MOOCs would like to see what we can do? We could, well... crowdsource it...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(of course, this was due yesterday: official deadline is "September")&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>connected_course</category><category>coursera</category><category>crowdsourcing</category><category>duolingo</category><category>ethics</category><category>t509massive</category><category>whyopen</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/learning-working-and.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2014 00:17:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Click here so I can tell you about privacy (and invade yours too)</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/click-here-so-i-can-teach-you-about-privacy-and-invade-it-too.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Simply by looking at this page, you agree to this site's privacy policy, which is a copy of the Swiss Railway's statement on the use of Google Analytics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This website uses Google Analytics, a web analytics service provided by Google, Inc. (“Google”). Google Analytics uses “cookies”, which are text files placed on your computer, to help the website analyze how users use the site. The information generated by the cookie about your use of the website (including your IP address) will be transmitted to and stored by Google on servers in the United States . Google will use this information for the purpose of evaluating your use of the website, compiling reports on website activity for website operators and providing other services relating to website activity and internet usage. Google may also transfer this information to third parties where required to do so by law, or where such third parties process the information on Google's behalf. Google will not associate your IP address with any other data held by Google. You may refuse the use of cookies by selecting the appropriate settings on your browser, however please note that if you do this you may not be able to use the full functionality of this website. By using this website, you consent to the processing of data about you by Google in the manner and for the purposes set out above.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://support.google.com/analytics/answer/6004245"&gt;Google Analytics Terms of Service&lt;/a&gt;, as on the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sbb.ch/en/meta/data-protection/data-protection-google-analytics-statement.html"&gt;SBB website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The site itself does not collect data. However I do use Google Analytics, which requires me to introduce this policy as part of the service. The service allows me to track users on this website in various ways, and produces beautiful graphics like this one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="../google-analytics.jpg" class="align-center" src="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/google-analytics.jpg" style="width: 1020.0px; height: 518.0px;"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The comments below are bound by the Disqus Terms of Service, which are &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://help.disqus.com/customer/portal/articles/466259-privacy-policy"&gt;available here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don't like it, you can leave. So is the law of the internet.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>connected_course</category><category>edtech</category><category>privacy</category><category>switzerland</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/click-here-so-i-can-teach-you-about-privacy-and-invade-it-too.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2014 06:44:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>(Social) teaching machines</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/social-teaching-machines.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I want to take the opportunity of the recent talk by Audrey Watters on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://hackeducation.com/2014/09/03/monsters-altc2014/"&gt;Ed-Tech's Monsters&lt;/a&gt; to share some of my thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In her talk, Watters physically bases herself at Bletchley Park, a place of invention, ingenuity and deceit that greatly contributed to the Allies' war effort and incidentally the evolution of computing. She then steps back in time to Ludd and his followers, who rebelled against the introduction of machinery in their work. She then segways into the Frankenstein story of a creation abandoned by its master and finally draws parallels with the situation in ed tech today and the "promises" of teaching machines. This was an impossibly bad and short summary of a very good talk, so I would highly recommend to any reader lost here to go read the original. After doing that, please come back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="900" height="600" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/6qwZm56UadE?rel=0&amp;amp;hd=1&amp;amp;wmode=transparent"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt;During World War II, cryptographers worked at Bletchley Park to decipher German and Japanese secret messages. These were encoded by various versions of a machine called &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enigma_machine"&gt;Enigma&lt;/a&gt;, a typewriter wired with multiple electrical contacts that constantly shuffled letters around. It is really a quite dumb but very messy and obfuscated process, with one useful property: at any stage it created an &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Involution_(mathematics)"&gt;involution&lt;/a&gt;, so one can use the same machine to both encrypt and decrypt. You can see little Millie demonstrating this in the video above (shot in September 2013 by yours truly).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="../bombe-front.jpg" class="align-right" src="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/bombe-front.jpg" style="width: 365.04px; height: 273.6px;"&gt;&lt;p&gt;To attack the ciphered messages, the cryptologists at Bletchley Park did not build full on computers, but instead  machines that could simulate many Enigmas in parallel (36 Enigmas per &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bombe"&gt;Turing Bombe&lt;/a&gt;). These also had extra wiring which encoded additional properties of the Enigma protocol. On any given day, around 200 of these machines were used to recover the common settings for all the encrypted messages sent that day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What has always fascinated me with Blecthley Park is the &lt;strong&gt;subtle interplay between humans and the machines&lt;/strong&gt;. While the heavy computations were done by those Bombes, the British did not seek/manage to automate everything. Some steps were always left to manual labor, most notably message passing and picking the initial input. The initial input was known as a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cryptanalysis_of_the_Enigma#Crib-based_decryption"&gt;crib&lt;/a&gt;, and  is essentially an informed guess at partial plain text. It seems to have always been more of an art than a science to obtain, even involving some psychology to know where to look. By message passing, I mean that Bletchley Park was not just a bunch of machines: these were disconnected, so there had to actually be many people transcribing output from one machine, making relatively simple decisions (all lights lit!) and entering that output into the next machine. There were several good reasons to do it this way. It is easier to train staff than build a new and complex sorting machine. On top, war is messy, and the Germans changed their procedures several times, requiring agility in the workflow (the Germans were less likely to change their hardware). Over the course of the war, there was constant prototyping of different workflows around core mechanical infrastructure, and this experience helped abstract the generic modern computer (formally, a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turing_machine"&gt;Turing Machine&lt;/a&gt;) and eventually build it (unlike Charles Babbage's machine and Ada Lovelace's programs which remained theoretical).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The lesson of Bletchley Park is that it is sometimes easier but sufficient to build a social machine rather than a fully automated machine.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social_machine"&gt;social machine&lt;/a&gt; is an environment comprising humans and technology interacting and producing outputs or action which would not be possible without both parties present. The term became popular thanks to Tim Berners-Lee, who anticipated them along with the World Wide Web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="../bombe-back.jpg" class="align-left" src="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/bombe-back.jpg" style="width: 365.04px; height: 273.6px;"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Facebook, for instance, serves as a social machine in multiple ways. You can pass on content to your friends, which they can "like" and comment on, they can tag you in pictures, etc. Every such action is logged, and this machine has a unique goal: to know you better and serve you more valuable ads. All the necessary information has to be volunteered by humans because machines would not have been able to guess it on their own. Sometimes this social machine actively uses your friends to disclose information you might have wanted to keep private, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.digitaltrends.com/social-media/what-exactly-is-a-facebook-shadow-profile/#!bP6C2L"&gt;even if you are not a Facebook user!&lt;/a&gt; Kids ratting on their parents, in other words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How is this relevant to ed tech? One of the most successful social machines in education is &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://duolingo.com"&gt;Duolingo&lt;/a&gt;. While it offers students the option of learning a language, it is really built with the intention of translating the web, and uses a creative setup to find and motivate participants. Even the course creation is now crowdsourced, via its &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://incubator.duolingo.com/"&gt;incubator&lt;/a&gt;. MOOCs actually tend to rely heavily on the same type of crowdsourcing. Course creation is crowdsourced to &lt;strong&gt;professors, who can create custom social machines tailored to the topic at hand&lt;/strong&gt;. When the course is run, this machine collects information about who is a good student, who is bad, who is a deep thinker, who is meticulous, who defines their own path, etc. Eventually, the goal might be to evaluate all these characteristics at scale algorithmically (despite all the risks for algorithmic bias that this entails), but the key point is that it can be "faked" at first: via peer feedback and rubric grading, one can use power relationships to inject fairly complicated judgements into this machine, at scale, with little cost.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, other relatively complex MOOC services are also sometimes crowdsourced, such as translating course materials, or mutual technical support for the professors and students. One can expect that some of these tasks will eventually also be automated: for instance, some MOOC platforms already use intelligent agents (robots masquerading as humans) to answer student questions in the forums.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
MOOC platforms offer the option to professors to easily stand up their own social machines. What should be their purpose? Who should be responsible for them?&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watters insist that Luddites were not rejecting technology, but rather rejecting exploitation. Crowdsourcing already carries significant risks of exploitation, particularly in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://florianschmidt.co/the-good-the-bad-and-the-ugly/"&gt;domain of intellectual property&lt;/a&gt;, but this is not the only one. In another talk, she says that &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://hackeducation.com/2013/10/17/student-data-is-the-new-oil/"&gt;"Student data is the new oil"&lt;/a&gt;. Indeed, this seems to be another path that all the big MOOC providers have chosen so far. A professor building a MOOC only helps the platform collect more private information about its users, maybe even under the guise of improving their user experience. But for what purpose exactly? Which engine is running off this oil? Where is it headed? Is this data helping for research in education? In social science? In human-computer interaction? Or simply for profit, selling that data to the highest bidder/best revenue model, without moral guidance? All these options are actively pursued right now, sometimes simultaneously, and professors preparing a MOOC should give great pause to these issues and think carefully at the setting where they have decided to do so. Possibly they might have to fight for the luxury of picking this setting. Professors have a lot of moral responsibility towards the students (the weakest cogs by far in this social machine), to make sure that the free-education-for-all mantra does not turn into another form of exploitation. Do these professors even fully understand the situation? Do they fully understand how &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ldhHkVjLe7A"&gt;free-is-a-lie&lt;/a&gt;? Who carries the responsibility of informing them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Research conducted without applied ethics is morally bankrupt because when scientists lack morals, outside sources can more easily manipulate their work for destructive purposes. In such situations, scientists are likely to adopt the rationalizations of that party to justify their efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ashbrook.org/publications/respub-v8n1-cook/"&gt;Erica Cook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Bletchley Park analogy, this moral responsibility is eclipsed by the dramatic circumstances of war. One person encodes, the other one decodes, some people die, some survive but at least it feels fair (to me at least, maybe blinded by my mathematicians' background). Yet the parallels outlined above remain as strong with Los Alamos and the atomic bomb, where Feynman was reorganising his own social machine to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://youtu.be/0ogSC6JKkrY?t=47m50s"&gt;perform simulations of atomic explosions&lt;/a&gt;, even holding competitions pitting his chimeric machine against actual IBM computers. Certainly, the ethical questions are more nagging with Los Alamos, but on either side of the Atlantic the machine operators never had the opportunity to raise concerns with what they were contributing to. In an environment full of (male) generals and (male) scientists the machines were mostly &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.mkheritage.co.uk/bpt/Women/wrensOS.html"&gt;"manned" by women&lt;/a&gt;, within a society that didn't even pretend to give them an equal voice. After the war, many ethical question &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ashbrook.org/publications/respub-v8n1-cook/"&gt;hung squarely  and solely on the scientists' shoulders&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if we don't like the current MOOC models, what should be the way forward?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Luddites were seeking to disrupt the technological disruption, and we as professors should seek to do the same.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, one might argue this is part of our job, to help society move forward without fear of a challenge, criticism or controversy, as long as we can back our arguments with evidence. In today's conversation, business logic has misappropriated the words &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clayton_M._Christensen"&gt;"disruption" and "innovation"&lt;/a&gt; and mostly tied them with technology. In fact, disruption is to be found anywhere in academia, if not more in the humanities: "why?" is a more powerful question than "how?". Certainly some MOOC providers have opened themselves up to this disruption themselves, through &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ODL-owGjti8"&gt;overinflated claims of fixing with old technology something that was not necessarily broken&lt;/a&gt;. MOOCs are a fantastic opportunity to build truly new ways of learning, collaborating, discovering and generally helping society progress through exchange of information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Getting these improved MOOCs off the ground will be hard. It will require dedication, transparency, freedom to tinker, accountability and tolerance for failure. Above all, it will require rock solid ethical ground, which is too easy to compromise in a competitive environment mixing academia and its "strategic relationships".&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>connected_course</category><category>crypto</category><category>edtech</category><category>social_machine</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/social-teaching-machines.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 04 Sep 2014 00:46:03 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>