<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>paulolivier.dehaye.org (mathematics)</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/</link><description></description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2016 10:52:58 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Activating mathematical knowledge</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/activating-mathematical-knowledge.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;In 2011, when I applied to my current position as Swiss National Science Foundation Assistant Professor, I included an &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/Annex_Dehaye.pdf"&gt;Annex&lt;/a&gt; to the proposal, titled &lt;em&gt;Making data useful for mathematical collaboratories and the example of the LMFDB project&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;collaboratory&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/activating-mathematical-knowledge.html#id2" id="id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; is an organizational entity that spans distance, supports rich and recurring human interaction oriented to a common research area, and fosters contact between researchers who are both known and unknown to each other, and provides access to data sources, artifacts, and tools required to accomplish research tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://soc.ics.uci.edu/"&gt;Science of Collaboratories&lt;/a&gt;, SNF survey 2007&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END: (Click to read the rest of the article) --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Already then, I highlighted a significant evolution in mentalities since a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://soc.ics.uci.edu/"&gt;reference SNF survey&lt;/a&gt; of 2007. This trend was explained by Michael Nielsen in a TED talk at around the same time, also taking mathematics as basis for many of his examples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;iframe width="425" height="344" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/DnWocYKqvhw?rel=0&amp;amp;hd=1&amp;amp;wmode=transparent"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the Annex, I make a distinction between &lt;em&gt;horizontal&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;vertical&lt;/em&gt; projects. &lt;cite&gt;Horizontal projects&lt;/cite&gt; are more infrastructure-like, &lt;cite&gt;with a wider mathematical audience, essentially the whole pure mathematical community&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
I would expect this difficulty in integrating new data to be the main cause of the lack of mathematical collaboratories. As such, it should be solved as a horizontal rather than vertical problem. From now on, I only discuss this problem, i.e. the creation of a flexible and coherent mathematical database starting from heterogenous data.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pushed to the extreme, one could see this problem as &lt;cite&gt;integrating all compiled knowledge in mathematics&lt;/cite&gt;, echoing a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/paul-bernays-lectures-at-eth-zurich.html#"&gt;description by Voevodsky&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was based around my experience for a few years with the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.lmfdb.org"&gt;LMFDB project&lt;/a&gt;, which is aimed at integrating lots of mathematical data in the general area of L-functions (two of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Millennium_Prize_Problems"&gt;Clay Millenium problems&lt;/a&gt; are in this area, the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Riemann_hypothesis"&gt;Riemann Hypothesis&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Birch_and_Swinnerton-Dyer_conjecture"&gt;Birch and Swinnerton-Dyer conjecture&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One interesting aspect of this annex is that it was, well, an annex. I knew including this as part of my main project could actually be hurtful and judged distracting to my main research proposal, since many of the ideas of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ec.europa.eu/research/consultations/science-2.0/consultation_en.htm"&gt;Science 2.0&lt;/a&gt; had not taken hold yet. Indeed, the Annex comes with a big disclaimer:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
I have also described my more personal project, which is concerned with the integration of mathematical data for collaboratories. While I do not consider this project a mathematical project, I think it could be of great value to research in mathematics in general. I intend on pursuing it on the side as a service to the community, just as paper refereeing, outreach, CAS development, etc. I am only mentioning it here because of its (presumed) originality and wide audience.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One year later, I coorganised a workshop at Edinburgh. The topic was &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://aimath.org/pastworkshops/onlinedata.html"&gt;Online databases: from L-functions to combinatorics&lt;/a&gt;, and it was meant to start unifying two separate areas in this horizontal problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id2" rules="none"&gt;
&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;
&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/activating-mathematical-knowledge.html#id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;A &lt;em&gt;portmanteau&lt;/em&gt; of collaboration and laboratory.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;</description><category>mathematics</category><category>social_machine</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/activating-mathematical-knowledge.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2014 23:26:35 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Foundations of mathematics</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/paul-bernays-lectures-at-eth-zurich.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;img alt="../bernays.jpg" class="align-right" src="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/bernays.jpg" style="width: 177.0px; height: 237.0px;"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ETH Zurich hosts every year the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.gess.ethz.ch/news/pbl"&gt;Paul Bernays lectures&lt;/a&gt;. This the type of lecture where people expect a Nobel prize winner to show up. Well, unless it is a mathematics one (the topic rotates among a few sciences), in which case it is OK if the speaker only has a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fields_Medal"&gt;Fields medal&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, it was the latter. The speaker was &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vladimir_Voevodsky"&gt;Vladimir Voevodsky&lt;/a&gt; from the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Institute_for_Advanced_Study"&gt;Institute for Advanced Study&lt;/a&gt; in Princeton (the same institute where Einstein and many other brilliant scientists were coopted following great successes).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voevodsky's initial success was in proving the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milnor_conjecture"&gt;Milnor conjecture&lt;/a&gt;, but he hasn't stopped there. He has announced a proof of the Bloch-Kato conjecture as well, and is now working on Homotopy Type Theory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This theory is tied to the foundations of mathematics. To the layman, it really asks deep questions about what mathematics is, and how mathematics is constructed and improved, both by computers and humans. In some ways, he is trying to scientifically map out mathematics, and during the talk suggested a 500 year horizon to do that (part of many bombastic and exciting claims made by very smart mathematicians, such as Thomas Hales at the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DJx8bFQbHsA"&gt;end of his lecture here&lt;/a&gt;, who are willing to challenge the statu quo). Of course, one needs to start "small", and this is what Voevodsky explained in Zurich, his vision of the &lt;em&gt;Foundations of Mathematics&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this he had three times one hour, which he sensibly divided into: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/vladimirias/2014_Paul_Bernays_Lectures/blob/master/2014_09_Bernays_1%20presentation.pdf?raw=true"&gt;past&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/vladimirias/2014_Paul_Bernays_Lectures/blob/master/2014_09_Bernays_2%20presentation.pdf?raw=true"&gt;present&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/vladimirias/2014_Paul_Bernays_Lectures/blob/master/2014_09_Bernays_3%20presentation.pdf?raw=true"&gt;future&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to focus here on the "past" talk. He started it by quoting wikipedia's definition of &lt;em&gt;Foundations of Mathematics&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="../wikipedia-foundations.jpg" class="align-center" src="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/wikipedia-foundations.jpg" style="width: 616.5px; height: 236.0px;"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and highlighted that there were two parts to this definition: the &lt;em&gt;mathematical concepts&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;metamathematical concepts&lt;/em&gt; (the &lt;em&gt;structures that form the language&lt;/em&gt;). He then went on to explain the presence of this dichotomy through the ages: discrete vs. continuous, pure vs. applied,  theorem vs. problem (&lt;em&gt;an inquiry the
answer to which is a construction of an object&lt;/em&gt;), and eventually touched on this account of what mathematics is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="../grassmann.jpg" class="align-center" src="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/grassmann.jpg" style="width: 617.5px; height: 308.5px;"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Voevodsky's interpretation of what Grassmann is saying is thus: &lt;strong&gt;mathematics is seen as rising from many independent roots and acquiring wholeness only through the intertwining of the lines arising from these roots&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>foundations</category><category>mathematics</category><category>rhizo14</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/paul-bernays-lectures-at-eth-zurich.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 13 Sep 2014 19:44:20 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>