<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>paulolivier.dehaye.org (mooc)</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/</link><description></description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2014 14:21:24 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>MOOCs as inventions #chals14</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/moocs-as-inventions-chals14.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I just finished giving my talk on &lt;em&gt;MOOCs as inventions: opportunities and risks&lt;/em&gt; in Goteborg, at the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/search?f=realtime&amp;amp;q=%23chals14&amp;amp;src=typd"&gt;#chals14&lt;/a&gt; meeting. This is a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.facebook.com/chals14?fref=ts"&gt;reunion of Swedish universities&lt;/a&gt; convened by Jonas Gilbert (Chalmers University Library) to discuss MOOCs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My slides are available &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/goteborg-final.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the talk, I discussed the idea that MOOCs are &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social_machine"&gt;social machines&lt;/a&gt; put in the hands of professors (thanks to my PhD student &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.math.uzh.ch/index.php?id=assistenten&amp;amp;L=&amp;amp;key1=4144&amp;amp;key2=&amp;amp;key3=&amp;amp;keySemId="&gt;Helen Riedtmann&lt;/a&gt; for boiling down my ideas to this simple statement), and quoted Evgeny Morozov, which I am reading at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In retrospect, it was much better to be last speaker of the morning, to offer a (hopefully constructive) balance to some of the other points made earlier. It also lead naturally to interesting discussions (including with &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.chalmers.se/en/about-chalmers/the-president-and-vice-presidents/Pages/karin-markides-president.aspx"&gt;Karin Markides&lt;/a&gt;, who asked me a few questions above my pay grade. It is much easier to convey these ideas offline than online, but indeed the audience is smaller and different).  Still, the digital world was interesting too: I was glad to see how Twitter added to the talk &lt;strong&gt;for me&lt;/strong&gt; afterwards (something I am not used to, since very few mathematicians use Twitter), since it helped me assess how my ideas were received. In a talk about MOOCs' risks and opportunities, someone immediately called me up on the risks of the opportunities, with a reference to Jaron Lanier:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/chals14?src=hash"&gt;#chals14&lt;/a&gt; The social machine; I wonder what Jaron Lanier would say about that. Read "You are not a gadget" for a critical take in this.&lt;/p&gt;— Thommy Eriksson (@KuggenMedialab) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/KuggenMedialab/status/514714933813338113"&gt;September 24, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;p&gt;Now adding this to my reading list, since in fact he seems to talk a lot about mathematics too! It was also good to meet &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://jorg.pareigis.se/"&gt;J&amp;amp;ouml;rg Pareigis&lt;/a&gt;, a fellow &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/search?f=realtime&amp;amp;q=%23ccourses&amp;amp;src=typd"&gt;#ccourses participant&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two quick mementos for myself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;&lt;li&gt;I have now traveled to the first 15 countries to constitute the European Union.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have never been before in such last minute trouble with computers: still private Google Slides locked out of my account, requiring Google two-factor authentication through a dead cell phone... Literally managed to get to the slide as I was walking to the stand.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description><category>connected_course</category><category>coursera</category><category>mooc</category><category>social_machine</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/moocs-as-inventions-chals14.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2014 11:39:41 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>