<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>paulolivier.dehaye.org (privacy)</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/</link><description></description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2015 11:54:19 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Student privacy in the digital age</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/student-privacy-in-the-digital-age.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today, US President Obama is due to call for laws covering student privacy. To quote the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/01/12/us/politics/obama-to-call-for-laws-covering-data-hacking-and-student-privacy.html"&gt;New York Times&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The president will also propose the Student Data Privacy Act, which would prohibit technology firms from profiting from information collected in schools as teachers adopt tablets, online services and Internet-connected software, officials said.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is an interesting development, very much top-down. The reality on the ground is that tech companies can do just about anything they want with student data. For instance, they can casually diss existing regulations. Quoting the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://chronicle.com/article/Are-MOOC-Takers-Students-/150325/"&gt;Chronicle of Higher Education&lt;/a&gt;  (December 3rd 2014):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Coursera, by contrast, does not believe federal student-privacy laws apply to MOOCs, according to Vivek Goel, the company’s chief academic strategist. But the company does follow the "principles" of Ferpa when handling the data of its users, according to Mr. Goel.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that noone cares what Goel "believes": this quote only constitutes a personal commitment, he is replaceable, and indeed had left Coursera within a month of that statement. It also matters very little whether Coursera follows the principles of FERPA now. Voluntary compliance in the present, while not tapping into one of your intended revenue streams, is very different from promised regulatory compliance in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obama's proposal is also bound to leave many shady areas in a field that is evolving very fast. One of the main questions would concern non-US students in MOOCs, at a time when &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://getpocket.com/a/read/813428833"&gt;Asia is emerging as the World's edtech laboratory&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/Buttarelli_G/status/443641146816729088"&gt;choices made in Europe will have a lasting impact on issues surrounding privacy&lt;/a&gt; (Buttarelli is European Data Protection Supervisor). This will fit into a larger struggle re-defining modern privacy laws, when data flows become crucial to national security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, it is my belief that these issues also need bottom-up approaches. For this reason, in October 2014 I filed a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/how-to-file-a-safe-harbor-request-for-your-personal-data.html"&gt;Safe Harbor request with Coursera&lt;/a&gt;. Safe Harbor is a program that authorises US companies to conduct business with EU based companies, provided they offer guarantees concerning data protection. This certification is a &lt;em&gt;sine qua non&lt;/em&gt; if Coursera wants to conduct business with EU-based universities. Under this program, any user has the right to request access to their data. Indeed, a couple weeks later (after sorting through several issues), Coursera did send me some of my data. However, this data was incomplete and partly inaccurate. In addition, it did not provide much light on what Coursera intends to do with this data. In reaction, back in December, I filed a second Safe Harbor request, asking many questions concerning their intentions with this data. Since Coursera still has not responded to those questions, I decided today to initiate the next step of this procedure: in accordance with &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://safeharbor.export.gov/companyinfo.aspx?id=26126"&gt;Coursera's filing at the Federal Trade Commission&lt;/a&gt;, I have contacted the recourse mechanism, i.e. the International Center for Dispute Resolution division of the American Arbitration Association.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have also notified the FTC, the Data Protection Officers at the Swiss cantonal and federal levels, as well as three EU parliamentarians: Julia Reda, Marietje Schaake and Jan Albrecht.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>coursera</category><category>privacy</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/student-privacy-in-the-digital-age.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2015 09:59:23 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Tequila, U.S. surveillance and me</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/tequila-us-surveillance-and-me.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Do we all have something to hide? Hopefully so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My life was scheduled to change on September 12th 2001. I was supposed to move to the US, through New York, to study at Stanford for my PhD. That didn't happen, of course. The day before, as I was saying goodbyes to friends at home, we watched horrific images on television. We learned through the TV ticker tape that all transatlantic flights were grounded. I remember staying in bed for the whole week after that, sick from egoistic stress: it felt as if World War III was about to erupt, and I was moving across the world in the middle of all that. Still, in the days that followed, I tried day after day to get a seat on a plane so I could move on time for my classes. Eventually, I flew in on September 17th, still routed through New York. I remember feeling relief when we took off. When we arrived though, we circled around the long plume of smoke and I felt overwhelmed with what had actually happened. Around me, all the passengers were New York residents, sobbing as they discovered the changed landscape of their city.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I flew on, and landed in California. Like everyone else, I rushed to buy a bike after realising how humongous the campus is. I remember making all the efforts to settle in: social security number, campus card, bank account, etc. Bought a phone and all the other dorm essentials. The general impression (on campus) was that the "events" were an East Coast thing, still far from the relatively peaceful West. Anyways, there was little time to reflect: it was the first week of classes, where I quickly understood how hard my first year would be leading up to my qualification exams. It was my 20th birthday that week. The older grad students had organised a party at the end of the first week, so I celebrated with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END: (Click to read the rest of this post) --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I had never drunk tequila. And even less so the el cheapo Walmart kind. After 2-3 shots, I was tired and ready to walk home, pushing my bike. I didn't make it though: on the way, in Escondido Village (the grad student residences), I collapsed. From drunkeness, sure, but also exhaustion, stress, hunger and immaturity, having never lived outside of the parental cocoon. And that's when the Stanford campus police showed up. They had been called for another party, but found me sitting there, next to my bike. They started giving me all the sobriety tests, while I was just asking for them to let me go home. Eventually they arrested me, and slapped the charge of resisting arrest on top (even though that "resistance" was only verbal, as confirmed to me later by witnesses). This allowed them to bring me to the "drunk tank", unfortunately located in San Jose, a good 50 miles away. This was actually next to the big real jail, which I got to see from the inside in the morning when I was released (presumably to impress the "nightly" residents like me, so they would not be tempted to come back for a longer stay). Waiting outside that Sunday morning was a long rank of taxicabs, each driver coming with a good dose of psychology to help reorient their clients in society. Where was I? What time is it? Etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;California: California Penal Code 647(f) considers public intoxication a misdemeanor. The code describes public intoxication as someone who displays intoxication to liquor, drugs, controlled substances or toluene and demonstrates an inability to care for themselves or others, or interferes or obstructs the free use of streets, sidewalks or other public way. California Penal Code 647(g) affords law enforcement the option to take an individual fitting the arrest criteria for 647(f), and no other crime, into civil protective custody if a "sobering facility" is available. Essentially, the detainee agrees to remain at the location until the facility's staff consents to their departure; usually after four hours and upon the belief that the detainee is safe to look after themselves. Not every municipality in California has such a facility. Also, if a person is being combative and/or is under the influence of drugs, they will be taken to jail. Unlike a person who is taken to jail, a civil detainee under 647(g) is not later prosecuted in a court of law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_intoxication"&gt;California code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more damaging consequence is that I now had a court date. It was a pretty bad situation to be in: the cops had slapped on an extra charge, so they were clearly hostile. Did they make up anything in the extended written report for the judge? I could not see it, unless I challenged the charge. I could do that by either hiring my own lawyer or committing to a public defender. The private lawyers I visited in Palo Alto all required deposits, since their goal would be to litigate for as long as I would pay. The public defender would not even talk to me or tell me how the cost would be defined unless I committed to that system. On top, it didn't really make sense to contest the charge: it is written very generically and includes "obstructing sidewalks" as an offense, a nice catchall for all kinds of mendicity, public drunkenness, etc. Me and my bike fit in there, if only for a few minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I called my embassy for help. They could not do anything, but from their perspective my case fit in a pattern of campus arrests over the past weeks, presumably so foreign students could be fingerprinted. I decided to plead guilty, and was promptly given a misdemeanor charge and a criminal record. This was the expected outcome, fair according to California law given the charges assigned by the campus police. The judge told me that I could wait for a year then get this expunged from my record, and to stay away from "those campus parties". For a year wherever I showed up to a party, I significantly increased the legal liability of the host (being still underaged).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the three years that followed, flying was more painful for me than the average. I learned a new word: &lt;em&gt;selectee&lt;/em&gt;. It was easy to double guess the TSA in my case: my criminal record was flagging me more often than the average foreign student from an allied country. This stopped though, around 2004. A bit later I also expunged the record, so I would not have to report it when applying for US postdocs (Harvard, for instance, has such a screening question). In the decade since, even after moving to the UK and Switzerland, I flew regularly to the U.S.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In August 2012, I got a surprise at SFO though, on my way to my PhD adviser's birthday conference. Suddenly, I was assigned for additional interrogation. I had to wait for two hours before the TSA officer talked to me. That's a long time to ask yourself why. Was it random? Was it due to my arrest 11 years earlier? For two hours I just had to sit and wait.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I finally got to talk to the officer, right away he asked me questions about my arrest. I was relieved to explain my boring story, of how I got drunk one night when I turned 20. It still confuses me why this would pop up 11 years after the fact, so blatantly this time. The officer could not tell, and when asked he told me it could happen again. It's hard for me to shake this up. How badly is TSA drowning itself in big data if that really is the basis for interrogating a traveler?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, I am writing this now on the plane, somewhere close to Greenland. In a few hours I will land at JFK. I look forward to seeing the new Freedom tower on approach, and hope its completion can bring some sense of closure to as many people as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After going through JFK immigration, I will go on to Pittsburgh to a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.humancomputation.com/2014/"&gt;Human Computation&lt;/a&gt; conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(To all academics who have found out the hard way that campus police is not there to encourage free speech)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Edit, written from JFK: there was too much fog to see the new tower at landing, and probably will be on departure to Pittsburgh. However, I had the "chance" of being selected once again. This time I had to wait for an hour, and they asked me to explain why I had been arrested in "September 2001". I did, then asked if this would happen everytime. The officer said that it would, because it is directly flagged from my fingerprints. I look forward to the day of portable scanners and what not, as well as to data transfers back to Europe.)&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>privacy</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/tequila-us-surveillance-and-me.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 01 Nov 2014 10:53:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>How to file a Safe Harbor request for your personal data</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/how-to-file-a-safe-harbor-request-for-your-personal-data.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a short practical guide for Europeans and Swiss residents to file a Safe Harbor request for their personal data from a US company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="what-is-safe-harbor"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What is Safe Harbor?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Safe_Harbor_Privacy_Principles"&gt;International Safe Harbor Privacy Principles&lt;/a&gt; are a set of regulations between the United States and either the European Union or Switzerland, which allow individuals based in those countries to claim back their personal data from US-based corporations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Copy-pasting from wikipedia, these principles must provide:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notice&lt;/strong&gt; - Individuals must be informed that their data is being collected and about how it will be used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Choice&lt;/strong&gt; - Individuals must have the option to opt out of the collection and forward transfer of the data to third parties.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Onward Transfer&lt;/strong&gt; - Transfers of data to third parties may only occur to other organizations that follow adequate data protection principles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Security&lt;/strong&gt; - Reasonable efforts must be made to prevent loss of collected information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Integrity&lt;/strong&gt; - Data must be relevant and reliable for the purpose it was collected for.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Access&lt;/strong&gt; - Individuals must be able to access information held about them, and correct or delete it if it is inaccurate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enforcement&lt;/strong&gt; - There must be effective means of enforcing these rules.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is meant to replicate a level of privacy protection similar to that enjoyed at home. Some companies implement these rules as services that you can activate yourself (like Facebook and Twitter, for instance, although some are arguing &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://europe-v-facebook.org"&gt;Facebook is not transparent enough&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END: (Click to read how to actually apply) --&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="how-to-apply"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;How to apply&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, it is really easy. I will describe the process for one company, Coursera. The first step is to look at the company's Privacy Policy. If it mentions Safe Harbor (as Coursera does), then you can proceed. It might be that the privacy policy lists an email address to contact. If not, the alternative is to go to the dedicated site of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.export.gov/safeharbor/"&gt;Federal Trade Commission&lt;/a&gt;. There are two lists there, one for &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://safeharbor.export.gov/list.aspx"&gt;U.S.-E.U data exchange&lt;/a&gt;, the other is the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://safeharbor.export.gov/swisslist.aspx"&gt;U.S.-Swiss list&lt;/a&gt;. You should then look up the relevant page. In Coursera's case , it is &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://safeharbor.export.gov/companyinfo.aspx?id=21417"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When everything goes smoothly, you should look up on that page the &lt;em&gt;Organization Contact&lt;/em&gt;. In Coursera's case, they have listed &lt;em&gt;security@coursera.org&lt;/em&gt;, which is not necessarily the best address to use. Much better seems to be &lt;em&gt;support@courserahelp.zendesk.com&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should then email that address with a very generic email wiht your demand. Here is an example, which you could cut and paste:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
To whom it may concern,

I would like to request a copy of all the personal data held by your company about me.
Please also describe what use you make of this data, and include a list of third parties with whom you are sharing it.

Sincerely yours,

XYZ
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, you should just wait for a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="what-if-i-don-t-get-what-i-want"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What if I don't get what I want?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your request might have different outcomes. I see a few possibilities:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;&lt;li&gt;you might get everything you asked for;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you might never hear back;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you might get some information, but not be satisfied.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you want to push the matter, you can always insist and argue why you should get more of the data. Private data is meant to be understood in a very broad sense under the original EU directive, and Safe Harbor should reflect that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, if this doesn't work, it's important to know that you have a recourse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Safe Harbor is based on self-enforcement: the tech company informs the FTC that it complies with the principles. As part of the filing, the company has to include an option for &lt;em&gt;Dispute Resolution&lt;/em&gt;, also listed on the site of the FTC.
In Coursera's case, they list the &lt;em&gt;International Center for Dispute Resolution division of the American Arbitration Association&lt;/em&gt; as the independent recourse mechanism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, you should google this arbitrator. For Coursera, you will quickly land at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://go.adr.org/safeharbor"&gt;this site&lt;/a&gt;, which has more information, including the fact that the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://images.go.adr.org/Web/AmericanArbitrationAssociation/%7Bfa41e5f8-52fd-407f-a380-803a4a4e1b36%7D_SafeHarbor_Fees.pdf"&gt;arbitration procedure is free (for the claimant)&lt;/a&gt;. This is not always the case, some arbitration companies require a filing fee of around $200.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have not had to go with an arbitrator yet, so I can't help you any further!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>coursera</category><category>privacy</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/how-to-file-a-safe-harbor-request-for-your-personal-data.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2014 20:48:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Extended statement on #massiveteaching (part II)</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/extended-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-ii.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;(This post is meant to be an account what happened in the Coursera course &lt;em&gt;Massive Teaching: New skills required&lt;/em&gt;. I suggest reading the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; first. This honors my commitment to trying to get the truth to my students)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="why-the-course"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why the course?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do believe that MOOCs offer many opportunities. Beyond providing educational material at a very large scale, they might for instance also help strengthen democracy or enable new discoveries. I have &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/mooc-research-proposal-using-crowdsourcing.html"&gt;submitted a grant proposal along those lines&lt;/a&gt;. Since utopian ideas often get compromised and ultimately shaped by commercial interests, I started in May 2013 to take a closer look at contracts between MOOC providers and educational institutions. Coursera was a natural choice for my focus: my university has partnered with them, they use closed source software (which increases lock-in), and they are the leading MOOC provider right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I read really bothered me, for a wide array of reasons. While the utopian vision of MOOCs (free-education-for-all) is compelling, these contracts reflect a very disturbing approach to that goal. In my opinion these contracts will have large societal implications, should they become the norm: disappearance of academic freedom, of the free agency of students, and complete disappearance of any form of privacy when learning. When I tried to communicate this around me, I encountered a clear lack of information on the subject. Getting past the utopian vision took time. Once there, many responded that my concerns were valid and worth discussing. In any case, this approach was ineffective: MOOC partnership decisions are often made by university administrations, based on factors other than those that drove my concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided that the best way to proceed was to teach a MOOC on the topic. The most natural place to do so was of course Coursera, and it also seemed natural to address the course to professors, i.e. individuals who might be able to affect decisions at their own institutions or in their local communities. It would also allow me to reach out to the more "typical" Coursera students and explain to them the contracts that are constructed around their learning. Finally, I thought it would be interesting to see the capacities at Coursera to reflect on their own practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I understand the paradox of teaching on Coursera about concerns relating to teaching on Coursera, but made the calculation that the benefits outweigh the costs in this case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END: (Click to read the rest of the statement) --&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="timeline-of-preparation-and-structure-of-the-course"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Timeline of preparation and structure of the course&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The course was approved by Coursera mid-April. The Quality Assurance Protocol at Coursera requires the first two weeks of material to be uploaded ahead of the beginning of the course. The third week (and later) can be uploaded at the last minute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In consequence, I structured the course &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1xnBH0JDaU8"&gt;in the following way&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;&lt;li&gt;week 1: pedagogy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;week 2: technology and copyright&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;week 3: business model, science fiction (utopia/dystopia), unresolved questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;In other words, the first two weeks were conceived to provide background for the third week, which would be quite critical of MOOC contracts. I didn't hide from Coursera or the students that I would be critical, and used the flexibility offered by Coursera not to provide the third week material ahead of time. There were several reasons for this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;&lt;li&gt;The MOOC world changes fast. In the three weeks before the course started, two comprehensive reports came out on MOOCs. I also &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/what-i-am-doing-with-moocs-and-why-june-2nd.html"&gt;attended two conferences on MOOCs, and was co-organiser of one&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I knew there was a risk that Coursera would shut down the course, either directly or indirectly. Coursera did drag their feet more and more in the lead up to the course. I attribute that to the realisation of the extent of what I wanted to say, but they could easily chalk it to other reasons.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;I conceived simple videos to illustrate concepts (like an illustrated glossary), but did not mean for this to constitute the whole course. The videos would be accompanied by readings and forum interactions. Of course, I recognised that students could still desire different levels of interactions, and I was fine with this diversity. Also, this course was meant to be &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1xnBH0JDaU8"&gt;very responsive to evolutions in the MOOC world in its later runs&lt;/a&gt;, which explains why the videos are relatively condensed and interchangeable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of the openness of the topic, I tried as much as possible not to give the impression of a "full course". This meant that it did not deliver either a Statement of Accomplishment or a Verified Certificate. Due to the Coursera contracts, I was still required to deliver a numerical grade at the end (which couldn't be 0% for all or 100% for all). I tentatively settled for a bland peer-feedback assessment, as I thought this would be more useful than a multiple choice quiz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, I prepared some "experiments" through the course forums. The term is very confusing: these were not scientific or social experiments, but clearly advertised and explained attempts to talk with the students, get the students to engage with the content and interact with each other and advance the state-of-the-art in collaborative tools in MOOCs. Unfortunately I have now lost electronic access to the course material itself, so I cannot relay the exact wording used to explain this to the students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="first-week-of-the-course"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;First week of the course&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first week of the course went according to me quite well, although it was exhausting: I interacted and welcomed dozens of students on the forum, orientated them, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition, I participated with the students in the "experiments" that I had prepared:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;&lt;li&gt;I had defined a process to manage the forums based on their preferences (like &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://area51.stackexchange.com/"&gt;Area 51 on Stack Exchange&lt;/a&gt;), but this had to be scrapped (lack of interest) and turned instead into a listing of desired features in forums;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One student initiated a wide survey of MOOC students by MOOC students, that I encouraged;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I decided to attempt to build a badging system (Open Badges is an infrastructure that allows the cryptographically secure attribution of rewards for contributions and achievements, however small or big). This was done in response to Coursera's requirement for a grade, and because I thought it would be very effective at shifting power towards the students/professors relationship rather than the universities/MOOC platforms. In my mind these badges would be based around the forums, and aim to make the final outcome more meaningful to each individual student (via student-defined badges granted through peer-feedback and certified by the instructor). This could have been achieved in this iteration or more realistically in a later iteration of the course, based on interactions already happening in the first run. In any case, this required looking a bit deeper into the kind of data collected on students (or at least the fraction of that data that was accessible to me as an instructor). To give an example, I would need to be able to see how an upvote was encoded, and whether there would be a way to retrieve useful information from that. I asked Coursera for an anonymized database dump taken &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; the course properly started, with some forums seeded with test data (generated by me and another instructor account). When I asked to share parts of this dump with the students (even in a sanitized version with synthetic data), in the interest of transparency, it was refused. Throughout Coursera dragged their feet, which only encouraged me to dig deeper: I was also forbidden to share the supporting documentation PDFs, and my request to share those refusal emails with the students was never answered.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;During the first week, some students also started Facebook and Google Plus groups associated to the course, unprompted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the start of the course, I also used confusion as a teaching tool, by sometimes acting a bit randomly but in non obtrusive ways. This was done to expose hidden assumptions, and incite reactions, which in a MOOC would be numerous and were likely to be contradictory and diverse. I saw this as conducive to questioning of the instructor himself (i.e. me, an individual having signed contracts unknown to the students) and therefore to exploratory learning, especially with my intended audience of professors. I realise this is quite bold, but I merely saw this as an extreme transposition to the web of the Socratic method. Since this concerned purely my teaching methods and did not involve any research component, I did not make a formal announcement about this, but was overt at the start, for instance by opening a thread with title "?". This lead one student to answer 42, then another to give an equation. Other students wrote poems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would love to debate the value of this technique, particularly when the goal is partly to push students to turn a critical eye towards an opaque and complex legal and technical construction such as Coursera, under various restrictions on the content. Bear also in mind that students were at any point free to leave. Some certainly did but many stayed. I was also hoping that the combinatorics of the peer-feedback exercise at the end would tie loose ends at scale and cement the efficacy of the technique (since it is my suspicion that a comment such as "I am still confused by..." is more likely to elicit constructive responses from peers than "I assert this and that...").&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="second-week-of-the-course"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Second week of the course&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social aspects of learning are currently completely unstructured and relatively weak on MOOC platforms, so a natural next step for them is to build some form of social network for students. Whatever form it takes (decentralised around each course, for instance), it will require extensive research unlikely to be done by the university partners since it will be core to the MOOC platforms. Concerning research practices, Facebook and Coursera have very similar, open-ended, Terms of Use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the first weekend of the course (June 29th?), the Facebook Emotion study made news: Facebook had manipulated the newsfeeds of many users, trying to selectively induce either happiness or sadness. The news coverage was extremely confusing: many academics were outraged at the lack of IRB approval, while others were unsurprised at these commercial practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having read Coursera Terms of Use, I knew right away that similar abuses could take place there, and had many reasons to think not enough safeguards were in place at Coursera either. I very quickly saw the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/erosion-of-thick-legitimacy-by-coursera.html"&gt;pernicious threat that Coursera's business model and practices represent to the thick legitimacy of instructors, researchers and universities&lt;/a&gt;, and ultimately to society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over and above this, I knew that data collected on the Coursera platform has no expiration date, can be replayed at will and that it had not been welcoming of my own transparency effort. In that sense, there was a more immediate concern, towards my students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike all the material I had prepared for week 3, which was researched and based on documents available to the general public (i.e. not derived from the Quality Assurance process, the Coursera Partners' Portal or private communication), any comment of mine linking ethics of experimenting at Coursera to ethics of experimenting at Facebook would have to be speculative at the time. Making this speculation public would expose me to the risk of a legal challenge. Continuing the course would put more ethical responsibility on me since I could not be fully transparent with the students, as I had been thus far. To add to all of this, all the unresolved ethical questions led me to question the wisdom of implementing the badging experimentation within Coursera itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started questioning the ethics of delivering a course in those conditions. I could not escape thinking along the lines of nested Stanford Experiment (Should I promote some students to Community TA? What are the other 599 courses doing?). Whatever I could think of doing I somehow could find a darker side as well, associating it to one of the studies that I had read in preparing the course. I became confused, but at a much deeper level: under all these adverse conditions, I should probably have decided to stop the course, even if doing so exposed me to legal risk. Instead, I pressed on, and resolved to deliver the rest of the course via Twitter and Youtube instead (while the willing students would support each other through the Facebook and Google Plus groups as well). I made no decision about the third week peer-feedback exam. Of course, in doing all this, I also confused the students to this much deeper level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For somewhere between 24 and 48 hours, I improvised and set out to prepare material on Twitter to support my upcoming explanations. Some of it was also intentionally confounding, likely to be misunderstood by anyone who was not involved in the course, but easily explainable with the proper context (Coursera repeatedly ignored requests to engage with me in a more public way within the course). In my (poor) judgement, confusion could be used to expose hidden assumptions through reactions of other parties. For instance, I knew this might lead Coursera to stop the course, which was fine with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another "subtext" of my tweets was the risk of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://socialmediacollective.org/2014/06/26/corrupt-personalization/"&gt;corrupt personalisation&lt;/a&gt; (June 26th) in teaching, originating from &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/niftyc/archives/975"&gt;algorithmic culture&lt;/a&gt;. I thought it would be interesting to show this to students, centered around the World Cup taking place at the same time (Twitter, for the duration of the World Cup, offered the opportunity to do your own A/B testing by selecting which team you wanted to support).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet another plan was to continue the course as a Twitter based game, that could involve participants external to the course as well. Setting it up as a game would allow me to imply things without properly saying them, diffusing some of the legal risk away from myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realise these are many options, but they did not need all to work and stick. And I knew I would be more free to explain them once the course finished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When ready, on Wednesday, I removed all content and forums, except for one forum. I also pinned one student post with an encouragement to fellow students to take ownership of their learning and join the Google Plus group associated to the course (in fact, this post is what triggered me to do this at that exact time). I removed video content because I wanted to encourage students who only watch video to consult the forums and notice that something was happening beyond business as usual. At the time I still felt very wary of the final peer-feedback exercise, and did not want these students to suddenly feel cheated. I intended to explain my actions on the very limited space I had left on the Coursera forums, at the best I could within my legal constraints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As the atmosphere had evolved between Monday and Wednesday, it was clear to me that students would be critical of switching from Coursera to another web platform. Again, this was fine as I could point them to the numerous Terms of Use I had read in preparation of the course, and show them contradictions in their own reasonings about privacy, and overreliance on sales pitches. I had already started highlighting the social network aspect of Coursera on Sunday or Monday, and ultimately wanted students to treat all those options on an equal footing, and make critical choices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Twitter and Youtube afford advantages that were required for me to be able to continue with the course content originally planned (hyperlinking to specific second or Tweet), while not requiring any login to consume passively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="fallout"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Fallout&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this stage (Wednesday), I was given a 24 hour deadline by Coursera to reinstate the content on their servers. This request arrived at 12:30 AM my time. When I woke up, I asked my university for ethical guidance through one channel.  Before I could consult with my university, by 11AM, I was removed as an instructor and Coursera engineers started reinstating content in a suspiciously selective fashion, reeking of sanctioned censorship (part of the contracts is that the instructor has to sign away rights to modify the material).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once my Coursera instructor rights were removed, in the interest of transparency, I immediately explained to the students what was going on through an etherpad document (for increased interactivity, still feeling under legal threat). Agreeing to a student request, I encouraged participants in that etherpad chat to share the document with the whole class. I also posted on the course forums and at the time I could not see that all my posts were being systematically deleted. I still do not know by whom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Confusingly, some students still received e-mail notifications of my messages, and they started to suspect I was deleting them myself. In parallel, there was increasing speculation on the blogosphere that I was performing some form of social experiment. New students were not allowed to sign up, so newcomers had little access to information about what had happened in the course itself. This fed an increased paranoia of some students against me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite all these misunderstandings, I was forbidden to clarify the situation with my students or the press. Later, I learned of misleading and false accusations made by Coursera to my university, and that Coursera used browsing behaviour information to support some of their claims.
I also learned that Coursera had issued legal threats against my university and was told that my own legal situation was precarious. Coursera temporarily suspended their agreement with my university. My assessment is that Coursera has so far successfully manipulated the media, my university and the students to damage my credibility and introduce doubts about my integrity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="summary"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I regret the breakdown of trust that occurred during the preparation of the course between Coursera and me, since this left me with no good option when an external event (the Facebook Emotion experiment) disrupted my course plan. I think Coursera's actions after I removed the content, such as deleting my messages or misleading journalists and my university, caused undue stress to the students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can fully understand the perspective of students who would feel cheated or manipulated in some way since so much information was hidden away from them. I tried my best to convey that a lot was going on behind the scenes (and clearly said so many times, referring explicitly to contracts and denied requests for data transparency).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, it feels like I have missed a chance to raise this debate and others more constructively. This is unfortunate since there are many more issues and opportunities of MOOCs I would have wanted to discuss in the third week:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;&lt;li&gt;intellectual property for professors and associated labor issues (cf. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ucscfa.org/2013/06/scfas-ongoing-discussion-concerning-ucscs-contract-with-coursera/"&gt;UCSC Faculty union resistance to Coursera&lt;/a&gt; );&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reportedly bad working conditions in the Coursera Global Translator Community, and the risks of crowdsourcing more components of teaching (Community TAs or alumni-led tutoring, for instance);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"partner"-walling of information in the Coursera Partner Portal that should be public (such as general best practices around MOOCs, data practices, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/thin-legitimacy-at-whisper-facebook-and-coursera.html"&gt;discussion around IRBs&lt;/a&gt; etc);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eJovz6IVzFU"&gt;vendor lock-in vs free/open source software&lt;/a&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.worklearn.org"&gt;merging of labour and educational markets, through crowdsourcing&lt;/a&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;technical interoperability of MOOC certificates;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;corrupt personalisation of educational experiences;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;erosion of academic freedom on commercial MOOC platforms;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;interactions &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://hci.uwaterloo.ca/faculty/elaw/citizenx/program.html"&gt;between MOOCs and citizen science or open democracies projects&lt;/a&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course, I missed a chance, but any of the other 103 Coursera partners, of which 25 or so are European or Swiss, have the option of starting a course on the same topics. I think it is very much needed: the shared interest of students and academics is to discuss these issues directly together at scale, without channeling this interaction through an intermediate corporation with obvious monetary interest. It is not clear that that many students are actually aware of any of those issues, highlighting the need for an urgent intervention on the topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I realise I have not answered all the questions or concerns that people might have about the course. The comment section is below, feel free to use it!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>coursera</category><category>ethics</category><category>massive_teaching</category><category>mooc</category><category>privacy</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/extended-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-ii.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2014 22:00:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Statement on #massiveteaching (part I)</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;(For a more extended statement, see &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/extended-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-ii.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My name is Paul-Olivier Dehaye, I am a mathematics professor at the University of Zurich. On June 23rd 2014, I started to teach a MOOC on Coursera, called &lt;em&gt;Teaching goes massive: New skills required&lt;/em&gt;, which was intended to last for three weeks and include a component on business practices of MOOC providers. During the course delivery, my perception of the ethical issues surrounding the course changed, which led me to alter its delivery methods. This prompted a reaction by Coursera itself, and I was censored &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html#id8" id="id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. In the fallout, I was also insulted and vilified online. Coursera used intentionally misleading information and deeply intrusive data held about the course and me to try to get my employer to launch a disciplinary procedure against me. Legal threats were also made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout my course, I acted with the interest of the European and Swiss public in mind. The ethical concerns that led me to change the course so abruptly hinged on strong similarities between the Coursera and Facebook Terms of Use, and the lack of transparency and accountability on the data collection and "research" practices at those companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There seems to be a very different perception across the Atlantic on privacy. As higher education moves online globally, it is important that the rest of the world does not adopt by default a Silicon Valley narrative on privacy issues in the educational domain. In my view, it is of primordial importance that European universities do not contribute to an erosion of the privacy values held by their local taxpayers &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html#id9" id="id2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. There are fundamentally different regulatory frameworks across the Atlantic: while privacy is seen in Europe as a human rights issue, it tends to be seen in the US as a tradable commodity, akin to a property right. If we consider instead developing countries, we are currently at a juncture point on this issue: while it is no doubt beneficial to offer access to educational material for their next generation, it is questionable whether this requires exporting business practices that are under increasingly intense scrutiny at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Privacy is only one of my concerns associated to Coursera and the current shaping of the MOOC market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By muddling the thick legitimacy of our universities with the thin legitimacy of companies backed by venture capital, we risk devaluing our core: academic freedom. This dynamic happened in other industries, such as journalism, where it has led to a complete reversal of power structures, and a struggle of journalists to remain relevant &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html#id10" id="id3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond delivering educational materials worldwide, I am optimistic for the potential of MOOCs to create rich and meaningful experiences for students, through citizen science and open democracy activities for instance. There is a rapid impulse to apply similar combinations of educational and crowdsourcing techniques at a high cognitive level to the labor market &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html#id11" id="id4"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;. The utopia is that this can solve labor issues on a mass scale, enabling students to extract value from their degrees right away. More ambiguously though, through &lt;em&gt;turking&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html#id12" id="id5"&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt; and the privatisation of higher education certification on a large scale, this perniciously opens the door to seamless integration of these two markets into a more exploitative arrangement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we should not forget what we lose by automating any component of an educational experience. Algorithmic culture comes with its own problems (especially when those algorithms are opaque &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html#id13" id="id6"&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;), and big data is by definition discriminatory &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html#id14" id="id7"&gt;[7]&lt;/a&gt; and hence a threat to any attempt at fostering equality in education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id8" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html#id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;My profile is missing &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.coursera.org/zurich"&gt;from here&lt;/a&gt;, for instance.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id9" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html#id2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;As an example, Coursera &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://safeharbor.export.gov/companyinfo.aspx?id=21417"&gt;refuses to comply with the EU and/or Swiss Data Protection Authorities&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id10" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html#id3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;As masterfully explained by Jay Rosen, journalism professor at NYU, in &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2014/07/facebook-has-all-the-power-you-have-almost-none/374215/"&gt;two&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/posteverything/wp/2014/07/03/dont-blame-facebook-for-screwing-with-your-mood-blame-academia/"&gt;articles&lt;/a&gt; written in the wake of the Facebook Emotion experiment. I detail some of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/erosion-of-thick-legitimacy-by-coursera.html"&gt;my concerns here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id11" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html#id4"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;See the two workshops at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.humancomputation.com/2014/"&gt;HCOMP 2014&lt;/a&gt; for these trends in &lt;em&gt;human computation&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id12" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html#id5"&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amazon_Mechanical_Turk"&gt;"A practice that enables individuals or businesses to coordinate the use of human intelligence to perform tasks that computers are currently unable to do."&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id13" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html#id6"&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;See &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://socialmediacollective.org/2014/03/25/show-and-tell-algorithmic-culture/"&gt;Show-and-Tell: Algorithmic Culture&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://socialmediacollective.org/2014/06/26/corrupt-personalization/"&gt;Corrupt Personalisation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id14" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html#id7"&gt;[7]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;See &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2477899"&gt;Big Data's Disparate Impact&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;</description><category>connected_course</category><category>coursera</category><category>ethics</category><category>massive_teaching</category><category>mooc</category><category>privacy</category><category>scholar14</category><category>t509massive</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2014 21:43:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Coursera and Safe Harbour of student data</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The European Union and Switzerland have agreements on free trade with the United States. One of those is &lt;strong&gt;Safe Harbour&lt;/strong&gt;, which has &lt;strong&gt;drastic implication for privacy&lt;/strong&gt;. In principle, Safe Harbour is a good idea: it creates &lt;strong&gt;little (business) friction&lt;/strong&gt; but ensures some form of &lt;strong&gt;citizen oversight&lt;/strong&gt; over the fastest evolving areas of e-commerce, by &lt;strong&gt;enforcing transparency&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html#id4" id="id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. It is being heavily tested though: in light of the Snowden revelations, there is growing understanding that this data originally held for commercial reasons is also a leverage of power. Andrus Ansip, the European Commissioner for Digital Single Market (designate)  &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.euractiv.com/sections/innovation-enterprise/ansip-threatens-suspend-safe-harbour-data-agreement-us-308962"&gt;acknowledged&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bits.blogs.nytimes.com/2014/10/06/europe-digital-nominee-demands-stronger-u-s-data-rules/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; in his hearings to be confirmed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;When it comes to protecting data - safe harbors need to be safe. 
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/EPhearings2014?src=hash"&gt;#EPhearings2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Andrus Ansip (@Ansip_EU) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Ansip_EU/status/519165997673373697"&gt;October 6, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Safe Harbour is not secure. The Agreement has yet to live up to its name. [..] If the U.S. Government does not make a clear statement, we must consider suspending the Agreement&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—Andrus Ansip &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html#id5" id="id2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The developments around &lt;strong&gt;MOOCs have very serious consequences for privacy&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END: (Click to read the rest of the article) --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dozens of European universities are working with US MOOC companies, spending lots, and ultimately contributing to data collection on millions of young EU citizens, all without clear purposes. There is very different cultural understanding across the Atlantic of the privacy protections of the relationships between platform and user, teacher and student and university and student. There are also very delicate (legal) constructions everywhere of what constitutes academic freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these ideas were extensively tested when I taught the class &lt;em&gt;Teaching goes massive: new skills required&lt;/em&gt; on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.coursera.org/course/massiveteaching"&gt;Coursera&lt;/a&gt;. Parts of this class were supposed to cover some of those issues, and explain directly to the students most concerned the privacy issues associated to Coursera's business models. Instead, I was &lt;strong&gt;censored&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;insulted&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;vilified&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;legally threatened&lt;/strong&gt;, and Coursera used &lt;strong&gt;false, misleading or deeply intrusive&lt;/strong&gt; data held about the course or me to get my employer to launch a disciplinary procedure against me (as even &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2014/07/15/after-massiveteaching-questions-about-mooc-quality-control"&gt;hinted to a newspaper&lt;/a&gt;!). On top, of course, my students have been left in the dark. And I have lost access to my course materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.coursera.org/about/privacy"&gt;Safe Harbour is a recourse here&lt;/a&gt; for me (as it is to any European student on Coursera). I have submitted a request to Coursera, if only to get back access to the material created.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving forward, Ansip has decided to follow a suggestion of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://juliareda.eu/en/"&gt;Julia Reda&lt;/a&gt;, a Pirate Party MEP, and host an online town hall meeting as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Watch &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/EU_Commission"&gt;@EU_Commission&lt;/a&gt; vice-presidency candidate &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Ansip_EU"&gt;@Ansip_EU&lt;/a&gt; agree to answer users' questions online: &lt;a href="https://t.co/ppTkzwojmi"&gt;https://t.co/ppTkzwojmi&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ephearings2014?src=hash"&gt;#ephearings2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Julia Reda (@Senficon) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Senficon/status/519179686967246849"&gt;October 6, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;p&gt;This hearing will take place soon, let's see what Coursera will have responded by then... &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html#id6" id="id3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let me know what should be on my "to-do-list" for the next 5 years – on Wed, Oct 15 from 11 -12 am. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/AskAnsip?src=hash"&gt;#AskAnsip&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Andrus Ansip (@Ansip_EU) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Ansip_EU/status/520593695029334016"&gt;October 10, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id4" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html#id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Let's say a US company wants to do business in the EU. The EU, well aware of dangers associated with big data businesses, is concerned about the privacy of its citizens. At the same time, it does not want to hamper innovation. The solution found with Safe Harbour is to enforce a &lt;strong&gt;series of privacy principles&lt;/strong&gt;,  as listed on the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Safe_Harbor_Privacy_Principles"&gt;Wikipedia page&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;&lt;li&gt;Notice - Individuals must be informed that their data is being collected and about how it will be used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choice - Individuals must have the option to opt out of the collection and forward transfer of the data to third  parties.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Onward Transfer - Transfers of data to third parties may only occur to other organizations that follow adequate data protection principles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Security - Reasonable efforts must be made to prevent loss of collected information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data Integrity - Data must be relevant and reliable for the purpose it was collected for.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Access - &lt;strong&gt;Individuals must be able to access information held about them&lt;/strong&gt;, and correct or delete it if it is inaccurate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enforcement - There must be effective means of enforcing these rules.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id5" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html#id2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Ansip is also former Prime Minister of Estonia, a country very much ahead in everything digital. One can even &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ibtimes.co.uk/estonia-first-country-offer-e-residency-digital-citizenship-1468766"&gt;become e-citizen there and get digital residency&lt;/a&gt;, with minimal requirements.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id6" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html#id3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Not very promising actually: within a few minutes of my original email, I got a canned message back sending me to assistance forums. I replied that this was not an answer to my request, and got the same canned message once again... Possibly I am the first Coursera user to make use of Safe Harbour.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;</description><category>connected_course</category><category>coursera</category><category>privacy</category><category>trust</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2014 18:33:34 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Click here so I can tell you about privacy (and invade yours too)</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/click-here-so-i-can-teach-you-about-privacy-and-invade-it-too.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Simply by looking at this page, you agree to this site's privacy policy, which is a copy of the Swiss Railway's statement on the use of Google Analytics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This website uses Google Analytics, a web analytics service provided by Google, Inc. (“Google”). Google Analytics uses “cookies”, which are text files placed on your computer, to help the website analyze how users use the site. The information generated by the cookie about your use of the website (including your IP address) will be transmitted to and stored by Google on servers in the United States . Google will use this information for the purpose of evaluating your use of the website, compiling reports on website activity for website operators and providing other services relating to website activity and internet usage. Google may also transfer this information to third parties where required to do so by law, or where such third parties process the information on Google's behalf. Google will not associate your IP address with any other data held by Google. You may refuse the use of cookies by selecting the appropriate settings on your browser, however please note that if you do this you may not be able to use the full functionality of this website. By using this website, you consent to the processing of data about you by Google in the manner and for the purposes set out above.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://support.google.com/analytics/answer/6004245"&gt;Google Analytics Terms of Service&lt;/a&gt;, as on the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sbb.ch/en/meta/data-protection/data-protection-google-analytics-statement.html"&gt;SBB website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The site itself does not collect data. However I do use Google Analytics, which requires me to introduce this policy as part of the service. The service allows me to track users on this website in various ways, and produces beautiful graphics like this one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="../google-analytics.jpg" class="align-center" src="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/google-analytics.jpg" style="width: 1020.0px; height: 518.0px;"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The comments below are bound by the Disqus Terms of Service, which are &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://help.disqus.com/customer/portal/articles/466259-privacy-policy"&gt;available here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don't like it, you can leave. So is the law of the internet.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>connected_course</category><category>edtech</category><category>privacy</category><category>switzerland</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/click-here-so-i-can-teach-you-about-privacy-and-invade-it-too.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2014 06:44:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Edtech policies (part I)</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/edtech-policies-part-i.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;In a previous post, I talked about some of the problems associated with &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/dont-be-evil-or-how-i-learned-to-behave-like-a-startup-and-love-the-data.html"&gt;data collection with no clear purpose&lt;/a&gt;. In this one, I want to compare two of the big players in edtech on a narrow point, that of comment posts and their associated privacy. This is partly done in response to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/funnymonkey"&gt;Bill Fitzgerald&lt;/a&gt;'s posts on edtech privacy policies, but also as a concerned parent looking a bit far out in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On June 26th Google held an I/O developer conference. I was hoping, like many, some kind of announcement about &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.mooc.org"&gt;mooc.org&lt;/a&gt;. Not much was said on that, but it was still an instructive watch of the efforts of Google in the MOOC space. I was particularly struck by a comment of Julia Wilkowski (leader in their MOOC project) following a question from the audience. The comment is at 28:35, if it does not play for you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;embed&gt;&lt;iframe width="640" height="360" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/YCUZ01yFtsM" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;p&gt;She informs us that no sophisticated analysis has been performed thus far on the Google MOOC forum posts. There are apparently two reasons: it is complicated, and they are required to delete all the posts after 60 days to comply with their privacy policy. Indeed, Google MOOCs fall under the global umbrella of the Google Privacy Policy, which seems to uniformly apply to all their products. The main reason for this number seems to be technical rather than anything else (the backup system is presumably very complex, extending all the way to physical tapes), since I couldn't find a reference to it in the Google Privacy Policy (and neither could other people, if you, well, google it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A tad later, Peter Norvig talks about classifiers (similar to those used in the recent Facebook experiment that would make the news 3 or 4 days later), for instance to help determine when a student might be confused, a classic trick in intelligent tutoring systems. He immediately reminds us though:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there still are a lot of privacy issues involved in what [..] information can you keep, how much can you tie the identity in the forum to the identity of the student, can you tie that to their identity someplace else, and the field as a whole has to come to grips with the privacy issues so we can share and learn what we want without violating privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—Peter Norvig&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coursera is another big player in the market, with a rather different approach. In their Terms of Service and Privacy policy, one can find the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="../forum-reuse.jpg" class="align-center" src="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/forum-reuse.jpg" style="width: 868.0px; height: 112.0px;"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The most remarkable sentence here is: &lt;strong&gt;We also reserve the right to reuse Forum posts containing Personally Identifiable Information in future versions of the course we offer, and to enhance further course offerings.&lt;/strong&gt; This sentence is very puzzling to me. What does it mean? The only logical explanation I can offer is that Coursera plans to repopulate forums in later iterations of the course with posts from a previous run, presumably one where there was more emphasis on moderating the course. Ask a dumb question once, and it will be asked again on repeat, &lt;strong&gt;in your name&lt;/strong&gt;, in contexts you don't necessarily know. Share a bit too much of your great idea for a startup, in a context where you feel confortable, well, too bad: it might be reshared again, even if you delete your post at the end of a course (many MOOC students have the feeble illusion that this protects their intellectual property).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Terms of Service also include the following, which is classically &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.google.ch/webhp?sourceid=chrome-instant&amp;amp;ion=1&amp;amp;espv=2&amp;amp;ie=UTF-8#q=%22Neither+the+User+Content+(as+defined+below)+on+these+Sites%2C+nor+any+links+to+other+websites%2C+are+screened%2C+moderated%2C+approved%2C+reviewed+or+endorsed%22&amp;amp;start=0"&gt;present in many platform disclaimers&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="../forum-disclaimer.jpg" class="align-center" src="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/forum-disclaimer.jpg" style="width: 863.0px; height: 156.0px;"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The Coursera Terms of Service include numerous such disturbing clauses, as detailed in &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.craigbutosi.ca/blog/coursera-or-socrates-was-not-a-content-provider-the-university-of-toronto-and-coursera-agreement"&gt;this wonderful post&lt;/a&gt; from August 2012. That post is a &lt;strong&gt;very highly recommended read&lt;/strong&gt;, since it details issues of free speech and academic freedom, a hot button those days. It also includes the following gem:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
It is crucial that we pay close attention to the fine print, something unfortunately overshadowed by the immediacy and novelty of Web 2.0 solutions and the latest trends in brand management techniques.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can only recommend this approach, but it has to be moderated by a quote given earlier in the piece:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Because Coursera mediates between instructor/university and user/student communication, we are dealing with at least four major relationships: user-Coursera, Coursera-instructor/university, user-Coursera-instructor/university, and vice versa. I am mainly focusing on the user-Coursera relation (terms of use and privacy policy), but it should be noted that these are really only separable at the analytical level. In reality, all of these relations are in play at any given time.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leaves many unanswered questions, which are not easy to address. It requires access to other contracts, between the instructor, the university and Coursera itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only one such contract between a university and Coursera has been discussed on a wide scale, the contract given to the University of Michigan. It was the object of a 2012 Chronicle of Higher Education article (an antiquity in the domain of MOOCs), and is based on a Freedom of Information request for the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://chronicle.com/article/Document-Examine-the-U-of/133063/"&gt;University of Michigan contracts&lt;/a&gt;.
More recently, the UCSC Faculty Union has entered negociations with Coursera, that are &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ucscfa.org/2013/06/scfas-ongoing-discussion-concerning-ucscs-contract-with-coursera/"&gt;detailed on its blog&lt;/a&gt;. From the outside, these negociations seem very one-sided and highlight differences with the University of Michigan contract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
In the Michigan contract, the instructor grants to COURSERA various rights FOR THE DURATION SUCH CONTENT IS OFFERED THROUGH THE PLATFORM (i.e., very limited transfer  of rights).  In our contract, in contrast, the rights are granted TO THE UNIVERSITY and this appears to be irrevocable and not connected to the hosting of the course on the Coursera  platform.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, the balance of the Coursera contract shifts towards the instructor at the University of Michigan, compared to at UCSC. In the latest Shangai rankings (for the little they are worth), Michigan was ranked 22nd while UCSC was 93rd. Bear in mind that Michigan joined earlier, which might also affect this complex bargaining equation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few other contracts have been put online, intentionally or not, and can be found by googling titles etc. I found eight in total, which can serve as evidence of subtle shifts of the Coursera strategy, and also segmentation according to the characteristics of the universities involved (European vs. American, public vs. private, etc). Since many of those contracts are locked under Non Disclosure Agreements, and this has already become a union issue elsewhere, I can only encourage other academics to push for openness of those contracts at their own institutions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(For a cool application of machine learning to the process of teaching, look also at the video around the 4:30 mark. Google seems to focus there on content rather than users, and to extract values from the student contributions rather than their private data. They effectively intend to crowdsource smarter compilers.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I want to thank Ignacio Despujol Zabala for letting me know about this Google I/O session.)&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>coursera</category><category>edtech</category><category>google</category><category>privacy</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/edtech-policies-part-i.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Sep 2014 10:23:58 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>How fast the world has changed</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/how-fast-the-world-has-changed.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;As I am starting to blog, I am taking a course on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://schoolofopen.p2pu.org/"&gt;openness with P2PU&lt;/a&gt;. This is helping me think of how to quickly and most efficiently &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://opencontent.org/blog/archives/3393"&gt;reclaim my domain&lt;/a&gt;. For this, I have been looking back at the few notes I have posted around on Facebook. Actually, you can too if you have a Facebook account, as I have just made them &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.facebook.com/paulolivier.dehaye/notes"&gt;viewable to every facebook user&lt;/a&gt;. This way, if you are new here, you can get a quick sense of what I am about. Incidentally, due to a little known item in the Facebook &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.facebook.com/about/privacy/your-info-on-fb"&gt;privacy policy&lt;/a&gt;, this means that all the comments are now public as well (i.e. my friends gave the rights to their comments to Facebook, I gave the right to my original posts to Facebook, and finally Facebook decides to correlate privacy of comments to the privacy settings of the original post). I suppose every platform owner has to make lots of those decisions, which eventually shape the service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, one of the notes struck me. It was just a link, actually, to a 2008 &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://warner.blogs.nytimes.com/2008/12/04/first-the-bad-news/"&gt;New York Times story&lt;/a&gt; about an unfortunate Walmart employee who was trampled to death on Black Friday. The angle is that bad things happen in the world, and sometimes this can end up on the internet, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7aUwmsi6Wc0"&gt;filmed on crappy cell phone cameras&lt;/a&gt;. And then we have to tell kids about all that violence. The undertone of the piece is that we were just starting to grapple with that problem back then. A friend of mine commented and asked for my opinion. The original note is &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.facebook.com/notes/paul-olivier-dehaye/kids-are-scary-sometimes/103572210077"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, with a contemporary screenshot below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="../walmart.jpg" class="align-center" src="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/walmart.jpg" style="width: 629.0px; height: 307.0px;"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Close to six years later, we are still facing the same problems, of course. Internet is more &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.mercurynews.com/business/ci_26459616/youtube-twitter-teamed-halt-spread-beheading-video-report"&gt;violent&lt;/a&gt; and more &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/emmawoollacott/2014/09/08/reddit-gives-mixed-messages-after-pulling-leaked-celebrity-photos/"&gt;invasive&lt;/a&gt; than ever. Any platform owner knows the value of good filters to curate content for its users. This content curation can be done jointly by machines and humans, leading to risks of algorithmic bias still misunderstood (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/dailymuse/2014/08/04/the-facebook-experiment-what-it-means-for-you/"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://medium.com/message/the-algorithm-giveth-but-it-also-taketh-b7efad92bc1f"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;). It can also be done exclusively by humans, operating under strict rules. For both posts and comments. This is the model applied by &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.metafilter.com"&gt;metafilter&lt;/a&gt;, leading to high quality output but a relatively weak business model, unfortunately &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://gigaom.com/2014/05/22/if-a-high-quality-site-like-metafilter-can-be-crushed-by-google-what-hope-do-other-sites-have/"&gt;still vulnerable to algorithmic whims&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
&lt;dl class="docutils"&gt;&lt;dt&gt;So you're saying that people tried to use the economies of scale of the internet to disrupt the conventional and somewhat hidebound traditional methods and then it turns out that certain things requiring human eyeballs and judgment do not actually scale along with this stuff and the lesson is that you need to keep people in the mix in not just token ways even if this interferes with your bottom line...? I know that song!&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;-- Metafilter user and former moderator &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.metafilter.com/user/292"&gt;jessamyn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, eight years after this Facebook note, the world still turns around. People get married, have babies, raise their children. And most people still use Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>baby</category><category>facebook</category><category>metafilter</category><category>privacy</category><category>reclaim</category><category>violence</category><category>whyopen</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/how-fast-the-world-has-changed.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2014 13:37:35 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>"Don't be evil", or how I learned to behave like a startup and love the data</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/dont-be-evil-or-how-i-learned-to-behave-like-a-startup-and-love-the-data.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;img alt="../strangelove.png" class="align-right" src="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/strangelove.png" style="width: 320.0px; height: 240.0px;"&gt;&lt;p&gt;When Gmail was opened in 2004, I received invitations early. If I remember well, they came from a friend working at Google who had already snatched a few fun login names. I did the same, and passed on further invitations to my brother and our friends back home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A year or so later, when my brother was visiting with his friends, we went on a tour of the Googleplex. Randomly passing in front of the cubicle of a homonym, one of the friends suddenly realised why he had not been able to register his own name earlier. In other words, &lt;strong&gt;an unknown collision in the physical world had first manifested digitally&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like to think of those collisions as the digital equivalent of New York overcrowding, trying to fit too many people in just a few login characters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So which fun pseudonyms did we chose? Which did we consider worthy in this land grab? Certainly many of them were aimed at our shared cultural backgrounds as Belgians in the Silicon Valley. If you had &lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:tintin@gmail.com"&gt;tintin@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://nl.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frietkot"&gt;frietkot@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt; that would be pretty impressive, no? Indeed, we grabbed names of regions, superheroes, movie stars, concepts, etc. We certainly thought this was OK, and didn't reflect more on something that &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nymwars"&gt;became controversial only later&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the logins I grabbed had the name of a Belgian politician, let's call him Some Guy. He was on TV and I thought my friends would get a chuckle if I emailed them from it. Certainly, I might have crossed a moral line already then, but it felt like a very tiny escalation in this virtual land grab.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What did I do with this account? I mostly used it for spam protection. I set it up so that all emails sent there would be forwarded to my default inbox, and gave this address whenever there was a need to a register for a spammy online service. This worked well, possibly because Gmail's algorithms had learned to weigh emails transiting through this address differently and benefited from the additional segmenting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around 2008, inevitably, I started receiving emails addressed to That Guy. Those collisions happen to all of us, for all of our email accounts. What is the moral thing to do there? My philosophy is most of the time to let it drop, but  sometimes also to reply to the sender telling them that they got the wrong address (due to emails missent to my main account, I must have had to contact a dozen hotels in Quebec by now). In most cases, the only way to know what to do is to read the email, slightly invading this other persons' privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Just like Rachel and her Friends in their New York apartment, we struggle to deal with those privacy collisions, especially when we feel a need to intervene.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;iframe width="900" height="600" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/tYn8s0_kDUw?rel=0&amp;amp;hd=1&amp;amp;wmode=transparent"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;p&gt;For That Guy, it was even easier to feel morally OK about it: I never actively sought the emails, had no way to prevent the mistake, and anyways the emails were from cranks. On top, by that time I had registered to too many services with that pseudonym, which effectively tied my identity to it, with no way to revert the situation. So in effect this data collection was happening, whether I liked it or not, or at least that was my moral justification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The problem with data is that it leaks.&lt;/strong&gt; The cranks don't just email one influential person at a time. They email a few, who are susceptible to know each other. As a consequence, in this case, the cranks polluted those recipients' email software  with a wrong email address. Of course, in due time, the email autocompletion software of those recipients started tripping them and I started receiving emails from other politicians to That Guy. &lt;strong&gt;Algorithmic curation had gone wrong, and actively mislead humans.&lt;/strong&gt; The fact that these were politicians might have mislead me: I should have made the effort of explaining the awkward situation to That Guy's interlocutors and tried to correct it. But I didn't. Somehow a couple more emails made it to me that were clearly of more social nature. Again, I didn't do anything. &lt;strong&gt;This data will not disappear unless actively deleted&lt;/strong&gt;, and even then I can only be so sure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
At this point you will deservedly think that I am a moron. But was it morally wrong? And when exactly did it go wrong?&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout my moral justification was that I was not actively seeking this. Emails would land in my mailbox and I would have to read them to know what to do. Of course, this conveniently ignores what I could have done to prevent those emails to arrive in the first place. Part of my justification was that I wasn't doing anything with the data collected. There was no clear goal, except &lt;strong&gt;awareness that this could be used to make a point later, which I guess I am making here now publicly&lt;/strong&gt; (in fact, I have used this to make this point in private throughout the years).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more interesting issue here is to understand that this is exactly how many big data companies function. "Don't be evil" Google gobbles data all over the place &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.wired.com/2014/04/threatlevel_0401_streetview/"&gt;for purposes that are not always clear at the time&lt;/a&gt;, and the justification is often that this was incidental, automated and did not require human intervention. Looking at a corporate setting elevates the stakes, and my feeble moral justifications are not sufficient anymore. It becomes a matter of ethics, which arguably should be that data collection is by default unethical: data should not be kept beyond the time necessary for its intended use, with that use itself subject to precise and established ethical rules. It looks like Google has understood this in some markets, for instance education (unlike other players there), and this will be the topic of a later post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Image in the public domain: the Dr Stangelove War Room, which &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://valleywag.gawker.com/airbnbs-office-has-a-replica-of-the-dr-strangelove-wa-1475788543"&gt;happens to be replicated in the Airbnb HQ&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>ethics</category><category>privacy</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/dont-be-evil-or-how-i-learned-to-behave-like-a-startup-and-love-the-data.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2014 09:45:51 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>