<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>paulolivier.dehaye.org (switzerland)</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/</link><description></description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2014 09:55:02 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Click here so I can tell you about privacy (and invade yours too)</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/click-here-so-i-can-teach-you-about-privacy-and-invade-it-too.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Simply by looking at this page, you agree to this site's privacy policy, which is a copy of the Swiss Railway's statement on the use of Google Analytics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“This website uses Google Analytics, a web analytics service provided by Google, Inc. (“Google”). Google Analytics uses “cookies”, which are text files placed on your computer, to help the website analyze how users use the site. The information generated by the cookie about your use of the website (including your IP address) will be transmitted to and stored by Google on servers in the United States . Google will use this information for the purpose of evaluating your use of the website, compiling reports on website activity for website operators and providing other services relating to website activity and internet usage. Google may also transfer this information to third parties where required to do so by law, or where such third parties process the information on Google's behalf. Google will not associate your IP address with any other data held by Google. You may refuse the use of cookies by selecting the appropriate settings on your browser, however please note that if you do this you may not be able to use the full functionality of this website. By using this website, you consent to the processing of data about you by Google in the manner and for the purposes set out above.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://support.google.com/analytics/answer/6004245"&gt;Google Analytics Terms of Service&lt;/a&gt;, as on the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sbb.ch/en/meta/data-protection/data-protection-google-analytics-statement.html"&gt;SBB website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The site itself does not collect data. However I do use Google Analytics, which requires me to introduce this policy as part of the service. The service allows me to track users on this website in various ways, and produces beautiful graphics like this one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="../google-analytics.jpg" class="align-center" src="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/google-analytics.jpg" style="width: 1020.0px; height: 518.0px;"&gt;&lt;p&gt;The comments below are bound by the Disqus Terms of Service, which are &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://help.disqus.com/customer/portal/articles/466259-privacy-policy"&gt;available here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don't like it, you can leave. So is the law of the internet.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>connected_course</category><category>edtech</category><category>privacy</category><category>switzerland</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/click-here-so-i-can-teach-you-about-privacy-and-invade-it-too.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 10 Sep 2014 06:44:21 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>