<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>paulolivier.dehaye.org (t509massive)</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/</link><description></description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2014 04:02:28 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Dear Daphne</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/dear-daphne.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The following is an open letter to Daphne Koller, CEO of Coursera. I sent her also a copy via email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
Dear Daphne,

Please send the email below to the students of my course "Massive Teaching: New skills required" to the entirety of my class.
As you know, I am unable to send it now that my Coursera instructor rights have been removed.

Sincerely yours,

Prof. Paul-Olivier Dehaye
University of Zurich
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="letter-to-coursera-students-of-massive-teaching-new-skills-required"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Letter to Coursera students of "Massive Teaching: New skills required"&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dear students of "Massive Teaching: New skills required",&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I must first apologize to you for what must have been a very confusing time. It was confusing for me too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you recall, my plan was for the course to span three weeks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;&lt;li&gt;pedagogy;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;technology and copyright;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;business models, and science-fiction of MOOCs (i.e. utopia and dystopia)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;I decided to give this course because I thought it would be important to inform widely on these topics, especially the third week. Coursera did not know what the content would be, and neither did I have the full picture: as advertised I would be responsive and adaptive to the issues arising on the forum. Coursera knew however that I would be critical then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the first week, came disputed news report of a confusing ethical lapse at Cornell University and Facebook, in conducting a study on the influence of the Facebook newsfeed on users' emotions. The main thrust of the criticism addressed towards Cornell, a university, is that it cannot shield itself from ethical responsibility by claiming the data collection has been done at Facebook, a private institution. Some Maryland law professors are now even arguing this study might actually have broken state laws on human subjects research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I had prepared the third week on business models, I knew right away that Coursera's partner institutions have  subjected themselves to similar criticism. It is universally acknowledged that at least for the moment, universities lose money on MOOCs. In exchange, they get recognition, brand, reach, but also crucially access to data, the raw material driving an increasingly digital economy. Universities are more and more acting like businesses, and this data is key to them. All kinds of experiments are or will be performed around this data, to improve the core business of teaching. This means that universities play dual roles here, defending simultaneously research and business. This in itself is an ethical bomb, one that weakens the standing of universities in society. In the wake of the Facebook experiment it led me to cast an even more critical eye on the handling of your data, and to judge to the best of my ability that no proper procedures were in place. In fact, I could not rule out that I myself was party of an experiment without giving any informed consent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the reason &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; I pulled content: academia and civil society need to have a global debate on the issue of data mining of students, for both commercial and research purposes. Regulations differ widely across the world, and creative but morally dubious solutions are being found. However much I would have liked, my course was not the proper place to initiate that debate  since I am not qualified: the setting of a course on a commercial platform was too risky for me from a legal standpoint to even express doubts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this reason, I resolved to pull out the videos, and simplify the forum to the maximum, to just one thread. Both my university and Coursera were surprised, and reinstated content. I welcome any further clarification by my university and Coursera on what exactly happened after I pulled content, when I was prevented from fully explaining my views to you or the public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that the university has clarified its position with me on the legal matters, I am glad to be able to get this message to you, via Coursera's messaging system. By definition this will have closed the first (reported) incident of censorship when teaching at Coursera.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sincerely yours,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul-Olivier Dehaye&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS: Should you not be satisfied with this account, I have written a more detailed one &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/extended-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-ii.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. You are welcome to criticize if this does not correspond to your recollection, but bear in mind the timeline. A lot of what you might have read afterwards was pure fabrication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>connected_course</category><category>coursera</category><category>massive_teaching</category><category>scholar14</category><category>t509massive</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/dear-daphne.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2014 13:53:11 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Statement on #massiveteaching (part I)</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;(For a more extended statement, see &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/extended-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-ii.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My name is Paul-Olivier Dehaye, I am a mathematics professor at the University of Zurich. On June 23rd 2014, I started to teach a MOOC on Coursera, called &lt;em&gt;Teaching goes massive: New skills required&lt;/em&gt;, which was intended to last for three weeks and include a component on business practices of MOOC providers. During the course delivery, my perception of the ethical issues surrounding the course changed, which led me to alter its delivery methods. This prompted a reaction by Coursera itself, and I was censored &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html#id8" id="id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. In the fallout, I was also insulted and vilified online. Coursera used intentionally misleading information and deeply intrusive data held about the course and me to try to get my employer to launch a disciplinary procedure against me. Legal threats were also made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout my course, I acted with the interest of the European and Swiss public in mind. The ethical concerns that led me to change the course so abruptly hinged on strong similarities between the Coursera and Facebook Terms of Use, and the lack of transparency and accountability on the data collection and "research" practices at those companies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There seems to be a very different perception across the Atlantic on privacy. As higher education moves online globally, it is important that the rest of the world does not adopt by default a Silicon Valley narrative on privacy issues in the educational domain. In my view, it is of primordial importance that European universities do not contribute to an erosion of the privacy values held by their local taxpayers &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html#id9" id="id2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. There are fundamentally different regulatory frameworks across the Atlantic: while privacy is seen in Europe as a human rights issue, it tends to be seen in the US as a tradable commodity, akin to a property right. If we consider instead developing countries, we are currently at a juncture point on this issue: while it is no doubt beneficial to offer access to educational material for their next generation, it is questionable whether this requires exporting business practices that are under increasingly intense scrutiny at home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Privacy is only one of my concerns associated to Coursera and the current shaping of the MOOC market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By muddling the thick legitimacy of our universities with the thin legitimacy of companies backed by venture capital, we risk devaluing our core: academic freedom. This dynamic happened in other industries, such as journalism, where it has led to a complete reversal of power structures, and a struggle of journalists to remain relevant &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html#id10" id="id3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond delivering educational materials worldwide, I am optimistic for the potential of MOOCs to create rich and meaningful experiences for students, through citizen science and open democracy activities for instance. There is a rapid impulse to apply similar combinations of educational and crowdsourcing techniques at a high cognitive level to the labor market &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html#id11" id="id4"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;. The utopia is that this can solve labor issues on a mass scale, enabling students to extract value from their degrees right away. More ambiguously though, through &lt;em&gt;turking&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html#id12" id="id5"&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt; and the privatisation of higher education certification on a large scale, this perniciously opens the door to seamless integration of these two markets into a more exploitative arrangement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we should not forget what we lose by automating any component of an educational experience. Algorithmic culture comes with its own problems (especially when those algorithms are opaque &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html#id13" id="id6"&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;), and big data is by definition discriminatory &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html#id14" id="id7"&gt;[7]&lt;/a&gt; and hence a threat to any attempt at fostering equality in education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id8" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html#id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;My profile is missing &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.coursera.org/zurich"&gt;from here&lt;/a&gt;, for instance.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id9" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html#id2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;As an example, Coursera &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://safeharbor.export.gov/companyinfo.aspx?id=21417"&gt;refuses to comply with the EU and/or Swiss Data Protection Authorities&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id10" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html#id3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;As masterfully explained by Jay Rosen, journalism professor at NYU, in &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2014/07/facebook-has-all-the-power-you-have-almost-none/374215/"&gt;two&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/posteverything/wp/2014/07/03/dont-blame-facebook-for-screwing-with-your-mood-blame-academia/"&gt;articles&lt;/a&gt; written in the wake of the Facebook Emotion experiment. I detail some of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/erosion-of-thick-legitimacy-by-coursera.html"&gt;my concerns here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id11" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html#id4"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;See the two workshops at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.humancomputation.com/2014/"&gt;HCOMP 2014&lt;/a&gt; for these trends in &lt;em&gt;human computation&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id12" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html#id5"&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amazon_Mechanical_Turk"&gt;"A practice that enables individuals or businesses to coordinate the use of human intelligence to perform tasks that computers are currently unable to do."&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id13" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html#id6"&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;See &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://socialmediacollective.org/2014/03/25/show-and-tell-algorithmic-culture/"&gt;Show-and-Tell: Algorithmic Culture&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://socialmediacollective.org/2014/06/26/corrupt-personalization/"&gt;Corrupt Personalisation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id14" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html#id7"&gt;[7]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;See &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2477899"&gt;Big Data's Disparate Impact&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;</description><category>connected_course</category><category>coursera</category><category>ethics</category><category>massive_teaching</category><category>mooc</category><category>privacy</category><category>scholar14</category><category>t509massive</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/short-statement-on-massiveteaching-part-i.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2014 21:43:30 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Learning, working and ?</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/learning-working-and.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;A lot of my recent thoughts have turned around issues of crowdsourcing and online education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="../worklearn.jpg" class="align-right" src="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/worklearn.jpg" style="width: 346.4px; height: 85.6px;"&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of my co-authors (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://hci.uni-hannover.de/people/markus"&gt;Markus Krause&lt;/a&gt;) is co-organising a workshop on that topic, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.worklearn.org/"&gt;WorkLearn 2014&lt;/a&gt;. It will take place in Pittsburgh November 2-4, as part of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.humancomputation.com/2014/"&gt;Human Computation conference HCOMP2014&lt;/a&gt;. Human Computation is another expression interchangeable for &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/social-teaching-machines.html"&gt;social machine&lt;/a&gt;, although it has different connotations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stated motivation of the workshop is very ambitious:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The online education and crowdsourcing communities are addressing similar problems in educating, motivating and evaluating students and workers. The online learning community succeeds in increasing the supply side of the cognitively skilled labor market, and the crowdsourcing at scale community creates a larger marketplace for cognitively skilled work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linking online platforms for crowd work with platforms for MOOCs has the potential to: provide knowledge and training at a massive scale to contributors; collect data that identify expert skills; engage contributors in simultaneously working and learning in a social environment; and organize large communities around online courses on specific topics. These all provide new opportunities to support and deploy sophisticated algorithms for crowd learning and work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most successful example in this direction is of course &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://duolingo.com"&gt;Duolingo&lt;/a&gt;, which helps translate the web while using volunteer labor by language learners. If one omits the learning, the strategy there is not that different from the strategy used by my Coursera coworker &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.coursera.org/instructor/bernstein"&gt;Abraham Bernstein&lt;/a&gt; to translate books using &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amazon_Mechanical_Turk"&gt;Amazon Mechanical Turk&lt;/a&gt;, and indeed part of his efforts aim to design effective tools to program those social machines (with the programming language CrowdLang).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;embed&gt;&lt;iframe width="640" height="360" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/emCABRV2cUA" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have always had some qualms about the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://florianschmidt.co/the-good-the-bad-and-the-ugly/"&gt;ethics of crowdsourcing&lt;/a&gt;, even though it can clearly be used for good: the prototypical success story is in the work of Ushahidi during the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ushahidi.com/blog/2012/01/12/haiti-and-the-power-of-crowdsourcing/"&gt;2010 Haiti earthquake&lt;/a&gt;. I was thus very happy to see over Labor Day 2014 that Michael Bernstein from Stanford announced &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://crowdresearch.org/blog/?p=9039"&gt;guidelines for academic requesters on Amazon Mechanical Turk&lt;/a&gt;. He explains the rationale for this (a Turker is a worker on a crowdsourcing platform):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
An IRB-approved researcher experimented on the [crowdsourcing] platform unannounced. The result was Turker confusion, strife, and wasted time, in a system where time is what it takes to make ends meet.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These guidelines were themselves crowdsourced, designed together with the Turkers (it's only natural!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, over the summer, there was a huge controversy over the iffy ethics of social platforms experimentation. This is due to the release at the very end of June 2014 of a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/kashmirhill/2014/06/29/facebook-doesnt-understand-the-fuss-about-its-emotion-manipulation-study/"&gt;Facebook experiment on its users&lt;/a&gt; (don't miss the Cornell IRB flowchart there). There are a ton of links about this, but the best is probably the account by Mary L. Gray of an &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://marylgray.org/?page_id=203"&gt;ethics panel that took place at the Microsoft Research Faculty Summit&lt;/a&gt; (and unfortunately was published with much delay).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, this should give serious pause to any educator. One can see lots of fields suddenly getting much too close, with very different or inexistent values. Online learners, just as Turkers, are vulnerable. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://nogoodreason.typepad.co.uk/no_good_reason/2014/06/the-ethics-of-digital-scholarship.html"&gt;Martin Weller&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.elearnspace.org/blog/2014/01/13/the-vulnerability-of-learning/"&gt;George Siemens&lt;/a&gt; have recently insisted on this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what do you think? Anyone wants to submit a position paper (2 pages) on the topic? Any of my co-learners in MOOCs would like to see what we can do? We could, well... crowdsource it...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(of course, this was due yesterday: official deadline is "September")&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>connected_course</category><category>coursera</category><category>crowdsourcing</category><category>duolingo</category><category>ethics</category><category>t509massive</category><category>whyopen</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/learning-working-and.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2014 00:17:10 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>