<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>paulolivier.dehaye.org (trust)</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/</link><description></description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2014 04:02:27 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Coursera and Safe Harbour of student data</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The European Union and Switzerland have agreements on free trade with the United States. One of those is &lt;strong&gt;Safe Harbour&lt;/strong&gt;, which has &lt;strong&gt;drastic implication for privacy&lt;/strong&gt;. In principle, Safe Harbour is a good idea: it creates &lt;strong&gt;little (business) friction&lt;/strong&gt; but ensures some form of &lt;strong&gt;citizen oversight&lt;/strong&gt; over the fastest evolving areas of e-commerce, by &lt;strong&gt;enforcing transparency&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html#id4" id="id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. It is being heavily tested though: in light of the Snowden revelations, there is growing understanding that this data originally held for commercial reasons is also a leverage of power. Andrus Ansip, the European Commissioner for Digital Single Market (designate)  &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.euractiv.com/sections/innovation-enterprise/ansip-threatens-suspend-safe-harbour-data-agreement-us-308962"&gt;acknowledged&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bits.blogs.nytimes.com/2014/10/06/europe-digital-nominee-demands-stronger-u-s-data-rules/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; in his hearings to be confirmed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;When it comes to protecting data - safe harbors need to be safe. 
&lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/EPhearings2014?src=hash"&gt;#EPhearings2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Andrus Ansip (@Ansip_EU) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Ansip_EU/status/519165997673373697"&gt;October 6, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Safe Harbour is not secure. The Agreement has yet to live up to its name. [..] If the U.S. Government does not make a clear statement, we must consider suspending the Agreement&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—Andrus Ansip &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html#id5" id="id2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The developments around &lt;strong&gt;MOOCs have very serious consequences for privacy&lt;/strong&gt;. Dozens of European universities are working with US MOOC companies, spending lots, and ultimately contributing to data collection on millions of young EU citizens, all without clear purposes. There is very different cultural understanding across the Atlantic of the privacy protections of the relationships between platform and user, teacher and student and university and student. There are also very delicate (legal) constructions everywhere of what constitutes academic freedom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these ideas were extensively tested when I taught the class &lt;em&gt;Teaching goes massive: new skills required&lt;/em&gt; on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.coursera.org/course/massiveteaching"&gt;Coursera&lt;/a&gt;. Parts of this class were supposed to cover some of those issues, and explain directly to the students most concerned the privacy issues associated to Coursera's business models. Instead, I was &lt;strong&gt;censored&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;insulted&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;vilified&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;legally threatened&lt;/strong&gt;, and Coursera used &lt;strong&gt;false, misleading or deeply intrusive&lt;/strong&gt; data held about the course or me to get my employer to launch a disciplinary procedure against me (as even &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2014/07/15/after-massiveteaching-questions-about-mooc-quality-control"&gt;hinted to a newspaper&lt;/a&gt;!). On top, of course, my students have been left in the dark. And I have lost access to my course materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.coursera.org/about/privacy"&gt;Safe Harbour is a recourse here&lt;/a&gt; for me (as it is to any European student on Coursera). I have submitted a request to Coursera, if only to get back access to the material created.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moving forward, Ansip has decided to follow a suggestion of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://juliareda.eu/en/"&gt;Julia Reda&lt;/a&gt;, a Pirate Party MEP, and host an online town hall meeting as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Watch &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/EU_Commission"&gt;@EU_Commission&lt;/a&gt; vice-presidency candidate &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Ansip_EU"&gt;@Ansip_EU&lt;/a&gt; agree to answer users' questions online: &lt;a href="https://t.co/ppTkzwojmi"&gt;https://t.co/ppTkzwojmi&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ephearings2014?src=hash"&gt;#ephearings2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Julia Reda (@Senficon) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Senficon/status/519179686967246849"&gt;October 6, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;p&gt;This hearing will take place soon, let's see what Coursera will have responded by then... &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html#id6" id="id3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Let me know what should be on my "to-do-list" for the next 5 years – on Wed, Oct 15 from 11 -12 am. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/AskAnsip?src=hash"&gt;#AskAnsip&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;— Andrus Ansip (@Ansip_EU) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Ansip_EU/status/520593695029334016"&gt;October 10, 2014&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;script async src="//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id4" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html#id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Let's say a US company wants to do business in the EU. The EU, well aware of dangers associated with big data businesses, is concerned about the privacy of its citizens. At the same time, it does not want to hamper innovation. The solution found with Safe Harbour is to enforce a &lt;strong&gt;series of privacy principles&lt;/strong&gt;,  as listed on the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Safe_Harbor_Privacy_Principles"&gt;Wikipedia page&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;&lt;li&gt;Notice - Individuals must be informed that their data is being collected and about how it will be used.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choice - Individuals must have the option to opt out of the collection and forward transfer of the data to third  parties.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Onward Transfer - Transfers of data to third parties may only occur to other organizations that follow adequate data protection principles.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Security - Reasonable efforts must be made to prevent loss of collected information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data Integrity - Data must be relevant and reliable for the purpose it was collected for.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Access - &lt;strong&gt;Individuals must be able to access information held about them&lt;/strong&gt;, and correct or delete it if it is inaccurate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enforcement - There must be effective means of enforcing these rules.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id5" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html#id2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Ansip is also former Prime Minister of Estonia, a country very much ahead in everything digital. One can even &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ibtimes.co.uk/estonia-first-country-offer-e-residency-digital-citizenship-1468766"&gt;become e-citizen there and get digital residency&lt;/a&gt;, with minimal requirements.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id6" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html#id3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Not very promising actually: within a few minutes of my original email, I got a canned message back sending me to assistance forums. I replied that this was not an answer to my request, and got the same canned message once again... Possibly I am the first Coursera user to make use of Safe Harbour.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;</description><category>connected_course</category><category>coursera</category><category>privacy</category><category>trust</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/coursera-and-safe-harbour-of-student-data.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 10 Oct 2014 18:33:34 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Culture of humiliation</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/culture-of-humiliation.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I have learned a lot recently about online humiliation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monica Lewinsky's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.vanityfair.com/society/2014/06/monica-lewinsky-humiliation-culture"&gt;Vanity Fair piece&lt;/a&gt; was very insightful. Indeed, if anyone would know about being the victim of online shaming, it would be her. Interestingly, she shares that a new stage of horror for her was achieved when she understood the impact his scandal had on her family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In September of 2010, the culmination of these experiences began to snap into a broader context for me. A phone conversation with my mother shifted the lens through which I viewed my world. We were discussing the tragic death of Tyler Clementi. Tyler, you will recall, was an 18-year-old Rutgers freshman who was secretly streamed via Webcam kissing another man. Days later, after being derided and humiliated on social media, he committed suicide by jumping off the George Washington Bridge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My mom wept. Sobbing, she kept repeating over and over, “How his parents must feel … his poor parents.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was an unbearably tragic event, and while hearing of it brought me to tears, too, I couldn’t quite grasp why my mom was so distraught. And then it dawned on me: she was reliving 1998, when she wouldn’t let me out of her sight. She was replaying those weeks when she stayed by my bed, night after night, because I, too, was suicidal. The shame, the scorn, and the fear that had been thrown at her daughter left her afraid that I would take my own life—a fear that I would be literally humiliated to death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—Monica Lewinsky, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.vanityfair.com/society/2014/06/monica-lewinsky-humiliation-culture"&gt;Shame and Survival&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Look at the year, 2010, that's twelve years after the facts. A lot of time for a mom to suffer with weakened trust in her daughter that she would take on life, with its good and bad days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something else that crossed my path is a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mathbabe.org/2014/09/30/people-hate-me-i-must-be-doing-something-right/"&gt;post by Cathy O'Neil on her blog mathbabe&lt;/a&gt;, where she discusses some ways she has built a thick skin and maintains confidence in herself, even in the face of criticism that can get very personal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there’s one other thing I conclude when I piss people off: that I’m getting under their skin, which means what I’m saying is getting out there, to a wider audience than just people who already agree with me, and if that guy hates me then maybe 100 other people are listening and not quite hating me. They might even be agreeing with me. They might even be changing their minds about some things because of my arguments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I realize this sounds twisted, but when people hate me, I feel like I must be doing something right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One other thing I’ll say, which the article brings up. It is a luxury indeed to be a woman who can afford to be hated. I am not at risk, or at least I don’t feel at all at risk, when other people hate me. They are entitled to hate me, and I don’t need to bother myself about getting them to like me. It’s a deep and wonderful fact about our civilization that I can say that, and I am very glad to be living here and now, where I can be a provocative and opinionated intellectual woman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—Cathy O'Neil&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, the humiliation could get very deep in her psyche, but she makes her way of fighting it back very explicit. It's an utilitarian calculus, based on the scale of the positive impact she hopes to achieve versus the one negative comment she just had to face.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She ends the piece with this powerful line:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Fuck yes! Let’s do this, people! Let’s have ideas and argue about them and disagree! It’s what freedom is all about.&lt;/blockquote&gt;</description><category>connected_course</category><category>trust</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/culture-of-humiliation.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2014 21:37:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Building trust in #massiveteaching, through visuals</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;As part of the module on trust in &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.connectedcourses.net"&gt;Connected Courses&lt;/a&gt;, I would like to share some tricks that I have used to visually build trust across cultures. It was especially powerful for me to watch Jonathan Worth's video on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://phonar.org/2014/09/leveraging-you-why-in-answer-to-mike-wesch/"&gt;Leveraging your why&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html#id5" id="id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Worth offers that his "Why?" for #phonar is actually citizen journalism, and discusses a photo by John Stanmeyer, winner of the World Press Photo 2013 award.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this brings me back to, this is my ‘why?’ So this image is the winning image from the World Press Photo this year, by a photographer called John Stanmeyer, and this is why it annoys me so much. Because it’s by a photographer called John Stanmeyer. These are African immigrants standing on a beach, trying to get a phone signal before they jump in the water. Let me just get this right, “on the shore of Djibouti City at night raising their phones in an attempt to capture an inexpensive signal from neighbouring Somalia”. These are the people that aren’t in my class. They’re holding these smart devices which can all take pictures, and yet it takes a photographer from New York to bring it back and we can now talk about it.  What these people need is to be able to be trusted and to be heard, and these are the people that aren’t in the class. So this is my why, and this is my way marker, so this is definitely the best and most exciting thing that’s come out of my classes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="attribution"&gt;—&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://phonar.org/2014/09/leveraging-you-why-in-answer-to-mike-wesch/"&gt;Jonathan Worth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of my efforts with my &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.coursera.org/course/massiveteaching"&gt;Coursera course&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Massive Teaching: News skills required&lt;/em&gt; were some interesting blend of Worth's efforts in #phonar and in #connected_courses. Let's first consider the exact opposite of what I did. Relax, prepare some popcorn, and watch the following video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;iframe width="425" height="344" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/0rmJqQotDWo?rel=0&amp;amp;hd=1&amp;amp;wmode=transparent"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clealy this video exploits the elite university brand together with a lot of pixie dust to try to cement this elite brand even more. The "why?" of this MIT video certainly shows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as in Worth's #phonar course leading up to citizen journalism, I am hoping with parts of &lt;em&gt;Massive Teaching&lt;/em&gt; to enable some form of citizen-MOOCing, to create a small distributed network of video production, with no sacrifice on the quality of the education provided. My sidegoal was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to find the cheapest way to produce video, but to find a visual style that could appeal equally to institutions (even very elite) and lonely individuals anywhere in the world &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html#id6" id="id2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sidegoal was to make for a more homogeneous and egalitarian pool of video producers &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html#id7" id="id3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;, but it goes further. How do we enable anyone anywhere to build trust with &lt;strong&gt;connected diverse individuals&lt;/strong&gt; (a concept that I used in a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/moocs-as-inventions-chals14.html"&gt;recent talk&lt;/a&gt; and is obviously core to #ccourses)? Let's consider one of my videos, where the topic is precisely on tracking of individuals by large corporations, drawing parallels between educational analytics and AdWords style advertising.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;iframe width="425" height="344" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/qOCln176bM4?rel=0&amp;amp;hd=1&amp;amp;wmode=transparent"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;img alt="../crib.jpeg" class="align-right" src="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/crib.jpeg" style="width: 216.0px; height: 288.0px;"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note a few things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;&lt;li&gt;it uses easily findable DUPLO pieces &lt;a class="footnote-reference" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html#id8" id="id4"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt; and paper cutouts;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I feel that using kids' toys produces emotional responses and increases trust;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;my hands are there, and that makes the videos still personal (contrast with the expense at &lt;a class="reference external" href="mailto:CEDE@EPFL"&gt;CEDE@EPFL&lt;/a&gt; for their &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=agbe9B5l_VI"&gt;invisible hand effect&lt;/a&gt;);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the production process is first audio, then video, and the two are completely separate (I replay the audio when filming the video). In this way I actually first write the transcript, record a reading, and then illustrate. It makes translations very easy: simply re-record the sound, at the pace of the video.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I designed a recording studio out of IKEA furniture pieces (a crib, for instance for a cage, so it is easy to attach camera, light, etc); IKEA is not cheap enough but it gives wide reach. I have confidence that this can be improved drastically, by posting on sites such as &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ikeahackers.net/"&gt;IKEAhackers&lt;/a&gt;;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I encouraged my students to do the same, by describing my process as throgouhly as possible (done here again);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;None of those cheap tricks are new, it is mere borrowing of on-the-street intelligence of High School teachers and the Maker movement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;p&gt;As stated, one of the sidegoals was to enable anyone to do this, and for anyone to create trust with anyone else, without necessarily going through a central authority (like that provided by my Coursera course). For this purpose, I selected some articles to help guide students on what might build trust across cultural divides, such as &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.featureshoot.com/2013/03/photos-of-children-from-around-the-world-with-their-most-prized-possessions/"&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;, which clearly echoes the emotional response I was referring to earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what happened with &lt;em&gt;Massive Teaching&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, despite my best efforts it turns out that the fact that Coursera owned the channel was still &lt;em&gt;massively&lt;/em&gt; important. I might have made sure I owned all the content, and diluted as much as possible all ambient brands, I still needed Coursera for its reach (or at least I felt I did!). Going through them was not a smart way to challenge the general status quo in MOOCs, but the interesting paradox of #massiveteaching is that ultimately it is not the content that went missing, but rather the human (me, the instructor). The content was instead reinstated (well, actually only partially and with questionable motives), and I was unable to access the sources anymore, thereby losing some of my own content. This paradox was then compounded by further issues of trust and disinformation, where again access to communication channels was crucial. This account of course omits any of the students' perspectives, which must have been wildly different, depending on the activities they actually engaged in. With the instructor gone, only disaster was possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id5" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html#id1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;He apparently himself was troubled by Mike Wesch's &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f_mcTLlG_wg&amp;amp;feature=youtu.be"&gt;fantastic talk&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;em&gt;Why we need a why&lt;/em&gt; (just making the chain of trust explicit here, as explained in the talk...)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id6" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html#id2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Judging from aggregate and individual feedback, that was achieved.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id7" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html#id3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;This echoes a parallel effort in academic publishing in some disciplines. Indeed, the refereeing process, which is a form of  authority and power, is done double-blind, to prevent reinforcement of biases. In mathematics the author of a submitted paper is not anonymous to the referee, which is arguably a problem.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;table class="docutils footnote" frame="void" id="id8" rules="none"&gt;&lt;colgroup&gt;&lt;col class="label"&gt;&lt;col&gt;&lt;/colgroup&gt;&lt;tbody valign="top"&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="label"&gt;&lt;a class="fn-backref" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html#id4"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;td&gt;This in itself is very interestingly pain point. Can I use a DUPLO piece as a tool? I had &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dearrichblog.blogspot.ch/2014/05/cut-out-animations-moocs-and-copyright.html"&gt;to ask a lawyer for that&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;</description><category>connected_course</category><category>coursera</category><category>epfl</category><category>massive_teaching</category><category>mit</category><category>trust</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/building-trust-in-massiveteaching-through-visuals.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2014 11:38:58 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>