<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>paulolivier.dehaye.org (whyopen)</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/</link><description></description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2014 23:51:46 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Learning, working and ?</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/learning-working-and.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;A lot of my recent thoughts have turned around issues of crowdsourcing and online education.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="../worklearn.jpg" class="align-right" src="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/worklearn.jpg" style="width: 346.4px; height: 85.6px;"&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of my co-authors (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://hci.uni-hannover.de/people/markus"&gt;Markus Krause&lt;/a&gt;) is co-organising a workshop on that topic, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.worklearn.org/"&gt;WorkLearn 2014&lt;/a&gt;. It will take place in Pittsburgh November 2-4, as part of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.humancomputation.com/2014/"&gt;Human Computation conference HCOMP2014&lt;/a&gt;. Human Computation is another expression interchangeable for &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/social-teaching-machines.html"&gt;social machine&lt;/a&gt;, although it has different connotations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stated motivation of the workshop is very ambitious:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The online education and crowdsourcing communities are addressing similar problems in educating, motivating and evaluating students and workers. The online learning community succeeds in increasing the supply side of the cognitively skilled labor market, and the crowdsourcing at scale community creates a larger marketplace for cognitively skilled work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linking online platforms for crowd work with platforms for MOOCs has the potential to: provide knowledge and training at a massive scale to contributors; collect data that identify expert skills; engage contributors in simultaneously working and learning in a social environment; and organize large communities around online courses on specific topics. These all provide new opportunities to support and deploy sophisticated algorithms for crowd learning and work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most successful example in this direction is of course &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://duolingo.com"&gt;Duolingo&lt;/a&gt;, which helps translate the web while using volunteer labor by language learners. If one omits the learning, the strategy there is not that different from the strategy used by my Coursera coworker &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.coursera.org/instructor/bernstein"&gt;Abraham Bernstein&lt;/a&gt; to translate books using &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amazon_Mechanical_Turk"&gt;Amazon Mechanical Turk&lt;/a&gt;, and indeed part of his efforts aim to design effective tools to program those social machines (with the programming language CrowdLang).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;embed&gt;&lt;iframe width="640" height="360" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/emCABRV2cUA" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have always had some qualms about the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://florianschmidt.co/the-good-the-bad-and-the-ugly/"&gt;ethics of crowdsourcing&lt;/a&gt;, even though it can clearly be used for good: the prototypical success story is in the work of Ushahidi during the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ushahidi.com/blog/2012/01/12/haiti-and-the-power-of-crowdsourcing/"&gt;2010 Haiti earthquake&lt;/a&gt;. I was thus very happy to see over Labor Day 2014 that Michael Bernstein from Stanford announced &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://crowdresearch.org/blog/?p=9039"&gt;guidelines for academic requesters on Amazon Mechanical Turk&lt;/a&gt;. He explains the rationale for this (a Turker is a worker on a crowdsourcing platform):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
An IRB-approved researcher experimented on the [crowdsourcing] platform unannounced. The result was Turker confusion, strife, and wasted time, in a system where time is what it takes to make ends meet.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These guidelines were themselves crowdsourced, designed together with the Turkers (it's only natural!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the same time, over the summer, there was a huge controversy over the iffy ethics of social platforms experimentation. This is due to the release at the very end of June 2014 of a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/kashmirhill/2014/06/29/facebook-doesnt-understand-the-fuss-about-its-emotion-manipulation-study/"&gt;Facebook experiment on its users&lt;/a&gt; (don't miss the Cornell IRB flowchart there). There are a ton of links about this, but the best is probably the account by Mary L. Gray of an &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://marylgray.org/?page_id=203"&gt;ethics panel that took place at the Microsoft Research Faculty Summit&lt;/a&gt; (and unfortunately was published with much delay).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, this should give serious pause to any educator. One can see lots of fields suddenly getting much too close, with very different or inexistent values. Online learners, just as Turkers, are vulnerable. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://nogoodreason.typepad.co.uk/no_good_reason/2014/06/the-ethics-of-digital-scholarship.html"&gt;Martin Weller&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.elearnspace.org/blog/2014/01/13/the-vulnerability-of-learning/"&gt;George Siemens&lt;/a&gt; have recently insisted on this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what do you think? Anyone wants to submit a position paper (2 pages) on the topic? Any of my co-learners in MOOCs would like to see what we can do? We could, well... crowdsource it...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(of course, this was due yesterday: official deadline is "September")&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>connected_course</category><category>coursera</category><category>crowdsourcing</category><category>duolingo</category><category>ethics</category><category>t509massive</category><category>whyopen</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/learning-working-and.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2014 00:17:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>How fast the world has changed</title><link>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/how-fast-the-world-has-changed.html</link><dc:creator>Paul-Olivier Dehaye</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;As I am starting to blog, I am taking a course on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://schoolofopen.p2pu.org/"&gt;openness with P2PU&lt;/a&gt;. This is helping me think of how to quickly and most efficiently &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://opencontent.org/blog/archives/3393"&gt;reclaim my domain&lt;/a&gt;. For this, I have been looking back at the few notes I have posted around on Facebook. Actually, you can too if you have a Facebook account, as I have just made them &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.facebook.com/paulolivier.dehaye/notes"&gt;viewable to every facebook user&lt;/a&gt;. This way, if you are new here, you can get a quick sense of what I am about. Incidentally, due to a little known item in the Facebook &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.facebook.com/about/privacy/your-info-on-fb"&gt;privacy policy&lt;/a&gt;, this means that all the comments are now public as well (i.e. my friends gave the rights to their comments to Facebook, I gave the right to my original posts to Facebook, and finally Facebook decides to correlate privacy of comments to the privacy settings of the original post). I suppose every platform owner has to make lots of those decisions, which eventually shape the service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, one of the notes struck me. It was just a link, actually, to a 2008 &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://warner.blogs.nytimes.com/2008/12/04/first-the-bad-news/"&gt;New York Times story&lt;/a&gt; about an unfortunate Walmart employee who was trampled to death on Black Friday. The angle is that bad things happen in the world, and sometimes this can end up on the internet, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7aUwmsi6Wc0"&gt;filmed on crappy cell phone cameras&lt;/a&gt;. And then we have to tell kids about all that violence. The undertone of the piece is that we were just starting to grapple with that problem back then. A friend of mine commented and asked for my opinion. The original note is &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.facebook.com/notes/paul-olivier-dehaye/kids-are-scary-sometimes/103572210077"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, with a contemporary screenshot below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="../walmart.jpg" class="align-center" src="http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/walmart.jpg" style="width: 629.0px; height: 307.0px;"&gt;&lt;p&gt;Close to six years later, we are still facing the same problems, of course. Internet is more &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.mercurynews.com/business/ci_26459616/youtube-twitter-teamed-halt-spread-beheading-video-report"&gt;violent&lt;/a&gt; and more &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/emmawoollacott/2014/09/08/reddit-gives-mixed-messages-after-pulling-leaked-celebrity-photos/"&gt;invasive&lt;/a&gt; than ever. Any platform owner knows the value of good filters to curate content for its users. This content curation can be done jointly by machines and humans, leading to risks of algorithmic bias still misunderstood (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/dailymuse/2014/08/04/the-facebook-experiment-what-it-means-for-you/"&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://medium.com/message/the-algorithm-giveth-but-it-also-taketh-b7efad92bc1f"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;). It can also be done exclusively by humans, operating under strict rules. For both posts and comments. This is the model applied by &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.metafilter.com"&gt;metafilter&lt;/a&gt;, leading to high quality output but a relatively weak business model, unfortunately &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://gigaom.com/2014/05/22/if-a-high-quality-site-like-metafilter-can-be-crushed-by-google-what-hope-do-other-sites-have/"&gt;still vulnerable to algorithmic whims&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="epigraph"&gt;
&lt;dl class="docutils"&gt;&lt;dt&gt;So you're saying that people tried to use the economies of scale of the internet to disrupt the conventional and somewhat hidebound traditional methods and then it turns out that certain things requiring human eyeballs and judgment do not actually scale along with this stuff and the lesson is that you need to keep people in the mix in not just token ways even if this interferes with your bottom line...? I know that song!&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;-- Metafilter user and former moderator &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.metafilter.com/user/292"&gt;jessamyn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, eight years after this Facebook note, the world still turns around. People get married, have babies, raise their children. And most people still use Facebook.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>baby</category><category>facebook</category><category>metafilter</category><category>privacy</category><category>reclaim</category><category>violence</category><category>whyopen</category><guid>http://paulolivier.dehaye.org/posts/how-fast-the-world-has-changed.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2014 13:37:35 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>